<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/P4X/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
 <!ENTITY % TEI.prose 'INCLUDE'>
 <!ENTITY % TEI.names.dates 'INCLUDE'>
 <!ENTITY % TEI.figures 'INCLUDE'>
 <!ENTITY % TEI.XML 'INCLUDE'>
]>

<TEI.2>


<teiHeader>
	<fileDesc>
		<titleStmt>
			<title>Temple Bar: The City Golgatha.</title>
			<title> A narrative of the historical occurances of a criminal character associated with the present bar.</title>
			<author> James Holbert Wilson</author>
			<funder>Institute for Museum and Library Services</funder>
		</titleStmt>

		<editionStmt>
			<edition><date>2002-01-01</date></edition>
		</editionStmt>

		<extent>120320 bytes</extent>

		<publicationStmt>
			<distributor>Tufts University Digital Collections and Archives</distributor>
			<address>
				<addrLine>Tufts University</addrLine>
				<addrLine>35 Professors Row</addrLine>
				<addrLine>Tisch Library Medford, MA 02155</addrLine>
			</address>
			<idno>tufts:central:dca:UA069:UA069.005.DO.00033</idno>
			<availability status="free"><p>This publication is freely available for scholarly or

educational use.</p></availability>
		</publicationStmt>

  		<notesStmt>
			<note>This document was created from the 1853 printing of James Holbert Wilson's Temple Bar: The City Golgatha.</note>
		</notesStmt>

    		<sourceDesc>
			<biblStruct>
				<monogr>
				<title>Temple Bar: The City Golgatha.</title>
				<title> A narrative of the historical occurances of a criminal character associated with the present bar.</title>
				<author>Wilson, James Holbert</author>
				<imprint>
				<pubPlace>London: 86 Fleet Street</pubPlace>
				<publisher>David Bogue</publisher>
				<date>1853</date>
				</imprint>
				</monogr>
			</biblStruct>
		</sourceDesc>
	</fileDesc>

	<encodingDesc>
		<editorialDecl>
			<stdVals><p>Standard date values are given in ISO form:

yyyy-mm-dd.</p></stdVals>
			<interpretation><p>Page breaks are marked.</p>
			<p>Dates are marked.</p>
			<p>Personal names are marked.</p>
			<p>Place names are marked.</p>
			</interpretation>
			<hyphenation eol="none"><p>End of line hyphens have been
removed.</p></hyphenation>
<normalization method="tags">
<p>Footnotes originally numbered by page but for electronic version, footnotes are sequential throughout each section.</p>
</normalization>
		</editorialDecl>

		
		<refsDecl n="TOC">
			<state unit="chapter"/>
		</refsDecl>

		<classDecl>
		<taxonomy id="LCSH"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject

Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy>
		<taxonomy id="LC"><bibl><title>Library of Congress</title></bibl></taxonomy>
		</classDecl>
	</encodingDesc>

	<profileDesc>
		<creation><date>2000-01-01</date></creation>
		<langUsage><language id="EN" usage="99">English.</language>
		<language id="FR" usage="1">French.</language>
		<language id="LA" usage="1">Latin.</language>
					</langUsage>

			<textClass>
			<keywords scheme="LCSH">
			<list>
			<item>Temple Bar (London, England).</item>
			<item>Conspiracies--England--London.</item>
			<item>London (England)--History--17th century.</item>
			<item>London (England)--History--18th century.</item>
			</list>
			</keywords>
			<classCode scheme='LC'>DA 687.T19 </classCode>
		</textClass>
	</profileDesc>

	<revisionDesc>
		<change><date>2004-12-09</date><respStmt><name>Cynthia Mackey</name><resp>admin.</resp></respStmt><item>Updated text to TEI P4 XML. Added Tufts Digital Library object identifiers for figures.</item></change>
	</revisionDesc>


</teiHeader>

   <text>
<front>
	<titlePage>
		<pb id="p.i"  n="i"/>
		<figure id="fig.1" n="tufts:central:dca:MS004:MS004.002.009.DO01.00001"><head>Temple Bar as it appeared at the commencement of the 18th Century.</head></figure>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart type="main">TEMPLE BAR</titlePart>
			<titlePart type="sub">The City Golgotha</titlePart>
			<titlePart type="desc">A NARRATIVE OF THE HISTORICAL OCCURRENCES OF A CRIMINAL
			<lb/>CHARACTER ASSOCIATED WITH THE PRESENT BAR.</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
			<byline>BY<docAuthor>A MEMBER OF THE INNER TEMPLE.</docAuthor></byline>
		<epigraph><cit><q>I would we were all of one mind, and one mind good.-O! there were desolation
         of gaolers and gallowses!-</q><bibl>Cymbeline, Act V. Scene 4.</bibl></cit></epigraph>
         <docImprint>
   		<pubPlace>LONDON:</pubPlace><publisher>DAVID BOGUE,</publisher> <address><addrLine>86 FLEET STREET.</addrLine></address>
                      <docDate>MDCCCLIII</docDate>
          </docImprint>
<pb id="p.ii"  n="ii"/>
<figure id="fig.3" n="tufts:central:dca:MS004:MS004.002.009.DO01.00002"><head>Temple Bar in a scarce print in the possesion of the Author.</head></figure>
                  <docImprint>
                  	<pubPlace>LONDON:</pubPlace>
                  	PRINTED BY <publisher>G BARCLAY</publisher>, <address><addrLine>CASTLE ST. LEICESTER SQ.</addrLine></address>
                  </docImprint>
           </titlePage>
  </front>
<body>
<pb id="p.1"  n="1"/>

                <div1 type="chapter" n="PART I: From the Restoration of Charles II, 1660, to the Death of Queen Anne, 1714" id="c1">           <head type="main">PART I.</head>
    <head type="sub">FROM THE RESTORATION OF <persName key="Charles II.">CHARLES II.</persName>, <date value="1660">1660</date>, TO THE
                 DEATH OF <persName key="Anne I.">QUEEN ANNE</persName>, <date value="1714">1714</date>.</head>
<p><placeName key="TEMPLE BAR">TEMPLE BAR</placeName>,
the only survivor of the City bars and gates, has, on
many occasions, obtained no inconsiderable share of public attention.</p>
   <p>Placed between the liberties of the cities of London and
Westminster, it sets to each a limit.</p>
   <p>It stands alone-a monument of bygone days, an enduring record
of the power of the Crown, and of the passions of the people - a
memorial of a period when, to insure the security of the throne, the
terrors of the law were alone relied upon, and humanity and
compassion for human imperfections constituted no part of the criminal
jurisprudence of the country.</p>
   <p>Replete as this every-day scene is with reminiscences of the
past, we have considered that half an hour might not be
unprofitably employed in recalling some of those historical occurrences
with which it has been associated.</p>

<pb id="p.2"  n="2"/>



   <p>We have, however, no intention of indulging our readers with
antiquarian lore, of dwelling for one moment on its architectural
proportions.  Neither do we propose accompanying the herald in
those gorgeous processions to which, at the sound of his trumpet, its
gates have opened to admit the Sovereign, encircled by the chivalry
of the Court, within the most loyal of all cities, the good city of
London! <note place="foot" n="1">A work, we believe, is in the course of preparation by a gentleman
fully qualified for the task he has undertaken, which will embrace both these
subjects.</note>  <quote>"May peace be within her walls."</quote></p>
   <p>The historical occurrences to which our attention will be limited
are of a much less attractive character.  We have to contemplate
the frown, not the smile of royalty; to direct our attention from the
crowded thoroughfare to the gloomy summit of the arch, to behold
there in the vividness of mental vision what our forefathers, in the
distinct reality of form, were forced to regard-those livid heads
and dismembered limbs which, as terrible examples of hostile
resistance to the power of the throne, have from time to time been
affixed upon it. A practical commentary, illustrating in characters
of blood the words of Solomon,-<quote>" Curse not the king, no not
in thy thoughts; and curse not the rich in thy bedchamber: for
a bird of the air shall carry the voice, and that which hath wings
shall tell the matter."</quote></p>


<pb id="p.3"  n="3"/>


   <p>If, from the contemplation of this mournful subject, any
suggestions should arise having a tendency yet further to ameliorate
the criminal institutions of our country, to render them still more
in accordance with the improved feelings of the great community
in which we are living, we shall reflect with much pleasure on
the time we have passed near the City Bar.</p>
   <p>Old London Bridge, the southern entrance to the metropolis,
had for many centuries been considered a locality advantageously
adapted, from its public position, for striking terror into the hearts
of the rebellious, by the display of the lifeless heads of those who
had fallen under the severity of the laws-laws ruthlessly
administered, and carried into execution with a barbarity the conception
of which it is difficult at the present day to realise.<note place="foot" n="2">In the reign of Edward IV. Thomas Burdet, Esq., of Arrowe, in
Warwickshire, was beheaded for having used a coarse expression, the application
of which had been erroneously applied to the person of the king. In the same
reign, a tradesman, who kept a shop at the sign of the Crown, having said he
would make his son heir to the Crown, this harmless pleasantry was
interpreted to be spoken in derision of Edward's assumed title, and he was
condemned and executed for the offence.
   In the reign of <persName key="Henry VIII.">Henry VIII.</persName>, April 5, <date value="1531">1531</date>, Richard Rose, a cook, was
boiled to death in Smithfield, for poisoning several persons in the family of the
Bishop of Rochester ; an <foreign lang="LA">ex post facto</foreign> act had been passed for this express
purpose. Margaret Davy subsequently, on March 17, <date value="1541">1541</date>, suffered a similar death in Smithfield, <quote>"for poisoning three households that she had
dwelled in."</quote>
   This Act was repealed in the following reign. Burning females to death,
however, continued, within the memory of the present generation, to be
inflicted by the law for the crimes of high and petty treason. For the latter
crime, the last to suffer in London was Catherine Hayes, burnt to death at
<placeName key="Tyburn">Tyburn</placeName>, May 9, <date value="1726">1726</date>, for the murder of her husband; for the former,
Catherine Murphy, for colouring a piece of metal to resemble a
shilling made high treason by the 15th and 16th <persName key="George II.">George II.</persName> c. 28-was burnt in the
Old Bailey, on the 18th March, <date value="1789">1789</date> ; by the humanity of the sheriff, she
was, however, first strangled. By the 30th Geo. III. c. 48, this barbarous
mode of punishment was abolished, and hanging substituted.</note></p>
   <p>The head of the Scottish patriot, <persName key="Wallace, William">Wallace</persName>, and, subsequently,


<pb id="p.4"  n="4"/>



the heads of Sir <persName key="More, Thomas">Thomas More</persName> and <persName key="Fisher, John">Fisher</persName>, bishop of Rochester,
had, amidst many others of scarcely inferior note, graced, not
disgraced, the stern battlements of the Drawbridge Tower.</p>
    <p>The restoration of <persName key="Charles II.">Charles II.</persName> to the throne-in whose reign
our narrative commences-had been accompanied by little
amendment either in the criminal law or practice of the country; with
few exceptions, the same severe enactments continued on the statute
book; the same means as those adopted in the days of the
Plantagenets and Tudors were still deemed essential to punish treason,
or to deter from its commission.</p>
    <p>It was the misfortune of <persName key="Charles II.">the king</persName>, on his arrival in England,
to receive from all classes of his subjects the most servile adulation.
Endeared to them by the recollection of his past adversities, no

<pb id="p.5"  n="5"/>


measures, however humiliating, were neglected to convince him
of their sincere contrition for their former rebellious conduct. The
clergy hastened to place his dethroned and beheaded father in the
martyrology of the saints; the legislature, to decree that the day on
which the <quote>"Sons of Belial"</quote> had imbrued their hands in his blood
should ever after be observed as a day of solemn fasting and
humiliation; and the lower orders, frantic with loyalty and the
wine running from the conduits, <quote>"to throw up their caps, and cry
<quote>' God save his Majesty.'</quote>"</quote></p>
   <p>In this excited state of feeling an Act was passed, by which
the judges who condemned the deceased monarch, and some
others who had taken a leading part in the civil commotions of
the last reign, were excluded from an indemnity which exempted
from punishment many who had been less actively engaged in
the stirring events of that period.</p>
   <p>For this exception the nation were indebted more to the
clemency of the Crown than to the merciful disposition of the
Parliament.</p>
   <p>By the operation of this Act, several of the persons we have
mentioned were soon afterwards tried, condemned, and executed,
and their heads affixed, in terrorem, on London Bridge.</p>
   <p>That the sword of justice should descend on those alone
whose lives had been prolonged to this period, was, however,
<pb id="p.6"  n="6"/>



deemed an insufficient expiation for the crimes that had been
committed.</p>
   <p>Death had kindly removed three of the principal actors from
the scene--<persName key="Cromwell, Oliver">Cromwell</persName>, <persName key="Bradshaw, John">Bradshaw</persName>, and <persName key="Ireton, Henry">Ireton</persName>.
The graves were now searched for their dead bodies, and upon their discovery,
fast passing into decay, they were torn from the tomb, and,
amidst the jeers and scoffs of the rabble, borne to the gallows
at <placeName key="Tyburn">Tyburn</placeName>.    On the evening of the same day their bodies were
decapitated and buried in a deep hole under the gallows, and
their heads placed aloft on <placeName key="Westminster Hall">Westminster Hall</placeName>.<note place="foot" n="3"><quote>" The bodies of the three usurpers, viz. <persName key="Cromwell, Oliver">Cromwell</persName>, <persName key="Bradshaw, John">Bradshaw</persName>, and <persName key="Ireton, Henry">Ireton</persName>,
after an industrious search, were found on Sunday last. Thereupon they
(except <persName key="Bradshaw, John">Bradshaw</persName>, who, on account of the offensive state of his body, could
not be immediately removed) were taken out of the graves. On the evening
of the 23d January, <dateRange from="1660" to="1661">1660-1</dateRange>, all of them were brought out into a public-house
in Holborn, and shown to any one who desired to see them; and in the
course of the following Wednesday, being the 30th January, on which his
majesty's father, of excellent and blessed memory, was murdered, the
abovementioned bodies were conveyed in their open coffins to <placeName key="Tyburn">Tyburn</placeName> (a place where
the worst criminals and thieves are hanged); the bodies were then taken out
of the coffins, and hanged on the gallows. <persName key="Cromwell, Oliver">Cromwell</persName> was wrapped in a green
shroud, <persName key="Bradshaw, John">Bradshaw</persName> in a coloured, and <persName key="Ireton, Henry">Ireton</persName> in a white cloth; it was a fine
day, and the sun shone as warm as in summer, and made <persName key="Cromwell, Oliver">Cromwell</persName>'s fat so
scorched that no one could stand by on account of the offensive smell. They
were again in the evening removed, their heads cut off, and the bodies buried
under the gallows. Subsequently their heads were placed on
<placeName key="Westminster Hall">Westminster Hall</placeName>."</quote>-News from London of the 4th February, <date value="1661">1661</date>. Translated from the
scarce original in Dutch.</note></p>
   <p>These acts of vindictive justice had scarcely terminated, when
the office of the executioner was again called into requisition, to
mete out condign punishment on a band of insane adventurers,
who sought to overthrow the  government of <persName key="Charles II.">Charles</persName>, and to

   <pb id="p.7"  n="7"/>


establish in its place one of a most wild and visionary
character.</p>
    <p>We allude to the Millenarians, or Fifth Monarchy men. These
enthusiasts, led on by Venner, who believed himself commissioned
by Heaven to proclaim the advent of the Prince of Peace, committed
the most frightful excesses.</p>
    <p>The truth of the assertions they had boldly made, that <quote>"no
weapons formed against them should prosper,"</quote> <quote>"no hair of their
heads be touched,"</quote> was shortly to be tested in the most
satisfactory manner, by the execution, in different parts of the City
of London, of the leader and his misguided associates. Venner
was executed in Coleman Street, at the commencement of the
year <date value="1661">1661</date>.    Their heads were placed along with those of the
regicides on London Bridge.<note place="foot" n="4">Thomas Venner was a wine-cooper, and acquired a competent estate
by his trade. He was so strongly possessed of the notions of the
Millenarians, or Fifth Monarchy men, that he expected Christ was coming to reign
upon earth, and that all human government, except that of the saints, was
presently to cease.
   He looked upon <persName key="Cromwell, Oliver">Cromwell</persName> and <persName key="Charles II.">Charles the Second</persName> as usurpers upon Christ's
dominion, and persuaded his weak brethren that it was their duty to rise
and seize upon the kingdom in his name. Accordingly a rabble of them,
with Venner at their head, assembled in the streets, and proclaimed King
Jesus. They were attacked by a party of the militia, whom they resolutely
engaged, as many believed themselves invulnerable. They were at length
overpowered by numbers, and Venner and Roger Hodgkin, a button-seller
in St. Clement's Lane, Lombard Street (another fanatic), were executed before
their meeting-house in Swan Alley, Coleman Street, in the City, on the 19th
January, <date value="1661">1661</date>. On Monday the 21st nine more were executed, at five several
places, by one executioner; two at the west end of St. Paul's, two at the
Bull and Mouth, two at Beech Lane, two at the Royal Exchange, and a notable
fellow, the last, by name Leonard Gowler, at Bishopsgate. Their heads were
placed upon London Bridge.</note></p>



<pb id="p.8"  n="8"/>



   <p>These were the last destined to be placed there.  On future
occasions, when the right to dispose of the quartered remains of
the subject devolved on the Crown, that right, as regards those
who had suffered for high-treason in London, was, with few
exceptions, wholly or partially exercised in favour of
<placeName key="Temple Bar">Temple Bar</placeName>.</p>
   <p>Thus the City Bar became the City Golgotha.<note place="foot" n="5">The erection of the present bar commenced in the year <date value="1670">1670</date>, and was
completed in <date value="1672">1672</date>. The design is stated to be by Sir <persName key="Wren, Christopher">Christopher Wren</persName>.</note></p>
   <p>Afflictive as was the criminal jurisprudence of the country at
this period, it was rendered still more so by the irregular manner


<pb id="p.9"  n="9"/>




in which it was administered.  <soCalled>" Reasons of state,"</soCalled> rather than
the acknowledged principles of law, influenced the decisions of the
courts. Judges dependent for the duration of their office on the
pleasure of the Crown, made it their pleasure, by slavishly obeying
its mandates, to prolong their tenure of office, and thus degrade
the character of the judicial bench-a bench over which the
inhuman <persName key="Jeffreys, George">Jefferies</persName> presided, whose natural element seemed to be amidst
death and destruction: his most joyous moments those in which
he sent a patriot to the block, or rejected, with a coarse, unfeeling
jest, the last heartbroken supplication for mercy or justice.</p>
   <p>Suspicion, conviction, and execution, ever constituted an unholy
trinity in the mind of this judge.</p>
   <p>We are convinced, that no language we can employ can
adequately depict the character of one who has left so foul a blot
on the judicial records of the country; we shall, therefore, abandon
the attempt, and proceed at once with our narrative to those
occurrences of the year <date value="1683">1683</date>, in which he took so prominent and so
atrocious a part.</p>
   <p>In the summer of the year we have named, the discovery of
a real or pretended conspiracy to assassinate <persName key="Charles II.">the King</persName> on his return
from the races at <placeName key="Newmarket">Newmarket</placeName>, and to alter the form of Government,
commonly known as the Rye-House Plot, evinced the most
unscrupulous determination on the part of the Crown and of the
<pb id="p.10"  n="10"/>


Chief Justice to proceed against those upon whom scarcely a shadow
of implication could rest, with a relentless severity of purpose,
and a total disregard of the principles of law or of justice.</p>
   <p>The sole object of the Government being the conviction of
the accused, the law was to be made, by strained interpretation, the
instrument to effect that end. The mockery of a trial might have
been, in all instances, and actually was in one, dispensed with.
This unconstitutional course, while it inflicted an indelible stigma
on the Government, greatly elevated the character of its victims.</p>
   <p><persName key="Russell, William">William Lord Russell</persName>, eldest son of the noble house of Bedford,
had displayed the heroic character of a patriot on the scaffold in
<placeName key="Lincoln's Inn Fields">Lincoln's Inn Fields</placeName> - <persName key="Sidney, Algernon">Algernon Sidney</persName> had prayed for his
murderers on Tower Hill--Holloway had been hurried from the West
Indies to the triple tree at <placeName key="Tyburn">Tyburn</placeName>-- when the last remaining
victim, Sir <persName key="Armstrong, William">William Armstrong</persName>, was delivered up to the English
Government by the payment of a large bribe, and transferred from
a foreign soil to the common gaol of <placeName key="Newgate">Newgate</placeName>. His history-being
the first associated with the criminal records of <placeName key="Temple Bar">Temple Bar</placeName>
-we
shall, in accordance with the plan we have formed, proceed to give
more at length.</p>
   <p>Sir <persName key="Armstrong, Thomas">Thomas Armstrong</persName>, descended from an ancient and loyal
family, was born at Nimeguen, in Holland.  As he advanced in
years, he discovered a vigorous, martial disposition, and possessed
<pb id="p.11"  n="11"/>




a warm heart and a good head. During the exile of <persName key="Charles II.">Charles II.</persName>,
his strong royalist predilections rendered him  obnoxious to the
Protector, <persName key="Cromwell, Oliver">Cromwell</persName>, who confined him a whole year in Lambeth
House,<note place="foot" n="6">This palace of the Archbishops of Canterbury was during the
Commonwealth converted into a prison.</note> at that time a prison. Fortunately, however, he recovered
his liberty, and the usage he had received not having abated his
loyalty, he undertook the hazardous service of conveying to his
majesty, at Brussels, bills of exchange and other papers of great
importance.  This he executed so much to the satisfaction of the
King, that he conferred upon him the honour of knighthood.  On
his return, however, <persName key="Cromwell, Oliver">Cromwell</persName>, who had received intelligence of
this journey, seized and sent him to the Gatehouse, <note place="foot" n="7">Gatehouse: Tothill Street; Westminster, is so called from two gates
erected there in the reign of <persName key="Edward III.">Edward III.</persName> Here is a prison for debtors and
criminals.--<hi rend="italics">London and its Environs, by Dodsley.</hi></note> where he
again suffered a lengthened imprisonment.  Subsequently he was
confined in <placeName key="the Tower of London">the Tower</placeName>, and regained his liberty only on the death
of the Protector. <persName key="Charles II.">Charles II.</persName>, on his return, received him into great
favour, promoted him to the rank of lieutenant in one of the troops
of Horse Guards, and conferred upon him the honourable post of
Gentleman of the Horse to his Majesty.  An unfortunate quarrel
at the theatre, in which a person of some importance, of the name


<pb id="p.12"  n="12"/>




of Scroop, was killed, rendered it expedient for him to leave the
kingdom. This he was enabled to do as an attendant on <persName key="Charles II.">the king</persName>'s
natural son, the Duke of Monmouth.  He served with him in
Flanders, and acquired a high military reputation, and was held
in much esteem by the friends of the Duke. On the termination
of the war he returned to England, and, to all appearance, was as
high in favour and credit with the court as ever.</p>
   <p>This prosperity was of short duration; for, owing to the unsettled
state of the country, and the violent factions which agitated society,
he had the misfortune to countenance such measures as at first
occasioned his removal from office, and, ultimately, his dismissal
from the court.  We may trace the ruin of <persName key="Armstrong, Thomas">Sir Thomas</persName> to his
long and friendly intercourse with the Duke of Monmouth. The
known vigour of his mind, and the constancy of his attachment
to the person of the Duke, caused him invariably to be regarded
as his principal adviser.  In connexion, however, with the Rye
House Plot,-to which period we have now brought his
history,no other positive proof could be adduced than the solitary one of his
having been present at a meeting, at a Mr. Sheppard's, towards the
latter end of October, <date value="1682">1682</date>, when, in conversation, a design of a
<soCalled>"rising "</soCalled> in Dorsetshire had been mentioned. This was considered
sufficient evidence to complete the ruin of the fallen favourite; and
every imaginable pains were taken to secure his person. For a
<pb id="p.13"  n="13"/>



time, however, from having received notice of the intention of the
Government, he was enabled to elude their vigilance, and after
having been concealed for some time in England, he withdrew to
Holland, where, under the assumed name of Henry Lawrence, he
trusted to continue safe from the pursuit of his enemies.</p>
   <p>The King's minister, Mr. Chudleigh, in the mean time, having
obtained a warrant from the States for apprehending such of the
conspirators as had fled from  England, Sir William was taken
at Leyden, and, for a present of 5000 guilders (about 5001.) to
the schout, or sheriff of the place, delivered to the King's minister,
who placed him on board a royal yacht, and sent him to England.
He neglected, probably owing to his confusion, to plead being a
native of Holland; which, had he done, there is little doubt,
would have ensured his safety.</p>
   <p>During his absence, an indictment had been preferred against
him, in London, for high treason, upon which he had been outlawed.
On his arrival, the Government resolved to proceed against him
upon this outlawry, without allowing him the benefit of a trial.
On the 10th of June, therefore, the day on which he reached
London, he was committed to <placeName key="Newgate">Newgate</placeName> under a warrant from the
Secretary of State, and on the 14th of the same month was carried
to the King's Bench at Westminster, when the Attorney General,
Sir Robert Sawyer, moved the Court for an award of execution
<pb id="p.14"  n="14"/>


upon the outlawry. The scene that followed between the prisoner
and the Chief Justice (the inhuman <persName key="Jeffreys, George">Jefferies</persName>) is of a character too
remarkable to be slightly passed over.  The Clerk of the Crown
having arraigned him upon the outlawry, Sir <persName key="Armstrong, Thomas">Thomas Armstrong</persName>
addressed the Chief Justice:
   <quote>"My lord, I was beyond seas at the time of the outlawry,
and beg I may be tried.</quote>
   <quote>" <hi rend="italics">Lord Chief Justice.</hi> That is not material at all to us; we have
here a record of an outlawry against you, <persName key="Armstrong, Thomas">Sir Thomas</persName>.</quote>
   <quote>"<hi rend="italics">Sir <persName key="Armstrong, Thomas">Thomas Armstrong</persName>.</hi> I desire to be put upon my trial,
my lord.</quote>
   <quote>"<hi rend="italics">Lord Chief Justice.</hi> We cannot allow any such thing; we have
nothing to do upon this record before us but to award execution.
Captain Richardson, which are your usual days of execution?</quote>
    <quote>"<hi rend="italics">Captain Richardson.</hi> Wednesdays and Fridays, my lord."</quote></p>
    <p>Sir <persName key="Armstrong, Thomas">Thomas Armstrong</persName> having afterwards called the attention
of the Chief Justice to an Act made in the sixth year of Edward VI.,
which allowed a party a twelvemonth to surrender to an
outlawry, contended that that period had not expired. In doing
this he was repeatedly interrupted by the Chief Justice, who
manifested the greatest impatience to pronounce sentence upon him;
and <persName key="Armstrong, Thomas">Sir Thomas</persName> having finally urged that he should have the
benefit of the law, <quote>"That you shall have,"</quote> jeeringly exclaimed
<pb id="p.15"  n="15"/>




the Chief Justice, <quote>"by the grace of God; see that execution be
done on Friday next, according to law: you shall have the full
benefit of the law."</quote></p>
   <p>Thus terminated a proceeding, alike disgraceful to the judge
that pronounced and to the sovereign that could permit such a
sentence to be carried into effect.</p>
   <p>We now approach the closing scene of his varied life.  On
the 20th of June, about nine in the morning, he was placed on
a sledge, and, attended by the sheriffs and a numerous guard,
conducted from <placeName key="Newgate">Newgate</placeName> to <placeName key="Tyburn">Tyburn</placeName>.   On his way, he employed
his time in reading the <quote>" Whole Duty of Man,"</quote> and having reached
the appointed place, he laid aside the book, and requested that
Dr. Tennison might be permitted to come near him, to whom he
delivered a paper for the sheriff, and knelt down with him for a
few minutes. He then resigned himself, with perfect composure of
mind, into the hands of the executioner.  After hanging about
half-an-hour, he was cut down, and, pursuant to his sentence, his
heart and bowels were taken out and committed to the flames, his
body divided into four parts, which, with his head, were conveyed
back to <placeName key="Newgate">Newgate</placeName>, to be disposed of according to his majesty's
pleasure, and were afterwards publicly exposed. His head being
set up upon <placeName key="Westminster Hall">Westminster Hall</placeName>, between those of <persName key="Cromwell, Oliver">Cromwell</persName> and
<persName key="Bradshaw, John">Bradshaw</persName> (note, p. 6), one of the quarters upon <placeName key="Temple Bar">Temple Bar</placeName>,

<pb id="p.16" n="16"/>

two others on Alsdersgate and Aldgate, and the fourth was sent
down to Stafford, which Borough he had represented in
parliament.</p>
	<p>Shortly after this event, when <persName key="Jeffreys, George">Jefferies</persName> had an interview with
the King at Windsor, <persName key="Charles II.">Charles</persName> took from his finger a diamond
ring of great value, and gave it to him; this ring was ever after
called the <soCalled>"bloodstone."</soCalled>  His majesty prudently added this advice,
to be careful not to grink too much wine on credit.  The attention
the Chief Justice paid to this recommendation, let the <soCalled>"Bloody
Assizes"</soCalled> testify.<note place="foot" n="8">The assizes held by the Chief Justice <persName key="Jeffreys, George">Jefferies</persName> in the West of England in
the year <date value="1685">1685</date>, after the defeat of Monmouth, which for cruelty and infamy
are unparalleled in the criminal records of the country, and which  obtained
for them the epithet of <soCalled>"bloody."</soCalled>  The historian Hume thus describes
them:--<quote>"The juries were so struck with his (Jeffries) menaces, that they
gave their verdict with precipitation; and many innocent persons, it is said,
were involved with the guilty.  And on the whole, besides those who were
butchered by the military commanders, 251 are computed to have fallen by
the hand of justive.  The whole country was strewed with the heads and
limbs of traitors.  Every village almost beheld the dead carcase of a wretched
inhabitant.  And all the rigours of justice, unabated by the appearance of
clemency, were fully displayed to the people by the inhuman Jeffries."</quote>--
<hi rend="italic">History of England</hi>, 8vo. vol.viii.p.233.</note></p>
	<p><persName key="Charles II.">Charles the Second</persName> was of an indolent and selfish disposition,
but was, when uninfluenced by others, neither vindicative nor ungenerous.

<pb id="p.17" n="17"/>
The following anecdote, forming an agreeable contrast
to the cruel, repulsive character of the Chief Justice, will show
that, unlike the judge, he occasionally possessed some sense of
moral right and justice.</p>
	<p>A report of the condemned malefactors being once made to
him, one mobleman interceded for one, another for another, until
they were all pardoned excepting one.  The <persName key="Charles II.">King</persName>, looking round
upon the council, asked of them if nobody would speak in behalf
of this man?  They all keeping silence, his majesty said, <q type="spoken">"Cod's
fish, My lords!  this is some poor devil who has, I suppose, neither
money nor friends: come, I'll be his friend myself!"</q> by which
they were all saved.  And it turned out afterwards, to his majesty's
great consolation, that the man whom he had pardoned by his
own royal motive proved an object more worthy of compassion
than any of the others.</p>
	<p>They who have hitherto believed, with the witty Rochester,
that <persName key="Charles II.">Charles</persName> never did a wise act, may, perhaps, be now
inclined to modify that opinion; so far, at least, as to allow him the credit
of wisdom in the one instance we have just narrated.</p>
	<p>Twelve years elapsed before the Bar had another occupant.</p>
	<p>In that interval great events had taken place--the House of Stuart
had ceased to reign.  The brutal <persName key="Jeffreys, George">Jefferies</persName> having with difficulty
escaped the fury of of the mob at Wapping, had sought the


<pb id="p.18"  n="18"/>


protection afforded in <placeName key="the Tower of London">the Tower of London</placeName>; there disease and
drunkenness speedily terminated a life of vice and infamy.
<persName key="William III.">William the Third</persName> had ascended the throne, not as a conqueror, but
by express compact with the nation.  Reciprocity of ties were
claimed and admitted as existing between the Crown and the
people. Constitutional liberty, trampled upon by the Tudors and
the Stuarts, revived with the House of Orange, and
henceforward became the acknowledged imperishable right of every
Englishman.</p>
   <p>Amidst this improved position of affairs there were, however,
some who, from interest or affection, maintained their attachment
to the fallen house. By the treaty of Limerick, in <date value="1691">1691</date>, <persName key="James II.">James</persName>
had lost all footing in the British dominions, and hope alone
remained to him-the equal privilege of majesty and misery. On
his return, however, to the Continent, intrigues were, both in
England and Scotland, carried on in his favour. These intrigues
received encouragement from the French ministry, who, although
they had suspended all open attempts in his favour, scrupled not
to employ the most atrocious means to promote his cause.
Assassination was resorted to. Chevalier de Granvale, taken in the
confederate camp in Flanders, in <date value="1692">1692</date>, having confessed the charge,
was speedily hanged; 2000 livres, and the Cross of St. Lazare,
were to have been the reward of his villany.</p>
<pb id="p.19"  n="19"/>




   <p>Notwithstanding this discouragement, three years afterwards,
in the year <date value="1695">1695</date>, a new plot was discovered at London; the
object being to carry off the King (as it was expressed) on his
return from Richmond, where he usually hunted on Saturdays.
<note place="foot" n="9">The place selected was a marshy bottom
between Brentford and Turnham Green, by which road the king used
to return to <placeName key="Kensington">Kensington</placeName> from Richmond, very slightly guarded.</note>
Sir George Barclay, a warm adherent to the house of Stuart,
had the chief direction of this conspiracy, in which about forty
were engaged. Fortunately, however, the hope of reward, or the
timidity of some of the subordinate actors, frustrated their
diabolical purpose. On the 14th February, <date value="1695">1695</date>, Thomas
Pendergrast revealed the whole scheme to the Earl of Portland; and
La Rue, on the same day, did the like to Brigadier Leveson.
The Government adopted the most vigorous measures to secure
the conspirators.  Several, however, suspecting their plans had
failed, had already withdrawn from danger.  In this number was
Sir George Barclay; others, less fortunate, were captured. Robert
Charnock, a Fellow of Magdalen College, was the first to suffer;
and, shortly afterwards, Sir <persName key="Friend, John">John Friend</persName> and Sir <persName key="Parkins, William">William Parkins</persName>
were placed on their trials before Chief Justice Holt, at the Sessions
House in the Old Bailey. This took place on the 23d and 24th
of March, <date value="1696">1696</date>.</p>


<pb id="p.20"  n="20"/>


     <p>We must, however, pause for a few  moments, in order to
 take some notice of the two last-named parties, who, as they
conspired together in life, in death were not to be far separated;
 the head and limbs of one, and the headless trunk of the other,
 being the next ornaments <placeName key="Temple Bar">Temple Bar</placeName>
 received.</p>
    <p>Sir <persName key="Friend, John">John Friend</persName>, from an humble position, had, by industry
and perseverance, arisen to considerable wealth and credit, and
had enjoyed, during the last reign, a lucrative situation in the
Excise.   He was, at the time of his death, the proprietor of a
large brewery near Tower Hill.<note place="foot" n="10">The brewery, after the death of Sir Thomas Friend, was taken by the
notorious swindler Joseph Crook, alias Sir Peter Stranger, Bart. He was the
last person tried and convicted under the statute of the 5th Elizabeth, c. 14,
entitled <quote>"An Act against Forgers of false Deeds and Writings."</quote> The instrument
he had forged was the will of a Mr. Thomas Hawkins, and having been found
guilty, the sentence provided by the statute was carried into effect.  On
June 10, <date value="1731">1731</date>, he stood in the pillory at Charing Cross, and the common
hangman cut off his ears and slit up his nostrils and seared them. He was
then in his 70th year. The 2d George II. c. 25, recently passed, made this
offence felony; and Richard Cooper, a victualler at Stepney, was the first
person (in London) to suffer the new penalty, for the forgery of a bond of 25&#x00A3;.
in the name of Holme, a grocer in the neighbourhood of Hanover Square.
This execution took place at <placeName key="Tyburn">Tyburn</placeName>, on Wednesday, June 16, <date value="1731">1731</date>.</note>  He had always remained
faithful to the interest of <persName key="James II.">James</persName>, and his purse was ever at his
service.  To his wealth, however, rather than to his abilities,

<pb id="p.21"  n="21"/>



he was indebted for the consideration he received.   He readily
entered into the proposed plans of invasion; and so soon as <persName key="James II.">James</persName>
should have effected a landing, with a force sufficient to give a
probability of success, had engaged to join him with 2000 horse.
This appears to have been the extent of his criminality: he
repudiated all idea of assassination, nor, in fact, was this aggravation
of his offence alleged against him, no count in the indictment
charging him with it.</p>
    <p>Sir <persName key="Parkins, William">William Parkins</persName> was also a gentleman of property, and
had warmly espoused the interests of the Stuarts. He had been
educated to the profession of the law, and, during the last reign,
had received the valuable appointment of one of the Six Clerks
in Chancery; rather than lose which he had, on the accession of
<persName key="William III.">William</persName>, taken all the oaths to the Government.  <note place="foot" n="11">As regards the moral obligation of an oath, Sir William would appear to
coincide with Sir Hudibras:-
               <quote rend="blockquote">"He that made and forced it broke it,
                 Not he that for convenience took it."</quote>
                                   <hi rend="italics">Hudibras</hi>, Part II. Canto 2, p. 275.</note>He was not
only a consenting party to the design of assassination, but had
promised to bring five men to assist in it.</p>
   <p>The names of these parties, to the last moment of his life, he
firmly refused to reveal to the Government, declining to save his

<pb id="p.22"  n="22"/>




own life by the sacrifice of his associates: a redeeming trait in a
character otherwise darkened by many vices.</p>
   <p>The jury at once found them guilty, and the usual sentence
was passed upon them as traitors.</p>
   <p>The following account of their execution is extracted from the
newspaper of the day:-</p>
   <p><quote>"Yesterday being the 3d of April, Sir <persName key="Parkins, William">William Parkins</persName> and
Sir <persName key="Friend, John">John Friend</persName> were drawn in a sledge from <placeName key="Newgate">Newgate</placeName> to <placeName key="Tyburn">Tyburn</placeName>,
where they were hanged and quartered. They had books in
their hands the whole way, and <persName key="Friend, John">Sir John</persName> seemed more penitent
than <persName key="Parkins, William">Sir William</persName>. They prayed very heartily, being assisted by
three non-jurant ministers, Mr. Cook, Mr. Collier, and Mr. Snatt:
they both confessed a knowledge of the plot.  Sir <persName key="Parkins, William">William Parkins</persName>
was observed several times to smile in the sledge, and seemed to
take much notice of the spectators.  Sir <persName key="Friend, John">John Friend</persName> confessed
having heard of the assassination, but that he abhorred it.</quote></p>
   <p><quote>"When they came to the press-yard, <persName key="Friend, John">Sir John</persName> said to Sir
William, <quote>' We shall soon be in a glorious state.'</quote> At the gallows,
before the cart was drawn away, they kneeled down, and the
three ministers<note place="foot" n="12"><quote>" Collier, Snatt, and Cook, three non-jurant clergymen, waited on them at
<placeName key="Tyburn">Tyburn</placeName>, and the three at the place of execution joined to give them public
absolution, with an imposition of hands, in the view of all the populace,
though they died avowing the evil doings in which they had been engaged,
and expressing no sort of repentance for them.
   "For this offence Cook and Snatt were committed to <placeName key="Newgate">Newgate</placeName>, Collier
absconded. The dispute lasted some time, but they were ultimately released."</quote>
--History of the Reign of <persName key="William III.">William</persName>.</note> laid their hands on their heads, and so they
went off."</quote></p>



<pb id="p.23"  n="23"/>



   <p>The quarters of Sir <persName key="Parkins, William">William Parkins</persName> and Sir <persName key="Friend, John">John Friend</persName>,
together with the head of the former, were placed on <placeName key="Temple Bar">Temple Bar</placeName>.</p>
   <p><persName key="Evelyn, John">Evelyn</persName>, in his <quote rend="blockquote">"Diary,"</quote> referring to this melancholy scene,
remarks,-<quote>" A dismal sight, which many pitied.  I think there
never was such a <placeName key="Temple Bar">Temple Bar</placeName>
 till now, except once in the time
of King <persName key="Charles II.">Charles the Second</persName>, viz. Sir <persName key="Armstrong, Thomas">Thomas Armstrong</persName>."</quote></p>
   <p>The head of Sir <persName key="Friend, John">John Friend</persName> was set up on Aldgate; on
account, it is presumed, of that gate being in the proximity of
his brewery.</p>
   <p>Pendergrast, the principal discoverer of the plot, received from
<persName key="William III.">the King</persName> a present of 3000&#x00A3;. in money; an annuity of 500&#x00A3;. was
likewise settled upon him and his heirs, and he had also conferred
upon him a colonel's commission in the army.</p>
   <p>Nearly the last person to suffer on account of this conspiracy
was Sir <persName key="Fenwick, John">John Fenwick</persName>, of Fenwick Castle, in the county of
Northumberland, a man of considerable talent but of a restless
disposition, and who, twenty years previously, had commanded a

<pb id="p.24"  n="24"/>




regiment in the service of <persName key="William III.">William the Third</persName>, when Prince of
Orange.  His history, excepting that he was a participator in
the crime of those whose limbs were then exposed, is not
associated with <placeName key="Temple Bar">Temple Bar</placeName>;
as, after his decapitation on Tower
Hill, on January 23, <date value="1697">1697</date>, his remains were removed to the
Church of St. Martin-in-the-Fields, and there deposited in the
family vault. We merely take notice of him, as, by a
remarkable coincidence, the death of <persName key="William III.">William</persName> was not altogether
unassociated with the execution of this northern baronet.</p>
   <p>The partiality of <persName key="William III.">the King</persName> for his palace at Hampton Court
is well known; and in the improvement of the gardens he had
projected a new canal, near that which is at present in existence.
On the morning of February 21, <date value="1702">1702</date>, he rode into the Home
Park to inspect the progress of the work, and was mounted on
a sorrel pony, which had formerly been the property of the
unfortunate Sir <persName key="Fenwick, John">John Fenwick</persName>.</p>
   <p>His Majesty having reached the spot where the operations
were being carried on, the pony accidentally placed his foot in
a mole-hill, and fell.  <persName key="William III.">the King</persName>'s collar-bone was fractured by
the fall, and having been removed first to Hampton Court Palace,
and subsequently by his desire to <placeName key="Kensington">Kensington</placeName>, he expired after
much suffering, on the morning of Sunday, the 8th day of March,
<date value="1702">1702</date>, in the fifty-second year of his age, and the thirteenth of
<pb id="p.25"  n="25"/>




his reign. The adherents of <persName key="James II.">James</persName> eulogised their beloved
<soCalled>"Sorrel ;"</soCalled> and the wit of Pope was shown in the following <foreign lang="FR">jeu d'esprit</foreign>,
contrasting the safety of <persName key="Charles II.">Charles</persName> in the oak at Boscobel, with the
accident to <persName key="William III.">William</persName> in the gardens at Hampton:-

            <quote rend="blockquote">"Angels, who watched the guardian oak so well,
            How chanced ye slept when luckless Sorrel fell ?"</quote></p>

   <p>In breathless haste-the historian informs us-the courtiers
hastened from the palace to announce to <persName key="Anne I.">Anne</persName> her exaltation to
the throne.</p>
   <p>We must now resume our narrative. With the peace of
Ryswick, in <date value="1697">1697</date>, ended all attempts in favour of the exiled
<persName key="James II.">king</persName>, who, from ambition, turned his attention to religion, trusting
to secure a heavenly crown as a recompense for the loss of his
earthly one; and in the practice of the austerities of an ascetic
course of life, he died of a lethargy, at St. Germains, July 6, <date value="1701">1701</date>,
at the age of sixty-eight, and was buried in the English Benedictine
monastery at Paris. As we have seen, a few months subsequent to
this event, <persName key="William III.">William the Third</persName> had expired at <placeName key="Kensington">Kensington</placeName>. <persName key="Anne I.">Anne</persName>,
the second daughter of <persName key="James II.">James</persName> by his first wife, the daughter of the
great Lord Clarendon, by virtue of the Act of Settlement ascended
the throne, and was speedily engaged in continental wars to check
the power of France; Louis the Fourteenth having, by a family

<pb id="p.26"  n="26"/>



marriage, connected the crown of Spain with the House of Bourbon.
The Peace of Utrecht, in <date value="1713">1713</date>, effected this object, and, moreover,
compelled Louis to send James Francis Edward, the son of the
late exiled <persName key="James II.">monarch</persName> (who had been openly acknowledged by him by
the title of James the Third), out of his dominions. If we except
an abortive effort to land troops in Scotland, the reign of Queen
<persName key="Anne I.">Anne</persName> passed over without any open attempt to disturb her throne,
and she had the good fortune not to be called upon to execute the
rigour of the laws on any of the supporters of her family.</p>
  <p> After a reign of nearly thirteen years, made glorious by the
victories of Marlborough, the <persName key="Anne I.">Queen</persName> breathed her last at
<placeName key="Kensington">Kensington</placeName>, on the 1st day of August, <date value="1714">1714</date>, and was, on the 24th
of the same month, buried in <persName key="Henry VII.">Henry the Seventh</persName>'s chapel in
Westminster Abbey.</p>
   <p>The herald proclaimed over her tomb her earthly titles; to
which the nation, in affection for her memory, added another, by
which she has been generally distinguished-that of the good
<persName key="Anne I.">Queen Anne</persName>.</p></div1>
<pb id="p.27"  n="27"/>



<div1 type="chapter" n="PART II: From the Accession of the House of Hanover, 1714, to the Thirteenth Year of the Reign of George III, 1772" id="c2">

                          <head type="main">PART II.</head>
 <head type="sub">FROM THE ACCESSION OF THE HOUSE OF HANOVER, <date value="1714">1714</date>, TO THE
     THIRTEENTH YEAR OF THE REIGN OF GEORGE III., <date value="1772">1772</date>.</head>
<p><hi rend="cl"><persName key="George I.">GEORGE THE FIRST</persName></hi> had no sooner ascended the throne than the
slumbering embers of loyalty to the exiled family burst again into a
flame, and many of the Scotch, as also of the English nobility,
openly declared for <persName key="Stuart, James Francis Edward">the Pretender</persName>; by which name the heir of that
family was now called. His standard was raised in Scotland; but
divided councils and hesitation at the moment when the greatest
unanimity and decision were requisite, combined with other causes,
for which we must refer the reader to the historians of that period,
rendered all their attempts abortive. A very considerable force,
however, penetrated as far as Preston in Lancashire, which town
surrendered to them without offering any resistance.
Notwithstanding this success, the leaders of <persName key="Stuart, James Francis Edward">the Pretender</persName>'s forces,
satisfied of the inutility of continuing longer the contest, (the <persName key="George I.">King</persName>'s
<pb id="p.28"  n="28"/>



troops having been reinforced in the night), resolved at once to
capitulate, without having further recourse to arms-a resolution the
brave Highlanders resented as cowardly-and declared themselves
ready to make a sally, sword in hand, and either cut their way
through the <persName key="George I.">King</persName>'s troops or perish in the attempt.  This was
overruled, and <persName key="Stuart, James Francis Edward">the Pretender</persName>'s force surrendered at discretion. All
the noblemen and leaders were secured. Some were immediately
tried by a court-martial, and executed; whilst others, among them
Lords Derwentwater, Kenmuir, and other officers of distinction,
were sent to London, marched through the streets, pinioned like
malefactors, and committed to <placeName key="the Tower of London">the Tower</placeName> and other metropolitan
prisons.  It may be interesting to have from an eye-witness-a
prisoner at the time in <placeName key="Newgate">Newgate</placeName>-some account of this mournful
procession.</p>
   <p><quote>"The day now was come,"</quote> he observes, <quote>"when those
unfortunate noblemen and gentlemen who, by a surrender at discretion,
had entertained vain notions of saving life and estate, were to be
led in triumph, as an example to deter other incautious and rash
persons from the like attempt, through crowds of spectators to
their respective prisons, which the Government had appointed to
be <placeName key="the Tower of London">the Tower of London</placeName>, the Marshalsea Southwark, <placeName key="Newgate">Newgate</placeName>,
and the Fleet.  Wherefore all things being prepared for them,
especially in that mansion-house where my ill stars obliged me
<pb id="p.29"  n="29"/>



to take up my abode, I got leave of the Governor thereof to take
a view of them as they came through the gate, from a room over it
on the master's side. And here it may not be from the purpose
of an historian to say, that the respective prisoners, in their journey
from Preston to London, having been used with the utmost civility
and decency, according to their qualities, on their arrival at
Highgate were to know what they were to expect; which, indeed, was
no more than the laws of our own, and the common practice of
other nations, in like cases authorised and allowed.</quote></p>
   <p><quote>"Accordingly, Major-general Tatton, with two battalions of
the Royal Foot Guards, completely armed, attended their coming
to the place just mentioned; and having brought cords sufficient
to pinion each of them, after the fashion of condemned criminals,
and to lead their horses with (since, from the lord to the footman,
they were to have every one a grenadier for that end), they were
ordered to proceed on their march in four divisions from the Hill,
under safe conduct, to their several places of confinement.</quote></p>
   <p><quote>"The Major-general led the way (being preceded by several
citizens of more loyalty than compassion, who made repeated huzzas
to excite the mob to do the like), at the head of a company of
the First Regiment of Guards, who made a very fine appearance;
after which came the divisions that were appointed to take up
their abode in <placeName key="the Tower of London">the Tower</placeName>, two by two. The Earl of Derwentwater
<pb id="p.30"  n="30"/>


and Lord Widdrington in the first rank, and the other lords and
noblemen following, with haltered horses, and their riders, like
common malefactors, reviled and hooted."</quote></p>
   <p>Robert Dalziel, earl of Carnwath, and William Gordon lord
Kenmuir, upon the same authority, occupied the third rank. The
gates of the gloomy fortress had scarcely been closed on these
unfortunate noblemen, than they were to be again opened to deliver
over to the sheriffs the youthful Earl of Derwentwater and the
more aged Lord Kenmuir, who, having been impeached by the
House of Commons, had pleaded guilty to the articles exhibited
against them, and on the 24th of February, <date value="1716">1716</date>, were, by the
forfeiture of their lives, to pay the penalty of their misplaced
zeal and loyalty to the son of their former sovereign. The loss
of these noblemen was deeply felt in the north, where their estates
were situated. By their bounty the poor and needy had been fed,
and to them the widow and the fatherless had never appealed in
vain for protection.  In expressing commiseration, however, for
their fate, let us not forget the admonition contained in the words
of one of the greatest ornaments of the judicial bench, Judge Hale,
who was accustomed to remark, <quote>" When I find myself inclined to
pity a criminal, let me remember there is likewise a pity due to
the country."</quote></p>
   <p>Forming a part of the melancholy procession we have described
<pb id="p.31"  n="31"/>



were those destined to be confined in the prison of <placeName key="Newgate">Newgate</placeName>. In
this number were Colonel Henry Oxburg and Richard Gascoign.
Of the former we have to take some notice, as his head was shortly
to be placed on the top of <placeName key="Temple Bar">Temple Bar</placeName>
.</p>
   <p>Colonel Henry Oxburg, previous to the year <date value="1715">1715</date>, had resided
on his property in Lancashire, and from his attachment to the
cause of <persName key="Stuart, James Francis Edward">the Pretender</persName> had, immediately on the breaking out of
the rebellion, joined his forces in the north.   Whilst serving in
the French army some years prior to this event, he had acquired
a distinguished character for his gallant conduct, and was by
General Forster,<note place="foot" n="1"> General Forster had been confined in <placeName key="Newgate">Newgate</placeName>, with several of the
prisoners taken at the surrender of Preston. The following account of the
manner in which he effected his escape is taken from the diary of a prisoner
confined in the same prison with him:-
   <quote>"April 10, <date value="1716">1716</date>.-Mr. Forster abused the liberty which was allowed him
by Governor Pitt,<note place="foot" n="2">Mr. Forster and Mr. Anderton, another prisoner for the same offence, paid 5&#x00A3;.
a-week each for their lodging and diet in the Governor's house.</note> and made his escape as follows :-His servant had taken an
impression in wax of the key of the outer door, and got one made accordingly.
While Forster and Anderton were drinking French wine with Mr. Pitt, Forster
sent his own man for a bottle of his own wine to make up the treat, and on
pretence of going to the vault, he went out of the room. The fellow, according
to order, had locked up Mr. Pitt's black in the cellar, as he went down with
him to bring up the bottle, and then stayed at Mr. Pitt's outer door until
Forster came, and both went out together, having locked the door on the
outside, and left the false key in the lock to prevent them being suddenly
pursued. They got to Prettlewell, in Essex, next morning by four o'clock,
with two more horsemen that were ready to attend them, and having a vessel
provided at Leigh went over to France."</quote>-<hi rend="italics">Secret History of the Rebels in
<placeName key="Newgate">Newgate</placeName></hi>, <date value="1716">1716</date>.</note> who held the chief command in <persName key="Stuart, James Francis Edward">the Pretender</persName>'s
army, immediately made a colonel. To him had been consigned
the humiliating task of proposing the capitulation of Preston.



<pb id="p.32"  n="32"/>



We have already recounted the brief, and to them disastrous, issue
of this campaign. On the 9th of May he was placed on his trial
at Westminster, before Chief Justice Parker, on the charge of
high treason; and the jury, considering the evidence produced
conclusive of his guilt, returned a verdict to that effect. Pursuant
to his sentence, he was, on the 14th of the same month, executed at
<placeName key="Tyburn">Tyburn</placeName>; his body was buried in the churchyard of St. Giles-
inthe-Fields, and his head placed upon <placeName key="Temple Bar">Temple Bar</placeName>. This was on
the 16th of May, <quote>"which is a circumstance,"</quote> remarks a writer
of the day, <quote>"which we chose to mention, that the rebels may
place it among their other saints' days."</quote> He met death without
the slightest trepidation, and had attained such a remarkable serenity
and temper of mind during his imprisonment, that when, in the
language of one who had frequent opportunities of conversing with
him, <quote>"he declared his sentiments, they seemed to glide in upon

<pb id="p.33"  n="33"/>



you like a gleam from the true God: you received comfort from
the man you came to comfort."</quote></p>
   <p>Richard Gascoigne shortly followed his friend and companion
to the grave, having been executed at <placeName key="Tyburn">Tyburn</placeName> the 25th day of
May, <date value="1716">1716</date>.  He was likewise buried in the churchyard of St.
Giles-in-the-Fields.</p>
   <p>It forms no part of the plan of this narrative to trace, step
by step, the history of these troubled times, except so far as may
be sufficient to elucidate either the history of the Bar or the
biographical notices of those connected with it.  We shall, therefore,
not enlarge on the fate of many consigned to an ignominious death,
whose youth, and consequent inexperience of the world, might
justly have pleaded for a mitigation of the capital punishment;
<note place="foot" n="3">James Shepperd, executed for high treason at <placeName key="Tyburn">Tyburn</placeName>, the 17th March,
<date value="1718">1718</date>, at the age of eighteen.
   John Matthews, a printer, for printing and publishing a seditious libel,
executed at the age of nineteen, at <placeName key="Tyburn">Tyburn</placeName>, November 6, <date value="1719">1719</date>.</note>
but <persName key="George I.">George the First</persName> knew little of the English people, and
clemency formed no part of the policy of his ministers. They
sought to govern by the fear, and not by the affection, of the
nation.  Tower Hill and <placeName key="Tyburn">Tyburn</placeName> had already witnessed the closing
scenes of many of the supporters of the former family, and yet
the same disaffection to the existing Government remained,-still

<pb id="p.34"  n="34"/>


more victims were to be offered up as peace-offerings; and it was
only at length by the extinction of the House of Stuart, in the
direct line, that the Crown was quietly to rest with the House of
Hanover.</p>
   <p>Such poor supporters of a cause are the axe and the rope!</p>
   <p>To a young and enthusiastic mind, an enterprise fraught with
danger, difficult of accomplishment, and having a chivalrous issue,
will always prove a powerful attraction, successfully to resist which
will not only demand that the duty and obedience which every
citizen owes to the laws of his country should be ever present in
his mind, but that these obligations should be enforced by the
principles derived from religion and reason.</p>
   <p>Of such a character was the cause of <persName key="Stuart, James Francis Edward">the Pretender</persName>: an exile
from his infancy from the kingdom over which his ancestors had
ruled-dispossessed of that throne which, for nearly a hundred
years, <note place="foot" n="4"><persName key="James I.">James the First</persName> of England, and the Sixth of Scotland, ascended the
throne of England March 24, <date value="1603">1603</date>. <persName key="James II.">James</persName> the Second abdicated that same
throne, by leaving the country, December 23, <date value="1588">1588</date>.
   If, however, we include in our calculation the period of their occupation of
the throne of Scotland, we should extend the sovereignty of the House of
Stuart to upwards of three hundred years.</note>they had occupied-for no fault committed by him, for
no crime that could be alleged against him.</p>

<pb id="p.35"  n="35"/>


   <p>The nation, by the Act of Settlement, had visited the sins of
the father upon the children.  That they had a clear right to do
so, will always be maintained by those who hold that the sentiments
of the majority must in all cases be binding and conclusive on the
rest of the community.  To reason otherwise would, in this instance,
be to revive the doctrine of the <quote>"right divine of kings to govern
wrong,"</quote> which has long since been consigned to that <soCalled>"Limbo"</soCalled>
described by <persName key="Milton, John">Milton</persName>, to serve as an amusement to <quote>"the eremites
and friars, white, black, and grey,"</quote> who, according to the same
authority, are to be found there.<note place="foot" n="5">
<quote rend="blockquote"> "Eremites, and friars
           White, black, and grey, with all their trumpery.
           All these, upwhirl'd aloft,
           Fly o'er the backside of the world far off,
           Into a Limbo large and broad, since called
           The Paradise of Fools."</quote>- <persName key="Milton, John">Milton</persName>'S <hi rend="italics">Paradise Lost</hi>, book iii.</note></p>
   <p>Strongly imbued with feelings of the enthusiastic character we
have described, was <persName key="Layer, Christopher">Christopher Layer</persName>, who trusted alone to effect
that change which, as we have seen, armies in the field had failed
to accomplish. We shall proceed to give our readers some
information relative to this individual, whose head frowned from the
summit of the arch for a longer period than any other occupant.</p>
   <quote><persName key="Layer, Christopher">Christopher Layer</persName> was descended from an honourable family,
and after having completed his education at the University of


<pb id="p.36"  n="36"/>


Cambridge, was admitted a student of the Inner Temple. Having
kept the requisite number of terms, he was called to the Bar,
and from the large practice he speedily obtained, and his high
reputation and abilities, would have risen to fame and fortune,
had not the political tendency of his principles, and his
intercourse with females of disreputable character, entirely blasted
these prospects, and consigned him shortly to ruin and a
dishonourable grave.</quote>
   <quote>In the early part of the year <date value="1722">1722</date>, Francis Atterbury, the
witty Bishop of Rochester, had been arrested on suspicion of
treasonable practices and confined to <placeName key="the Tower of London">the Tower</placeName>, and upon his
trial, shortly afterwards, before the House of Commons, on a Bill
of Pains and Penalties, had been found guilty by a large majority,
and banished the kingdom for life, and at the same time disabled
from holding his preferments in the Church.</quote>
   <quote>The example given by this eminent divine was closely
followed by <persName key="Layer, Christopher">Layer</persName>, who proceeded to Rome, then the residence of
<persName key="Stuart, James Francis Edward">the Pretender</persName>, and had several conferences with him, in which
he engaged, on his return to England, to effect a revolution in
so secret a manner that no one in authority should be apprised
of the scheme until its actual accomplishment.</quote>
   <quote>Full of these chimerical notions, lie returned to England, and
formed the dastardly plan of hiring an assassin to murder the
<pb id="p.37"  n="37"/>




King as he returned from <placeName key="Kensington">Kensington</placeName>.   This being effected, the
guards were to be seized, and, during the confusion that this
event would naturally produce, the   chief officers of state and
the royal children were to be secured.</quote>
   <quote>It is difficult to conceive how any person of the penetration
and abilities of <persName key="Layer, Christopher">Layer</persName> could, for one moment, believe in the
practicability of a scheme so wild and dangerous. He had, however,
induced Lord Grey, an aged nobleman of the Roman Catholic
faith, to give his concurrence to it.  Fortunately, the death of
this nobleman in confinement, before the necessary legal
proceedings could take place, obviated, in all probability, the sad spectacle
of a public execution on Tower Hill.</quote>
   <quote><persName key="Layer, Christopher">Layer</persName> now entered into a correspondence with several Roman
Catholics, Non-jurors, and other persons disaffected to the
Government; and likewise engaged the assistance of a few disbanded
soldiers, who were to be the chief instruments in carrying the
plot into execution.  These soldiers he met at a public-house at
Stratford, in Essex, when he finally gave them their instructions
for seizing the King on his return from <placeName key="Kensington">Kensington</placeName>, and the day
was even fixed for carrying their plan into execution.</quote>
   <quote>Secret as may have been the concoction of this scheme, it
was not sufficiently so to ensure its accomplishment.  The
treasonable conversation had been overheard by some persons connected
<pb id="p.38"  n="38"/>



with the house, who had spoken of it publicly in the
neighbourhood. Suspicion immediately fell upon <persName key="Layer, Christopher">Layer</persName>. His known
predilection to the cause of <persName key="Stuart, James Francis Edward">the Pretender</persName>, combined with other
circumstances, induced the Secretary of State at once to issue a
warrant, by virtue of which he was taken into custody. Mention
has been made of his attachment to women: at the time of his
apprehension he had two mistresses, to both of whom   he had
given intimation of the proposed scheme. On searching their
apartments, many papers of a treasonable character were found. On
this being communicated to the Counsellor, and also that the women
were bound over to give evidence against him, he sent to the
Secretary of State, expressing his readiness to disclose all the
particulars of the conspiracy, if he were indulged with the
requisite materials for writing.</quote>
   <p>No time was lost in complying with this requisition, and had
he fulfilled the promise he had made, he would, in all
probability, have been admitted as evidence against his accomplices.
At that moment, however, his mind was engaged on a very
different project. The back-yard of the house in which he was
confined communicated with the yard of the adjoining
publichouse; and it occurred to the fertile brain of Mr. <persName key="Layer, Christopher">Layer</persName>, that
if he could descend from  his room into this yard, he should
find it a very easy matter to escape through the tap-room,
<pb id="p.39"  n="39"/>



where there was very little probability of his being
recognised.</p>
   <p>This plan he determined to carry, if possible, into execution;
he cut, therefore, the blankets of his bed into long pieces, and
fastened them together, and in the dusk of the evening descended
from his window; unfortunately, however, he fell upon a bottle-rack
in the yard, and upset it, and the noise occasioned by the breaking
of the bottles was such that it alarmed the family. <persName key="Layer, Christopher">Layer</persName>,
however, amidst the confusion which ensued, effected his escape. An
active search was instantly commenced by the almost distracted
messenger, who, tracking him to the Horseferry at Westminster,
where he had taken a boat, crossed the water after him, pursued
him through St. George's Fields, and ultimately succeeded in
recapturing him at <placeName key="Newington">Newington</placeName>. <persName key="Layer, Christopher">Layer</persName> was now again lodged in
the messenger's house, and securely guarded for the night. The
next day he underwent an examination by the Secretary of State,
and was committed to <placeName key="Newgate">Newgate</placeName>. The Government having decided
that no delay should take place in bringing him to trial, a grand
jury was at once empannelled at Romford, in Essex, by a warrant
from  the Sheriff, who found a true bill against him for high
treason; which bill was made returnable into the Court of King's
Bench.</p>
   <p>Wednesday, the 21st of November, was the day appointed
<pb id="p.40"  n="40"/>



for the trial of <persName key="Layer, Christopher">Layer</persName>.  The Lieutenant of <placeName key="the Tower of London">the Tower</placeName> brought
him  up to the bar of the Court, and upon a motion made by
Mr. Hungerford (who, together with Mr. Ketilby, had been
appointed his counsel), the Lord Chief Justice, Sir John Pratt,
ordered his irons to be removed. Every point that could be urged
in favour of the prisoner was, with much talent and pertinacity,
pressed on the attention of the Court, and on the termination of
a trial which lasted upwards of sixteen hours, the jury, after a
short consultation, returned a verdict of guilty.</p>
   <p>In order that he might have time to arrange his own affairs,
as also the affairs of his clients, his execution was postponed for
many months after his condemnation; doubtless it was also expected
that disclosures would be made by him relative to his
accomplices, and to this we may partly attribute the numerous reprieves
he received. At length, on the 17th of May, nearly seven months
after his trial at Westminster, he was conducted from <placeName key="the Tower of London">the Tower</placeName>
to <placeName key="Tyburn">Tyburn</placeName>, seated in a sledge, habited in a full-dress suit, and a
tie-wig. On taking leave of Colonel Williamson, the
Deputygovernor of <placeName key="the Tower of London">the Tower</placeName>, he told him he intended to die like a
man: to which the Colonel replied, <quote>"And, he hoped, like a
Christian."</quote>  At the place of execution he openly declared his
adherence to King James (as he called <persName key="Stuart, James Francis Edward">the Pretender</persName>), and
advised the people to take up arms on his behalf; he professed
<pb id="p.41"  n="41"/>




 himself willing to die for the cause, and expressed his confidence
 that Providence would effectually support the right heir to the
 throne on some future occasion, though he had failed of being
 the happy instrument of placing him upon the throne.</p>
    <p>The streets were never more crowded than on this occasion,
 and many fatal accidents occurred from  the breaking down of
 the stands erected to accommodate the spectators anxious to
witness the last moments of Counsellor <persName key="Layer, Christopher">Layer</persName>, as he was familiarly
 named.</p>
    <p>The day subsequent to his execution, his head was placed on
 <placeName key="Temple Bar">Temple Bar</placeName>
; there it remained, blackened and weatherbeaten
 with the storms of many successive years, until, as we have
remarked, it became its oldest occupant.  Infancy had advanced
 into matured manhood, and still that head repulsively looked
 down from   the summit of the arch.   It seemed part of the
 arch itself.</p>
   <p>It was not, however, alone during the latter part of its
occupancy. Battles had again been fought for that cause for which
<persName key="Layer, Christopher">Layer</persName>, on dying, had expressed so warm an attachment; defeats
had again been sustained by its friends. Once more the axe and
the rope, the fire and the fagot, had been busy, and two
additional heads had been borne from  Kennington Common to the
City Bar, there to convey, by their cold, apathetic gaze, to the
<pb id="p.42"  n="42"/>



passers along that great thoroughfare, a lesson more powerfully
instructive on the vanity and hollowness of all human
expectations, than could fall from the lips of the most eloquent
preacher.</p>
   <p>We, however, must not anticipate the <quote>" Rising of '45,"</quote> but must
proceed, in order not to interrupt hereafter the thread of this
narrative, at once to give some further account of the head of
the unfortunate Counsellor.</p>
   <p>For upwards of thirty years it had remained fixed on the
summit of the arch: at the close of that period, the elements
accomplished what the improving taste of the public had in vain
demanded.</p>
   <p>On one stormy night, a summary ejectment was served, and
the head of <persName key="Layer, Christopher">Layer</persName> left its long resting-place, and descended from
the arch into the Strand. We shall extract from Mr. Nicholl's
<quote>"Literary Anecdotes of the Eighteenth Century,"</quote> the sequel of
this curious history.  <quote>"When the head of <persName key="Layer, Christopher">Layer</persName> was blown
from <placeName key="Temple Bar">Temple Bar</placeName>,
it was picked up by a gentleman in the
neighbourhood (Mr. John Pearce, an attorney), who showed it to some
persons at a public-house, under the floor of which, I have been
assured, it was buried. Dr. Rawlinson, meanwhile, having made
inquiries after the head, with a wish to purchase it, was imposed
upon with another instead of <persName key="Layer, Christopher">Layer</persName>'s, which he preserved as a
<pb id="p.43"  n="43"/>



valuable relique, and directed it to be buried in his right hand."</quote>
<note place="foot" n="6"><quote>"On April 5, <date value="1755">1755</date>, died Richard Rawlinson, LL.D. and F.R.S., and one of
the first promoters of the Antiquarian Society. He was the third son of Sir
Thomas Rawlinson, lord mayor of London, <date value="1706">1706</date>. By his will he ordered his
body to be buried in a vault in St. Giles's Churchyard, Oxford, and his heart
in St. John's College, as a mark of his affection.
   A few days subsequently died Mr. Benjamin Bourn, author of <quote>'The Sure
Guide to Hell ;'</quote> a young man of the most promising expectations."</quote>-<hi rend="italics">Gent.
Mag</hi>. vol. xxvi.</note>We learn from another source that this request was complied
with.</p>
   <p>We shall have now to pass over several years, during which
the supporters of the doctrine of indefeasible hereditary right made
no open attempts to promote the cause of the exiled house; and
it is to some extent gratifying to remark, that it was owing alone
to the result of these misguided principles that, with the solitary
exception in the reign of <persName key="Charles II.">Charles the Second</persName>, we have any
criminal associations with the Bar to which this history relates.</p>
   <p>Scotland had suffered deeply from the effects of the Rebellion of
<date value="1715">1715</date>, and from   its disastrous issue it might have been presumed
that any renewed attempt would have found no encouragement
there. Pandora's box had been opened, and its contents poured
over the length and breadth of that devoted country; fire and
sword had wasted her hills, and in many parts her valleys wanted


<pb id="p.44"  n="44"/>




the labourer to cultivate them.  Still hope remained, and this was
shortly to reillumine the torch of civil war, to obliterate the
recollections of past sufferings, and to lead on the devoted adherents
of <persName key="Edward, Charles">Charles Edward</persName>, from their victory at Carlisle to their defeat
at Culloden.</p>
    <p>We must, however, be very brief in our relation of these events
<quote>-"the Rising of '45,"</quote> as it has been usually designated; we are
chiefly interested in its results, and those results of a very restricted
character.  After the reduction of Carlisle, on November 15, <date value="1745">1745</date>,
<persName key="Edward, Charles">Charles Edward</persName>, with his little army, advanced towards the south.
<placeName key="Lancaster">Lancaster</placeName> was taken, Preston surrendered, Manchester was
occupied, Derby opened its gates to him; and, previous to his effecting
that retreat to the north which, for talent and abilities, will bear
favourable comparison with any recorded in ancient or modern
history, he had advanced within one hundred miles of the
metropolis. When the news of this success reached London,
consternation was seen in every face. In hot haste the citizens left their
homes, to form   armed associations; the Warder stood on the
Tower wall with his match lighted, ready to give the appointed
signal of the approach of the enemy; a solemn fast was proclaimed,
and, like Israel of old, the nation, in humiliation and sorrow, bowed
down to Israel's God.</p>
    <p>The Battle of Culloden was fought.  A great victory was
<pb id="p.45"  n="45"/>


achieved, the enemy was prostrate, the vanquished were suppliants
for mercy. We shall presently see how a Christian nation, who,
on every Sunday in their churches, had besought the God of
mercy <quote>"to show pity on all prisoners and captives,"</quote> applied this
divine petition to those who, by the fortune of war, were now
placed in their power.  The plea of mercy--so far at least as to the
sparing of their lives-should never have been urged with greater
success than in the case before us. <note place="foot" n="7"><quote>"The benefit which is hoped from terror, for the future, appertains not
to the giving of a right to kill. For a more obstinate affection to one's own
side, if the cause is not altogether dishonourable, deserves not punishment;
or if there is any punishment thereof, it ought not to amount to death, for an
equal judge would not so determine."</quote>-GROTIUS, <hi rend="italics">Law of Peace and War,</hi>
Part III. c. xlvii.</note> Here were misguided
men--rebels, if you please--whose crime (and a very grave one we will
allow it to be) was their maintaining their fidelity intact to a line
of kings to whom their ancestors had sworn fealty and obedience,
but whom the nation, in its wisdom, had excluded from the
succession to the throne.   May the tear of the Recording Angel
obliterate many of the dark pages in the history of our country!</p>
   <p>Mention has been made of the Battle of Culloden. This
decisive engagement was fought on the 16th of April, <date value="1746">1746</date>.  The
King's forces were commanded by William, duke of Cumberland,

<pb id="p.46"  n="46"/>


son of the reigning monarch.  The carnage was terrific; no
quarter was given, none expected.<note place="foot" n="8">It is stated that his royal highness, on viewing the field of battle on the
following day, was heard to exclaim, <q type="spoken">"Lord, what am I that I am spared,
when so many men lie dead on the spot !"</q> The severities practised
afterwards acquired for him, in Scotland, the appellation of <quote>" Billy the Butcher."</quote></note></p>
   <p>In one decisive hour the young Chevalier beheld his hopes
blasted, his family doomed to perpetual exile, and himself a fugitive
and a wanderer.<note place="foot" n="9"><quote>"The young Chevalier, after moving from place to place for nearly five
months, at the commencement of September, <date value="1746">1746</date>, escaped on board the
Heureux privateer of St. Malo, with several of his adherents, and landed on
the 29th at Roscart, near Morlaix, in Brittany, from whence he set out for the
Court of France."</quote>--<hi rend="italics">History of the Rebellion</hi>, <date value="1745">1745</date>.</note></p>
   <p>The unhappy Earl of Kilmarnock and Lord Balmerino were
among the prisoners whom this victory delivered over to the
Government, and were beheaded on Tower Hill, on the 18th
day of August, <date value="1746">1746</date>.</p>
   <p>The execution, however, of a few noblemen, the attainder of
others and confiscation of their property, were alone considered
inadequate to ensure the safety of the throne. The blood of a
whole hecatomb of victims was requisite to cement a fabric which
had been so rudely assailed. The King of Terrors, therefore, was
to hold his high court of justice; and before him were placed, in


<pb id="p.47"  n="47"/>



grim array, the only acknowledged reformers of this period-the
axe and the rope.  Had any one suggested milder measures, if
he escaped a prison for his presumption, he would have been
consigned to a lunatic asylum for his folly.</p>
   <p>The nation, in acquiring greatness, had omitted the lesson of
generosity.</p>
   <p>Special commissions for the trial of the unfortunate prisoners
were shortly opened in various parts of the country; and on the
23d of June, at a Sessions held for this purpose at St. Margaret's
Hill, in the borough of Southwark, <persName key="Townley, Francis">Townley</persName>, colonel of
the Manchester Regiment, and <persName key="Fletcher, George">George Fletcher</persName>, holding a captain's
commission in the same force, were, with several others, placed
on their trials, and convicted of high treason.  The awful sentence
awarded by the law was passed upon them.</p>
   <p>Before we proceed to the last sad scene of their lives, we must
give our readers some account of these brave and gallant men,
who, as they had stood undaunted amidst the blaze of battle,
blanched not at the fearful preparatives of death on the scaffold.</p>
   <p><persName key="Townley, Francis">Francis Townley</persName> was of an old and honourable family, who
had long resided in Lancashire, and whose descent may be traced
from the earliest periods of English history.</p>
   <p>His grandfather, an able cavalier, had fought and died for
King <persName key="Charles II.">Charles</persName> at the fatal battle of Marston Moor; his brother,
<pb id="p.48"  n="48"/>



John Townley, Knight of St. Louis, was tutor to the son of
<persName key="James II.">James</persName> the Second, the Chevalier St. George, and was known as
the translator of <hi rend="italic">Hudibras</hi> into French.<note place="foot" n="10"> We have taken the account of the family of Colonel Townley from a very
meritorious work, recently published by Peter Burke, Esq., of the Inner
Temple, called <quote>"The Romance of the Forum."</quote> From the near relationship
subsisting between that gentleman and the talented editor of the <quote>" Peerage,"</quote>
Mr. Bernard Burke, there is no doubt of its strict accuracy.</note></p>
    <p>His uncle, Mr. Townley, of Townley Hall, had been, to some
extent, implicated in the former rebellion (<date value="1715">1715</date>); and although
on his trial acquitted by a jury, was not thereby fully exculpated
in the opinion of the public.<note place="foot" n="11"><quote>"May 10, <date value="1717">1717</date>. Townley of Townley paid them (the rebels in <placeName key="Newgate">Newgate</placeName>)
a visit, with great pomp and splendour, after his discharge from the
Marshalsea, but he could not well expect that all of them should have the like
good fortune for the like causes, because he knew they had not so much
money.
   " May 23, <date value="1717">1717</date>. Mr. Townley came again to visit in great pomp."</quote>-<hi rend="italics">Secret
History of the Rebels</hi>, p. 38.</note></p>
   <p><persName key="Townley, Francis">Francis Townley</persName>, the subject of the present notice, entered
early in life into the service of France, and displayed, at the
siege of Phillipsburg, in <date value="1734">1734</date>, whilst serving under the command
of the Duke of Berwick, <note place="foot" n="12">The Duke of Berwick was the natural son of <persName key="James II.">James</persName> the Second by
Arabella Churchill.</note> a bravery and courage under the fire



<pb id="p.49"  n="49"/>




of the enemy, and an acquaintance so extensive with military
tactics, as raised him  at once in the esteem  of all those with
whom he was associated.</p>
   <p>It was at this siege, whilst visiting the trenches, that the
Duke of Berwick, of whom mention has been made, one of the
most experienced generals in the French service, was killed by
a cannon-ball.  <persName key="Townley, Francis">Townley</persName> was near him at the moment.</p>
   <p>For nearly sixteen years he remained abroad, serving with zeal
and fidelity in the armies of France, and acquiring for himself
increasing honour and military reputation.  Desirous, however,
of once more visiting a country which, amidst all the changes of
his life, was still first in his thoughts and affections, he returned,
about the year <date value="1740">1740</date>, to England, and quietly resided with his
family in Lancashire.  This tranquillity, however, was to be of
short duration.  The year '45 arrived; the son of him whom he
considered as his lawful sovereign had advanced to <placeName key="Lancaster">Lancaster</placeName>,
his banner waved over Preston.   <persName key="Townley, Francis">Townley</persName> was not one ever to
permit the probability of personal danger to interfere with the
discharge of what he considered a positive duty.  He, therefore,
immediately offered his services to the young Chevalier, which
offer was at once accepted, and a colonel's commission conferred
upon him. He quickly placed himself at the head of 200 men,
and entered Derby with the victorious army.  On the retreat to
<pb id="p.50"  n="50"/>



Scotland, lie was invested with the important post of Governor
of the town of Carlisle; and upon that place capitulating to the
Duke of Cumberland, on the 30th December, <date value="1745">1745</date>, he, and about
114 other Englishmen, were made prisoners of war, and confined
in the various prisons of the country.</p>
    <p>We must now take some notice of his faithful companion in
arms and misfortune, <persName key="Fletcher, George">George Fletcher</persName>, who had been brought
up at Salford, near Manchester, where his parents had resided, and
were substantial people. His father had been for some time dead;
but his mother, whose business he managed, was still living. So
enthusiastically was he attached to the cause of <persName key="Stuart, James Francis Edward">the Pretender</persName>,
that all her entreaties were fruitlessly exerted to induce him not
to join an enterprise, in her opinion, of so desperate a character:
with the affection of a parent, she even offered him <date value="1000">1000</date>&#x00A3;. to
follow her advice. So far from doing this, he gave Mr. Murray,
the Prince's Secretary, 50&#x00A3;. for a Captain's commission. He might,
with much truth, remark at a subsequent period, that to his own
obstinacy he could alone attribute the misfortunes that had befallen
him.</p>
   <p>At two o'clock in the afternoon of the 29th July, the fatal
warrant was forwarded from the Secretary of State's office for
the execution, on the following day, of these unfortunate men:
it found them chained to the floor of their cells. The communication
<pb id="p.51"  n="51"/>




was received with cheerfulness and resignation.  The only
expression that escaped their lips was, <quote>"God's will be done!"</quote>
That night they went to bed and slept soundly.</p>
   <p>The next morning, at ten o'clock, the sledges being in
readiness, each drawn by three horses, the mournful procession was
formed in the following order: first, a party of dragoons; next,
a party of foot-guards; the three sledges then followed, in the
first of which was placed Colonel <persName key="Townley, Francis">Townley</persName> and two others.  In
the front seat sat the executioner, with a drawn scimitar; and in
this manner they proceeded to Kennington Common.</p>
   <p>In the rear of the procession, in a street coach, followed one
who mourned in earnest; that one was a woman.     Her whole
feelings were concentrated in the fate of a being, the occupant
of one of those sledges,-young James Dawson.       His life was
hers: in agony she had watched his trial, had listened to his
condemnation, and in the dark frenzy of despair was now resolved
to witness his death.  Through the vast multitudes of human
beings which the event had collected, the procession moved on
to the Common-that coach followed: it drew up near to the
fatal spot--her head was extended from the window-she gazed
as those who see not. The rude hand of the executioner tore from
its bosom the heart which she fondly imagined had beat only for her,
and round which all her warm, womanly feelings were entwined.
<pb id="p.52"  n="52"/>



A  moment's consciousness returned: she beheld him throw that
heart into the fire.  One wild, hysteric shriek-one piercing,
agonising cry-and her gentle spirit ascended with his to the
Throne of Mercy.</p>
   <p>We trust we shall be excused for inserting this short but
mournful episode.  We must now proceed with our narrative.
<persName key="Townley, Francis">Townley</persName> was the first to suffer. The executioner performed his
mournful office, the knife was applied to the yet breathing body,
the head was severed from it, and, with the warm blood still gushing
from its unclosed veins, held up to the vulgar gaze of the
populace, and the God of Mercy was invoked to save King George!
A  murmur of approbation ran through that great assembly-a
shout of exultation rose to the skies-the crowd was chanting
its <hi rend="cl"><foreign lang="LA">TE DEUM</foreign></hi> for the victory of Culloden!</p>
   <p>We must draw a veil over a scene so replete with painful
associations, at which the heart sickens whilst the pen describes
-a scene we should have considered suited only to afford
gratification to the worshippers of Moloch, when <quote>"alienated Judah"</quote>
passed her offspring through the fire to his grim altar,
                               <quote rend="blockquote">"Besmeared with blood
               Of human sacrifice ;"</quote>

or to the Manicheans of Central America, in the hideous worship
of their devil god.</p>
<pb id="p.53"  n="53"/>




    <p>It is scarcely requisite to add, that towards the other sufferers
the same revolting ceremony was repeated.</p>
    <p>The heads of <persName key="Townley, Francis">Townley</persName> and <persName key="Fletcher, George">Fletcher</persName> were removed, as already
stated, to <placeName key="Temple Bar">Temple Bar</placeName>,
and there placed in the positions indicated
in the print at the commencement of this chapter. For several
weeks, curiosity induced numbers to gather about the arch, to
gaze on those livid features which life and health had so recently
animated; glasses were let on hire, that the morbid feelings of
the masses might be indulged by a closer examination.       There
were many whose very souls, brutalised by these revolting
exhibitions, seemed to derive a savage pleasure from the contemplation.
One elderly person expressed his loyalty and humour in the
following impromptu:--
                  <quote rend="blockquote">"Three heads here I spy,
                  Which the glass did draw nigh,
                     The better to have a good sight;
                   Triangle they are placed,
                   Are bald and barefaced,-
                     Not one of them e'er was upright."</quote></p>
   <p>Of a character far more refined and intellectual is the
following anecdote, related by <persName key="Johnson, Samuel">Dr. Johnson</persName>, in reference to this
subject.  <quote>" I remember,"</quote> said the great lexicographer, <quote>"being, on
<pb id="p.54"  n="54"/>



one occasion, with Goldsmith in Westminster Abbey; while we
surveyed the Poet's Corner, I said to him, from Ovid,-

              <quote>'<foreign lang="LA">Forsitan et nostrum nomen miscebitur istis</foreign>.'</quote>

When he got to <placeName key="Temple Bar">Temple Bar</placeName>
, he stopped me, pointed to the heads
upon it, and slily whispered me,-

             <quote>' <foreign lang="LA">Forsitan et nostrum nomen miscebitur <hi rend="italic">istis</hi>.</foreign></quote>"</quote></p>
   <p><persName key="Johnson, Samuel">Johnson</persName>, we may remark, was strongly imbued with
Jacobite prejudices.</p>
   <p>These were the last fractions of humanity that <placeName key="Temple Bar">Temple Bar</placeName>
 was
destined to receive.  Before other treasonable attempts had subjected
their promoters to well-merited punishment, society had undergone
a great change.  The feelings of the nation had become more
refined-the Government more enlightened-the idea had gradually
acquired the force of conviction, that in order to elevate the moral
condition of the people, it was not essential to commence by
degrading it; and a belief existed, that exhibitions of the disgusting
character we have described might tend to that effect.<note place="foot" n="13">In the <quote>" London Post"</quote> of August 29th, <date value="1746">1746</date>, is the following horrible
account :-<quote>" Last Saturday, a chairman who plies in Great Ormond Street,
Queen's Square, having got from the fire made at the late execution on
Kennington Common, the liver of one of the unhappy sufferers, broiled and
eat it, whether out of derision, or to imitate a cannibal, is not known; but
the inhabitants are much displeased both at his banquet and taste."</quote> The
unhappy sufferers referred to were Donald M'Donald, James Nicholson, and
Walter Ogilvie, who were executed on Kennington Common on the 17th of
August, <date value="1746">1746</date>, for rebellion, a fortnight subsequent to the execution of
<persName key="Townley, Francis">Townley</persName> and <persName key="Fletcher, George">Fletcher</persName>.</note> The twilight

<pb id="p.55"  n="55"/>




of moral improvement had dawned on the world -the advent of a
brighter day was to follow. We have not yet arrived at its meridian
splendour.  We have yet to wait, wait patiently, but not
despairingly, until the world shall have realised the fulness of the idea;
it will then act with a faith that would remove mountains.</p>
   <p>Little more remains to be told of the Bar and its ghastly
occupants.  We find, however, the following notice in the <quote>"Annual
Register"</quote> for January <date value="1766">1766</date>.</p>
   <p><quote>"This morning (Jan. 20th), between two and three o'clock, a
person was observed to watch his opportunity of discharging
musket-balls, from a steel cross-bow, at the two remaining heads
upon <placeName key="Temple Bar">Temple Bar</placeName>.
On his examination he affected a disorder of
his senses, and said his reason for his so doing was his strong
attachment to the present Government, and that he thought it was not
sufficient that a traitor should only suffer death, and that this
provoked his indignation; and that it had been his constant practice,
for three nights past, to amuse himself in the same manner: but


<pb id="p.56"  n="56"/>



it is much to be feared that he is a near relation to one of the
unhappy sufferers." </quote> The account given in the <quote>" Gentleman's
Magazine"</quote> further states, <quote>" Upon searching him, above fifty musket-balls
were found wrapped in a paper, with this motto, <foreign lang="LA">Eripuit ille
vitam.</foreign>"</quote></p>
   <p>No further efforts appear to have been made, either by the
friends or enemies of the reigning family, either by the sane or
the insane, to dislodge these grim tenants of the Bar; there they
remained until the 31st of March, <date value="1772">1772</date>, when one of them fell
down, and we believe, very shortly afterwards, during a high wind,
the remaining head was swept from its lofty position, and Temple
Bar remained untenanted.</p>
   <p>Here, in strictness, terminates our task.  We have
endeavoured--feebly, we are aware--to narrate, in their chronological
order, those events of a criminal character with which <placeName key="Temple Bar">Temple Bar</placeName>

has been, more or less, directly associated. In so doing, we have
not been influenced by any morbid desire to re-open to public view
scenes over which an impenetrable curtain should be drawn, if,
from the contemplation of them no instruction could be
derived--if, in short, no higher object could be attained than the mere
gratification of curiosity.</p>
   <p>We, however, believe that, in tracing the errors as they are
now allowed to be, connected with the former enactments of our
<pb id="p.57"  n="57"/>



penal code, some thoughts may suggest themselves which, if acted
upon, would tend still further to humanize our criminal proceedings,
and thus, in better adapting them to the spirit of the times, render
them far more conducive to the great end of all legislation,-the
repression of crime, and the reformation of the criminal.</p>
   <p>The experience of many centuries had fully demonstrated to
the world the complete fallacy of the idea, that any moral benefit
could arise from  the public exposure of portions of the lifeless
clay of those who had fallen under the vindictive justice of
the law.</p>
 <p>  One result, and one only, had been hitherto attained by these
sanguinary exhibitions - moral degradation, not moral
improvement.</p>
   <p>Still, however, an idea continued to prevail--and a very
obstinate one it was--that, on the commission of any crime of more
than ordinary magnitude, the rigour of the law being carried out
on the spot on which such crime had been perpetrated, would prove
a more powerfully impressive lesson to evil-doers than allowing the
usual course of justice to take place. It did not occur to the minds
of the public, that if any impression were produced, it would
probably be on the feelings of the unfortunate criminal, and not on his
unreflecting associates in crime.  As soon as the world closed to
the one, the public-houses, or haunts of dissipation and vice, opened
<pb id="p.58"  n="58"/>



to the other.   A  life of crime must necessarily be one of
excitement.<note place="foot" n="14"> In the metropolis, at the present day, this excitement is chiefly sought
after in those fruitful nurseries for vice and crime, the penny theatres, saloons,
and concert-rooms. In the first, the most attractive pieces are those in which
a blood-stained career of vice and infamy is most vividly portrayed.
Consequently, such dramas as <quote>"Jack Sheppard,"</quote> <quote>"Claude Duval,"</quote> the ladies'
highwayman, <quote>" Sixteen-String Jack,"</quote> and <quote>" Oliver Twist,"</quote> invariably draw the largest
houses. The Artful Dodger, in the last-named piece, always proves, in
theatrical phraseology, powerfully attractive. From the mischievous results,
however, that have arisen from the representation of <quote>"Jack Sheppard,"</quote> we may
fairly claim for it the pre-eminence over all others of its class in its direct
tendency to fascinate the young and inexperienced with a life of crime.
Within the space of a few weeks, nearly sixty prisoners, committed to the
House of Correction at Westminster, attributed their initiation into criminal
courses to the habit of frequenting such places. From a great number of
letters addressed by the prisoners to one of the excellent chaplains of that
prison, we make the following extracts, corroborative of the correctness of our
remarks :-<quote>"We got our minds tainted by the pieces we see performed at
these low theatres. I have even known lads to swear, coming home after
seeing such pieces as <quote>" Jack Sheppard,"</quote> and <quote>" Oliver Twist,"</quote> that they would
not work any more, but be a thief, and lead a jolly life, like Jack Sheppard
did, and like the Artful Dodger in <quote>" Oliver Twist,"</quote> as the pieces represented
to us. I can say as to myself, that after witnessing such plays, I felt as if it
would <hi rend="italic">be a glory to be a thief; I never went a-thieving till after</hi>."</quote>
   Another thus writes:-<quote>" I used to go to the --- Saloon nearly every
night in the week, where I saw the play of <quote>'Jack Sheppard,'</quote> <quote>'Dick Turpin,'</quote>
<quote>'Oliver Twist,'</quote> and such-like; and when I and my mates came home of a
night, we admired what a jolly life it must be to be a thief, and we agreed
together to be a gang. I soon after left my work,"</quote> &amp;c.
   All further comment on our part would be superfluous.
   A system productive of the most pernicious consequences, and naturally
becoming more and more gigantic,-but which our space will only permit us to
mention,-is the establishment of <soCalled>" Betting Shops,"</soCalled> daily taking place in every
part of London. Should not the legislature speedily pass some measure to
close these seductive temples of vice, the plundered shopkeepers will be
called upon to contribute fresh rates for the enlargement of the metropolitan
and county prisons.</note></p>

    <p>To carry out, therefore, this reformatory principle, the gibbet
was erected in  the streets, in the squares, and other  public
thoroughfares of the metropolis; and had there been any soundness
in the system, from the frequency of its application, rapine and
violence would soon have become unknown: on the contrary,
however, they continued most fearfully to increase.</p>

<pb id="p.59"  n="59"/>



    <p>So inflexible was the Government in carrying out this scheme
of reformation, that nothing was ever permitted to interfere with
its execution.</p>
    <p>Notwithstanding that death had entered the palace, and the
inanimate form of majesty lay cold and extended on the royal
couch,-
                      <quote rend="blockquote">"The shroud its robe of state ;"</quote>

notwithstanding that the hand which signed the warrant was
<pb id="p.60"  n="60"/>



motionless, and that the crown had descended to another sovereign,
still, on the very day of the death of <persName key="George II.">George the Second</persName>, at the
corner of <placeName key="Russell Street">Russell Street</placeName>, <placeName key="Covent Garden">Covent Garden</placeName>, an unfortunate
fellow-creature, convicted of murder, was compelled to utter his last sigh,
and offer up his last prayer, to the throne of Him to whom even
kings are subject.<note place="foot" n="15"> Patrick M'Carty was executed at the corner of <placeName key="Russell Street">Russell Street</placeName>,
<placeName key="Covent Garden">Covent Garden</placeName>, on Saturday, October the 25th, <date value="1760">1760</date>, for the murder of William
Talbot.  <persName key="George II.">George the Second</persName> had expired early in the morning of that day.</note></p>
    <p>The number of murders, however, did not diminish.</p>
    <p>The riots of <date value="1780">1780</date> took place; and, chiefly owing to the
imbecility of the chief magistrate of the City, attained to a most alarming
height.  On their ultimate suppression, the executioner and the
gibbet again perambulated the streets; and more numerous were
the moral examples supplied to the public on this occasion than
on any previous one.</p>
    <p>Nevertheless, riotous conduct was far from being extinct.</p>
    <p>It would be useless to trace further these unsuccessful attempts
to deter from the commission of crime by investing its punishment
with more than ordinary severity.  The last time, we believe, the
gibbet was seen away from  its usual locality, was on the 12th of
March, <date value="1817">1817</date> ; and a most melancholy sight it was.  In Skinner
Street, in the City, a person, evidently insane, was, on that day,

<pb id="p.61"  n="61"/>



executed for riotous conduct.   Those who were present and
witnessed it are not likely to forget the horrors of that moment<note place="foot" n="16"><quote>"The executioner having quitted the platform, the unfortunate wretch
addressed the crowd nearest him, and exclaimed, <quote>'Now, you -- , give me
three cheers when I trip.'</quote> And then, calling to the executioner, he cried out,
<quote>' Come Jack, you -- , let go the jib-boom.'</quote> He was cheering at the instant
the fatal board fell."</quote>-<hi rend="italics">Gent. Magazine</hi>, year <date value="1817">1817</date>, p. 270.</note></p>
   <p>The period, however, had now arrived when the public mind
had become impressed that another great error had been committed;
that no improvement in the moral condition of the people could be
expected to arise by habituating them  to the horrors of executions
conducted in the manner we have described.     This lesson,
therefore, which had erroneously been calculated to produce such great
moral results, was discontinued. The gibbets were removed from our
commons; the dry bones suspended from them consigned to what,
years previously, should have been their destination - the grave;
and the nation advanced another step in the path of truth and
social improvement. <note place="foot" n="17">We, of course, imply that the practice was discontinued about this period.
It was not until the 4th and 5th Will. IV. c. 26, [<date value="1834">1834</date>,] that the hanging of
the bodies of criminals in chains was made illegal.</note> We must advance also a few years, when
another doubt arose, when another question agitated the public
mind, a satisfactory reply to which was imperatively demanded.</p>
    <p>Were the community benefited by placing the same value on

<pb id="p.62"  n="62"/>




life and property? Whether, in short, it was an offence of equal
enormity to pick a man's pocket, as to take his life ?  The public,
usually in advance of the Government, had long since solved this
doubt, had returned a decided negative to the question.  In many
cases, the plundered refused to prosecute -juries to convict; and
from the inequality of the punishment to the offence, too frequently
a total impunity for crime followed its detection.  At length, he
whose untimely death is still felt as a great national loss, and
whose judgment had long acquiesced in the decision given by the
public, the late Sir Robert Peel,<note place="foot" n="18">7th and 8th Geo. IV. c. 28. Bill brought in by the late Sir Robert Peel,
Feb. 23d, <date value="1827">1827</date>. How would the late Sir S. Romilly have rejoiced to see
that day!</note> in the year <date value="1827">1827</date>, by a series
of wise measures, placed our criminal code on a more rational
footing, and in rendering it more in accordance with the unalterable
principles of moral rule and justice, adapted it better to promote
the true ends, as we have stated, of all legislation,-the repression
of crime, and the reformation of the criminal.</p>
   <p>Once more, therefore, the nation acknowledged former errors;
and in abandoning them, a further step was gained towards the
elevation of the moral character of the people.</p>
   <p>The year <date value="1848">1848</date> came, big with the fate of empires, agitated with
those political convulsions which shook to their foundations many


<pb id="p.63"  n="63"/>




of the dynasties of Europe; and, greatly to the credit of the
Republic of France, with her prisons filled with political offenders,
she at once passed a law erasing from  her code the infliction of
death for political offences.  There was a moral dignity in this
course which, amidst much that was reprehensible, reflected honour
on the Provisional Government of that period.  Could England,
then, longer retain in her political code her coercive and
sanguinary enactments?  Was the blood of <persName key="Russell, William">William Lord Russell</persName> longer
to remain unavenged?  And what retribution for the wrongs he
had suffered, could, we ask, be more soothing to his gentle spirit,
than the removal from the statute-book of his country of those
vindictive laws, by the strained interpretation of which he had
been made to suffer an unmerited and painful death?</p>
   <p>To Lord John Russell, his honoured descendant, was entrusted
this retributive justice; and the national character received no
slight addition  to its moral grandeur, by the passing of that
Act by which the punishment of death was interdicted for offences
of a political character.<note place="foot" n="19">The 11th and 12th Vic. c. 12. <quote>"An Act for the better security of the
Crown and Government of the United Kingdom."</quote> Brought in by Sir George
Grey, Secretary for the Home Department, and strongly supported in every
stage by the Premier, Lord John Russell.</note></p>
   <p>By this, and the previous measures of which mention has been

<pb id="p.64"  n="64"/>




made, death, the greatest evil that man can inflict on his
fellowman, was reserved, with few exceptions, to guard that treasure
which if once taken can never be restored--the treasure of life.
But do we imagine, that with all these great and manifest
improvements in our criminal jurisprudence, we have at length arrived at
the last act of this tragedy of errors?  If so, we shall be much
mistaken.  We are still very distant from it. Let us take, however,
encouragement from the success of past efforts; let us still proceed
onwards in the path of improvement; let us not grow weary in
well doing.  We live in days of mighty progress, and the minds of
men were never better prepared than at present for the
perception of truth, and the consequent uprooting of long-cherished
errors.</p>
   <p>It may not be in our power to accomplish, at once, all that
is required, but much may immediately be done.  And one
suggestion which most powerfully arises from the perusal of the events
recorded in this chapter, we would, in all humility, but in all
earnestness, proceed to press on the attention of our readers,-the
baneful effects produced on the morals of the people by the <hi rend="italic">public</hi>
exhibition of the last moments of a criminal.</p>
   <p>Had the lesson intended to be conveyed been attended with
practical benefit, would it not, long since, have evinced itself
in the lives of those who have been placed in positions most
<pb id="p.65"  n="65"/>



to benefit by the example?   On the contrary, we find several
of these gloomy ministers of the law, who so frequently had
performed the last sad office to others, themselves consigned, for
crimes of no inconsiderable magnitude, to a like ignominious death.
Let us be convinced of this truth, that no process in this world is
more calculated to harden the heart and brutalize the feelings of
the public than exhibitions of the character we have mentioned;
whilst, in a country professing to regulate its actions by the
principles derived from Christianity, the compelling an unfortunate being
to offer up his last prayer to the Throne of Mercy amidst the jeers
and scoffs of a degraded rabble, to usher a soul into eternity with
blasphemies and obscenities sounding in his ears, appears to us so
diametrically opposed to all moral consistency, that, were it not
for the knowledge that the roots of error strike deep into the
mind, it would be difficult to comprehend how, for one moment
longer, it could be defended by any reflecting being. What, then,
do we propose as an alteration of a system believed to be
repugnant alike to moral and religious feeling?  We would offer then,
in all seriousness, for the consideration of the public, the propriety
of substituting for the publicity and noise of the open street, the
privacy and stillness of the prison court, or of some other suitable
locality set apart for the purpose.  We propose to invest the solemn
scene with every safeguard calculated to insure the humane and

<pb id="p.66"  n="66"/>


proper discharge of the mournful duty. Let the Sheriffs, men of
honour and probity, be present; let the Reporters for the press,
surpassed by none for intelligence and judicious discernment, be
admitted also; and we shall possess the strongest and most
undeniable assurance, that every obligation that justice and humanity could
impose will be observed.<note place="foot" n="20">It may be urged that the above suggestions are chiefly applicable to
executions in the metropolis. We are, however, convinced, that little
difficulty would arise in maturing some plan, at once so comprehensive in its
character as to apply to every part of the kingdom, and at the same time so
certain in its operation as to leave the most sceptical without a rational
doubt that the dread sentence of the law had been fully and impartially
carried out. We would, with pleasure, refer our readers to two letters which
appeared in the<quote> "Times,"</quote> immediately after the execution of the Mannings,
from the pen of the most graphic and philanthropic writer of the day, Mr.
Charles Dickens; the first bearing date the 15th of Nov. <date value="1849">1849</date>, and the second,
the 19th of the same month. From the latter we make the following extract,
coinciding fully with the views therein expressed :-<quote>" From the moment of a
murderer's being sentenced to death I would dismiss him to the dread
obscurity which the wisest judge upon the bench consigned the murderer
Rush. I would allow no curious visitors to hold any communication with
him. I would place every obstacle in the way of his sayings and doings being
served up in print on Sunday mornings for the perusal of families. His
execution, within the walls of a prison, should be conducted with every terrible
solemnity that careful consideration could devise. Mr. Calcraft the hangman
-of whom I have some information in reference to the last occasion-should
be restrained in his unseemly briskness, in his jokes, his oaths, and his brandy.
To attend the execution I would summon a jury of twenty-four, to be called
the witness jury, eight to be summoned on a low qualification, eight on a
higher, and eight on a higher still; so that it might fairly represent all
classes of society. There should be present, likewise, the governor of the
gaol, the chaplain, the surgeon, and other officers, the sheriffs of the county
or city, and two inspectors of prisons. All these should sign a grave and
solemn form of certificate-the same in every case-that on such a day, at
such an hour, in such a gaol, for such a crime, such a murderer was hanged in
their sight. There should be another certificate from the officer of the prison,
that the person hanged was that person and no other; a third, that that
person was buried. These should be posted on the prison gate for
twentyone days, printed in the <quote>'Gazette,'</quote> ard exhibited on other public places;
and during the hour of the body's hanging I would have the bells of all the
churches in the town or city tolled, and all the shops shut up, that all might
be reminded of what was being done."</quote></note></p>
    <p>Should any one be disposed to intimate that the infliction of
death itself should be at once discontinued; we reply, Not until a


<pb id="p.67"  n="67"/>



secondary punishment shall be introduced, adequate to meet the
offences for which the capital punishment is at present awarded.</p>
    <p>Life and property must never again be considered of the same
relative value.  The law should distinctly mark the several
gradations of crime, lest an inducement should be offered to the criminal
to venture on the commission of offences of a deeper dye by a
similarity of punishment awaiting the detection of those of lower
turpitude.</p>

<pb id="p.68"  n="68"/>


   <p>The day, we trust, may not, however, be distant, when man,
with safety to society, may relinquish his right over the life of his
fellow-man.  When that shall arrive, another great step will be
taken in social and moral improvement, until at length, in the
fulness of time, the sublime wish, expressed in the words of the Bard
of Avon, may find its accomplishment:-</p>
   <p><quote>"I would we were all of one mind, and one mind good. -O
there were desolation of gaolers and gallowses."</quote></p>

                             <p>THE END.</p>

                             <p>LONDON:
                 Printed by G. BARCLAY, Castle St. Leicester Sq,</p>
                 </div1>
                 </body>
                </text>


</TEI.2>