<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/P4X/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
 <!ENTITY % TEI.prose 'INCLUDE'>
 <!ENTITY % TEI.names.dates 'INCLUDE'>
 <!ENTITY % TEI.figures 'INCLUDE'>
 <!ENTITY % TEI.XML 'INCLUDE'>
]>
<TEI.2>

<teiHeader>
	<fileDesc>
		<titleStmt>
			<title>
			College Acquires the English Collection of Late Professor Edwin C. Bolles</title>
			<author>Boston Evening Transcript</author>
			<funder>IMLS</funder>
		</titleStmt>

		<editionStmt>
			<edition><date>2002-01-01</date></edition>
		</editionStmt>

		<extent>10554 bytes</extent>

		<publicationStmt>
			<distributor>Tufts University Digital Collections and Archives</distributor>
			<address>
				<addrLine>Tufts University</addrLine>
				<addrLine>35 Professors Row</addrLine>
				<addrLine>Tisch Library Medford, MA 02155</addrLine>
			</address>
			<idno>tufts:central:dca:UA069:UA069.005.DO.00035</idno>
			<availability status="free"><p>This publication is freely available for scholarly or
educational use.</p></availability>
		</publicationStmt>

  		<notesStmt>
			<note>This document was created from a 1921 article in the Boston Evening Transcript.</note>
		</notesStmt>
    		<sourceDesc>
			<biblStruct>
			<monogr>
			<title>
			College Acquires the English Collection of Late Professor Edwin C. Bolles</title>
			<imprint>
			<pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
			<publisher>Boston Evening Transcript</publisher>
			<date>January 19, 1921</date>
			</imprint>
			</monogr>
			</biblStruct>
		</sourceDesc>
	</fileDesc>

	<encodingDesc>
		<editorialDecl>
			<stdVals><p>Standard date values are given in ISO form: yyyy-mm-dd.</p></stdVals>
			<interpretation><p>Page breaks are marked.</p>
			</interpretation>
			<hyphenation eol="none"><p>End of line hyphens have been
removed.</p></hyphenation>
		</editorialDecl>

		<refsDecl n="TOC">
			<state unit="chapter"/>
		</refsDecl>
      	
		<classDecl>
		<taxonomy id="LCSH"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy>
		<taxonomy id="LC"><bibl><title>Library of Congress</title></bibl></taxonomy>
		</classDecl>
	</encodingDesc>

	<profileDesc>
		<creation><date>2000-01-01</date></creation>
		<langUsage><language id="EN" usage="99">English.</language>
		<language id="FR" usage="1">French.</language>
					</langUsage>

		<textClass>
			<keywords scheme="LCSH">
			<list>
			<item>Edwin C. Bolles Collection.</item>
			</list>
			</keywords>
		</textClass>
	</profileDesc>

	<revisionDesc>
		<change><date>2004-08-19</date><respStmt><name>Cynthia Mackey</name><resp>admin.</resp></respStmt><item>Updated text to TEI P4 XML. Added Tufts Digital Library object identifiers for figures.</item></change>
	</revisionDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text>
<body>
<pb n="1" id="p.1"/>
<div1 type="chapter" n="Rare Gift Made to Tufts Library" id="c1"><head>Rare Gift Made to Tufts Library</head>


     <p>Trustees of <orgName key="Tufts College">Tufts College</orgName> have purchased the English collection of the late
Professor <persName key="Edwin C. Bolles"> Edwin Courtlandt Bolles</persName>, which has been declared by experts to be one of
the best in the country.  The collection will be placed in the college library as
a personal gift from the trustees in memory of the late <persName key="Edwin C. Bolles">Dr. Bolles.</persName>  It includes
many rare books, maps and prints, these of the city of London numbering more than
<num value="6000">six thousand.</num>  The gift is one of the most elaborate that the <placeName key="Eaton Hall">Eaton Memorial Library</placeName>
has received in recent years. Amongst the books in the Collection are <num value="650">650</num> volumes on
England, more than half of which are on historic London. Dr. Bolles made the library while living in London near the <placeName key="cruch,British Museum">British Museum</placeName> over thirty years age, while preparing a series of lectures which he later gave at the <orgName key="Lowell Institue">Lowell Institute</orgName> in this
city in <dateRange from="1881-01-" to="1881-02-">January and February, 1881.</dateRange> The pamphlets alone number <num value="915">915</num> on England and
<num value="343">343</num> on Old London.</p>

     <p>Dr. Bolles spent many years on extra-illustration of his books. The most
elaborate of these is his "Old and New London" in six volumes. Instead of cutting
the volumes, a process which would have increased their number, the collector devised an original plan of underlining the passage to be illustrated, made marginal
notes numbering the illustration, and filed the prints volume by volume accordingly
to chapter and rages, in smaller cabinet and filing cases. These include some fine
prints in <placeName key="bart,Trafalgar Square">Trafalgar Square</placeName>  and the Tower, <placeName key="cruch,Westminster">Westminster</placeName> and the Fleet, and other subjects which form a rich treasure to the student of English history. There are two
sets of  the extra-illustrated works.  Much of this fine work was done during the
last decade after Dr. Bolles had lost the use of his sight.  During this time he
persevered and, with the aid of his assistants, completed the work before his death
a year ago.<name type="company" key="Philip Morris">Philip Morris</name> <name type="person" key="Louis Napoleon">Louis Napoleon</name></p>

     <p>Among the other treasures of the works is the <date value="1808">1808</date> edition of "James by C. J.
Fox, extra-illustrated by the Reverend Dr. Chapin of New York. It contains rare
engravings of Oliver Cromwell, Charles II, and the Earl of Southampton with his
autograph beautifully inlaid. Other features are engravings and autographs of
William III, Trumbull, Gedelphin, Montague, and Titus Oates.  There are also two
miniatures on ivory of James II and the Queen of James I from the Cotton collection.
In this work, too, are found autographs, one of Samuel Pepys, one of Richard Baxter,
one of Queensbury, and two of <persName key="Charles Stuart">Charles II</persName> one of which is an vellum.
</p>
     <p>The two-volume 'History of His Own Time" by Burnett has been expanded with
extra-illustrations to six volumes. "Memoirs of Brass Crosby, Lord Mayor of London
1770-1771" is also rich in extra-illustrations, documents, and autographs of Lord
Mayors on vellum.
</p>
<pb n="2" id="p.2"/>
</div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="The Great Seal of England" id="c2"><head>The Great Seal of England</head><p>
<figure n="tufts:central:dca:MS004:MS004.002.011.DO01.00001"><head> Front Side of Great Seal of England</head></figure>
</p>
     <p>The Great Seal of England bearing the signature of <persName key="James Stuart">James I</persName> and the official
signature of <persName>Lord Bacon</persName> is perfectly preserved, as clearly readable as a modern
document. It is made of pure beeswax, a circumstance which account for its perfect
condition. It is as large   as a teaplate and is attached to a "pardon of sale." <figure n="tufts:central:dca:MS004:MS004.002.011.DO01.00003"><head> Pardon of Sale</head></figure>
Dr. Bolles often recounted to his classes in English History the circumstances under
which this treasure came into his possession. "While in London he visited the shop
of a queer old bookseller named Salkill, who ... professed to hate all clergymen.
Not recognizing Dr. Bolles as a member of the cloth, the old character received him
cordially and gave him <foreign lang="FR">carte blanche </foreign>to his shop.  He showed Dr, Bolles an interesting old chest containing seals of many periods which he had bought at the <placeName id="Temple">Temple</placeName>,
and he bade Dr. Bolles pick out any one which he might want. The latter hesitated
a long time over his selection, having in mind the choice of a seal of <persName key="Elizabeth I">Elizabeth</persName>.
He chose the seal of <persName key="James Stuart">James</persName>, however, because it was the most perfect of the lot.
On the reverse of the parchment to which the seal is attached is a signature  "Bacon"
in a different hand from that on the face.   Dr. Bolles traced the difference and
finally accounted for it as being the private signature of the great Englishman.
Further investigation revealed, however, that it was the writing of the scribe who
drew up the pardon of sale.
</p>
     <p>One of the five extant copies of Pennet's "London", which are  printed on Whitman
drawing paper, is also included in the collection.   Of the other four, one is now
in the <placeName key="cruch,British Museum">British Museum</placeName>, one of [sic]  the Sir John Sloane Museum, one in a nobleman's
private library, and one has disappeared from the shelves of booklovers without
binding, but the original covers are with it and otherwise it is in good condition.
</p>
     <p>One of the rarest books of all, according to the estimate of experts, is "Tom
Brown's Schooldays." Two others of note are <persName key="Dickens, Charles">Charles Dickens'</persName> "London and Londoners,
or a Second Judgment of Babylon the Great," and Manners and Customs of Modern
London".  These books have their special value in that they were personal possessions of the great English author.  On the inside cover is a book-plate bearing a
star and twisted rope; below "Charles Dickens" is written in bold letters.  There
are also with them two works of William Winter, autographed.
</p>
     <p>A rare collection of hundreds of old coins are included in the treasure, many
bookbinding tools, tiles from the Norman church of St. Clement at Sandwich, a piece
of brick from <placeName key="Battle Abbey">Battle Abbey</placeName>, a fragment from an old Roman wall, and other touches
on the ancient landmarks of England.</p>

     <p>The full value of the treasure which has come to the library through the generosity of the trustees cannot at present be estimated. It will require many months of
expert appraisal before its extent can be realized.</p>

     <p>It was  Dr. Bolles's often expressed wish that the collection might eventually
be placed in the college library and the trustees in taking this action paid a
superlative tribute to the memory of the great man who for so many years  served the
college so faithfully and so effectively in his various capacities  as lecturer,
professor, trustee, and finally chaplain.  <figure n="tufts:central:dca:MS004:MS004.002.011.DO01.00002"><head>Memorial Book-plate</head></figure></p><p>A book-plate bearing the Bolles coat-of-arms and the seal will be  engraved and placed in each volume, with the inscription
indicating that it stands as a memorial to the memory of one of the most influential
men who ever served Tufts College as an officer of the institution.

</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>