<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/P4X/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
 <!ENTITY % TEI.prose 'INCLUDE'>
 <!ENTITY % TEI.names.dates 'INCLUDE'>
 <!ENTITY % TEI.figures 'INCLUDE'>
 <!ENTITY % TEI.XML 'INCLUDE'>
]>

<TEI.2>

<teiHeader>
	<fileDesc>
	<titleStmt>
		<title>The Joyous Neighbourhood of Covent Garden</title>
		<title>A Literary Souvenir of the Tavistock Hotel, Done in Celebration of its Hundredth
Anniversary</title>
		<author>Charles Eyre Pascoe</author>
		
		<funder>Institute for Museum and Library Services</funder>
	</titleStmt>

		<editionStmt>
			<edition><date>2002-01-01</date></edition>
		</editionStmt>

		<extent>139842 bytes</extent>

		<publicationStmt>
			<distributor>Tufts University Digital Collections and Archives</distributor>
			<address>
				<addrLine>Tufts University</addrLine>
				<addrLine>35 Professors Row</addrLine>
				<addrLine>Tisch Library Medford, MA 02155</addrLine>
			</address>
			<idno>tufts:central:dca:UA069:UA069.005.DO.00032</idno>
			<availability status="free"><p>This publication is freely available for scholarly or

educational use.</p></availability>
		</publicationStmt>

  		<notesStmt>
			<note>This doucument was created from the 1887 printing of Charles Eyre Pascoe's The Joyous Neighborhood of Covent Garden.</note>
		</notesStmt>

    		<sourceDesc>
			<biblStruct>
				<monogr>
				<author>Charles Eyre Pascoe</author>
				<title>The Joyous Neighbourhood of Covent Garden</title>
				<title>A Literary Souvenir of the Tavistock Hotel, Done in Celebration of its Hundredth
Anniversary</title>
				<imprint>
				<pubPlace>London: Tooks Court, Chancery Lane.</pubPlace>
				<publisher>The Chiswick Press</publisher>
				<date>1887</date>
				</imprint>
				</monogr>
			</biblStruct>
		</sourceDesc>
	</fileDesc>

	<encodingDesc>
		<editorialDecl>
			<stdVals><p>Standard date values are given in ISO form:
yyyy-mm-dd.</p></stdVals>
			<interpretation><p>Page breaks are marked.</p>
			<p>Dates are marked.</p>
			<p>Place names are marked.</p>
			<p>Personal names are marked.</p>
			</interpretation>
			<hyphenation eol="none"><p>End of line hyphens have been
removed.</p></hyphenation>
		</editorialDecl>

		
		<refsDecl n="TOC">
			<state unit="preface"/>
		</refsDecl>
		<refsDecl n="TOC">
			<state unit="chapter"/>
		</refsDecl>
		<refsDecl n="TOC">
			<state unit="appendix"/>
		</refsDecl>

		<classDecl>
		<taxonomy id="LCSH"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject
Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy>
		<taxonomy id="LC"><bibl><title>Library of Congress</title></bibl></taxonomy>
		</classDecl>
	</encodingDesc>

	<profileDesc>
		<creation><date>2000-01-01</date></creation>
		<langUsage><language id="EN" usage="99">English.</language>
		<language id="LA" usage="1">Latin.</language>
					</langUsage>

		<textClass>
			<keywords scheme="LCSH">
			<list>
			<item>Covent Garden (London, England).</item>
			</list>
			</keywords>
			<classCode scheme='LC'>DA 685.C7</classCode>
		</textClass>
	</profileDesc>

	<revisionDesc>
		<change><date>2004-08-18</date><respStmt><name>Cynthia Mackey</name><resp>admin.</resp></respStmt><item>Updated text to TEI P4 XML. Added Tufts Digital Library object identifiers for figures.</item></change>
	</revisionDesc>


</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
	<titlePage>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart type="main">"THE JOYOUS NEIGHBOURHOOD OF COVENT GARDEN:"</titlePart>
			<titlePart type="sub">A Literary Souvenir
			<lb/>OF THE
			<lb/>TAVISTOCK HOTEL,
			<lb/>DONE IN CELEBRATION OF ITS HUNDREDTH
			<lb/>ANNIVERSARY,</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<byline>BY<docAuthor>CHARLES EYRE PASCOE.</docAuthor></byline>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart type="desc">The Illustrations contributed by JOHN JELLICOE.</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<docImprint>
			<pubPlace>LONDON:</pubPlace>
			PRINTED AT THE <publisher>CHISWICK PRESS,</publisher>
			<address><addrLine>TOOKS COURT, CHANCERY LANE.</addrLine></address>
			<docDate>1887.</docDate>
		</docImprint>
	</titlePage>

<div1 type="preface" n="Preface" id="front001">
<pb n="i"/>
<p><figure id="fig.1" n="tufts:central:dca:MS004:MS004.002.008.DO01.00001"><head>The Tavistock Breakfast Rooms in 1787 from the eastern Piazza</head></figure></p>
<pb n="ii"/>
<p><hi rend="italic">Addison.</hi> We could talk more freely, you know,
at the tavern. There we have dined together some
hundred times.<hi rend="italic">Steele.</hi> Most days, for many years.
LANDOR'S <title>Imaginary Conversations</title>.</p>
</div1>
</front>

<body>
<pb n="11" id="p.11"/>
<div1 type="chapter" n="Chapter I: COVENT GARDEN" id="c1"><head>Chapter I:<placeName key="COVENT GARDEN">COVENT GARDEN</placeName>.</head><p><figure id="fig.5" n="tufts:central:dca:MS004:MS004.002.008.DO01.00002"><head></head></figure>
</p>
<p>THE man who first made the fame of
<placeName key="Covent Garden">Covent Garden</placeName> was <persName key="Inigo Jones">Inigo Jones</persName>. Except
among writers of text-books and
professors and students of architecture he is
of little account now.  Yet his name alone, said
Horace Walpole, would save England from the
disgrace of not having her representative among the
arts.  "She adopted <persName key="Holbein">Holbein</persName> and <persName key="Vandyke">Vandyke</persName>, she
borrowed Rubens, she produced Inigo Jones.
Vitruvius drew up his grammar, Palladio showed him his
practice, Rome displayed a theatre worthy of his

<pb n="12" id="p.12"/>
emulation, and King Charles was ready to encourage,
employ, and reward his talents." "Words of learned
<figure id="fig.6" n="tufts:central:dca:MS004:MS004.002.008.DO01.00003"><head>The Tavistock Hotel</head></figure>
length and
thund'ring  import "
in truth; but to
look at <placeName key="Covent Garden">Covent
Garden</placeName> now one
would hardly
credit it that
<persName key="Jones, Inigo">Inigo Jones</persName> was
so great a man.
It was he who
built the arcade
once known as
the <placeName key="Portico
Walk">Portico
Walk</placeName>, and in
later time as the
Great and Little
Piazzas. He also built the adjoining <placeName key="Church of St. Paul">Church of St. Paul</placeName>.
Walpole himself "lacked taste," he says, "to see the
beauties of these two structures." Others equally gifted
with the critical faculty, have probably never thought it
worth while to question his opinion that "the pilasters

               <pb n="13" id="p.13"/>
of the arcade are as errant and homely stripes as any
plaisterer would make."  To-day they engage the
attention of no one, except, perhaps, in protest of the
fetid filth which accumulates about them in summer
time, and their occasional dangerous proximity to the
big wheels of a " rolling" Hansom cab, fighting its
way to the Tavistock Hotel. But in Inigo Jones's
day the Portico Walk was one of the show-places of
London. As planned by him it was never completed.
It was originally intended to continue it along the
whole square.  The north and eastern sides were
built, and there the design was left. The Old and
New Hummums hotels (now pulled down), took the
place of the south-eastern piazza which was destroyed
by fire shortly after its erection. For the rest, those
who care to examine what remains of Inigo Jones's
famous structure will find it in the arcade extending
from the Tavistock Hotel to the fruiterers' shops that
have now taken the place of the old Bedford and the
adjoining tavern.</p>
<p>It will scarce interest the reader to trace the origin
of the market. Like many another market elsewhere,
it sprung up no one knows how. For some years

<pb n="14" id="p.14"/>
before Inigo Jones took it in hand, the open space
afforded a lean pasturage for a few cattle. After he
had completed the church of St. Paul and the Piazza,
it was still an unsightly plot of scrubby, ill-kept
ground, such as we often see disfiguring newly-planned
neighbourhoods in the suburbs. The " furies of the
football war" used to wage upon this plot in the
closing years of the seventeenth century.  Stray
vendors of fruit and vegetables, from the outlying
villages of Marylebone and Islington, gathered upon
it and sold to passers-by. At the outset, probably,
they had as much right to "make their pitch there"
as the costermongers of St. Luke's in the streets of
Hackney. But the ducal owner, nothing loth to see
his land utilized that way, encouraged their traffic and
applied to the king for letters patent for establishing
a market. A hundred years at least passed before it
became of any significance; and even then it was but
a collection of rude wooden sheds and railed in spaces,
familiar to many of us who have strolled into the
market-place of old French towns. The sturdy granite
edifice of to-day dates only from the third decade of
the present century. It is neither very imposing nor

              <pb n="15" id="p.15"/>
very convenient, but it is a palace compared with the
scanty hovels that dotted the square and formed the
market in the closing years of the seventeenth and
opening years of the eighteenth centuries. It was
then that Covent Garden began to be recognized as a
fashionable neighbourhood. Its history may be said
to date from that period.<figure id="fig.7" n="tufts:central:dca:MS004:MS004.002.008.DO01.00004"><head></head></figure></p></div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="Chapter II: THE PAINTERS OF THE PIAZZA" id="c2"><head>Chapter II: THE PAINTERS OF THE PIAZZA.</head>
<p><figure id="fig.8" n="tufts:central:dca:MS004:MS004.002.008.DO01.00005"><head></head></figure></p>

<p>SIR PETER LELY first brought it in
repute. In the angle of the Piazza which
now forms a part of the Tavistock Hotel,
lived this successorof Vandyck in England,
" the most capital painter " of the reign of Charles II.
He, too, came from across the seas-from the Hague,
where his father, one Vander Vaas, a captain of foot,
was born in a perfumer's shop, " at the sign of
the Lily." He received the appellation of Captain du
Lys (Anglicised) Lely, which later became the proper
name of the son.   Those who would become
acquainted with the works of Lely will find his most
famous examples hanging in the State Bed-room of
William III. at Hampton Court Palace. The
collection of pictures known as the Beauties of Charles II.'s
Court is by him. He was the ladies' painter, and not
all of his sitters showed the self-abasement of Crom-

               <pb n="17" id="p.17"/>
well. " Mr. Lely," said he (so at least the story runs),
"I desire you will use all your skill to paint my
picture truly like me, and not flatter me at all; but
remark all these roughnesses, pimples, warts, and
everything as you see; otherwise I never will pay a
farthing for it." Lely was somewhat prone to gratify
the vanity of the ladies who sat to him. To this
failing, by the way, Bernard Lens (the engraver, who
also lived in Covent Garden,) showed the stouter front.
He was drawing a lady's picture in the dress of the
Queen of Scots.  " But, Mr. Lens," said the lady,
"you have not made me like the Queen of Scots."
" No, madam," replied Lens: "if God Almighty had
made your ladyship like her, I would." The reader
must go to the palace at Hampton Court to study the
best of Lely's portraits. His pictures of Lady Bellasys;
Frances Stewart, Duchess of Richmond; Anne Hyde,
Duchess of York; Louise, Duchess of Portsmouth;
Barbara, Duchess of Cleveland; the Countess of
Grammont and the other ladies of Charles II.'s court, are
accounted to-day among the art-treasures of the nation.<note place="foot" n="1">
"No more appropriate place could have been selected. It
is a real delight to sit in the window-sill here, before the tramping crowds have invaded the quiet, and contemplate these
charming portraits with  Pepy's 'Diary' or Grammont's
' Memoirs' in one's hand ; or, better still, Mrs. Jameson's
'Beauties of Charles II.' One can imagine one's self for a
moment transported into that mixed society of frail, but lovely
and interesting women-' the professional beauties ' of the time.'La Duchesse d'York,' says Hamilton in his ' Memoires de
Grammont,' 'voulut avoir les portraits des plus belles
personnes de la Cour. Lely les peignit; il emploia tout son art
dans l'execution. Il ne pouvait travailler a de plus beaux sujets.
Chaque portrait parut etre un chef-d'ceuvre.'
"It must be confessed that he has succeeded in giving that
voluptuous expression of blended drowsiness and sweetness, and
that air of tender languishment which are so much in harmony
with the characters of these beautiful and charming creatures.
Their 'night-gowns fastened with a single pin,' and the
' sleepy eye that spoke the melting soul,' would have sufficiently
told us their history if the memoir writers had failed to supply
it."---Hampton Court Palace, ERNEST LAW.</note></p>


<pb n="18" id="p.18"/>
<p>At the corner house in the Great Piazza Sir Peter
Lely lived, and   there kept up somewhat of the<figure id="fig.9" n="tufts:central:dca:MS004:MS004.002.008.DO01.00006"><head></head></figure>
luxurious
style and
habits of
Vandyck, whose
manner,    by
the  way, he
copied in
more     ways
than one. "To see,"
exclaims the
inquisitive and
thrifty Pepys, "in what pomp his table is laid for
himself to go to dinner!      He showed    me Lady
Castlemaine's portrait, which is a most blessed
picture, and one that I must have a copy of."        We


                   <pb n="19" id="p.19"/>
wonder whether the curious little gentleman ever
secured that copy? </p>
<p>In the house in the north-east angle, next to
what was till lately "The Bedford" ("with a garden
going  back   to  Bow   Street :"  the  cultivation  of
flowers was his hobby) another painter of portraits,
Sir Godfrey Kneller, resided for many years; one of
the vainest of men, of whom many stories are related.
Pope, who used to visit him     here, was accustomed
to say that there was no flattery so gross but he
would swallow it.     " Sir Godfrey, I believe if the
Almighty had had your assistance," said Mr. Pope
one day, " the world would have been formed more


<pb n="20" id="p.20"/>
perfect." "'Fore God, sir," replied Kneller, laying his
hand upon the poet's deformed shoulder; " I believe
so "-an answer which was less impious perhaps than
the question that gave rise to it. " Where he [Sir
Godfrey Kneller] offered one picture to fame," says
Horace Walpole, " he sacrificed twenty to lucre; and
he met with customers of so little judgment, that they
were fond of being painted by a man who would
gladly have disowned his works the moment they
were paid for." Indeed, so hasty and rapacious was
Kneller that he used to send away the ladies who
sate to him, as soon as he had sketched their faces,
and to paint the figure and hands from his housemaid.
He left (it is said) 500 portraits unfinished, for his
customers proved less ready to pay than to sit.
Several of his works are at Hampton Court, the best
known being the pictures in the King's Presence
Chamber, the Beauties of the Court of William and
Mary, known as the " Hampton Court Beauties."
This name was given them from their being placed
in this Palace by Queen Mary, and also in order to
distinguish them from Lely's Beauties of Charles I.'s
Court, formerly at Windsor, and thence called " The
Windsor Beauties."</p>

              <pb n="21" id="p.21"/>
<p>Another painter of note, "the successor of Verrio,
and the rival of Laguerre in the decoration of our
palaces and public buildings," Sir James Thornhill,
was resident for some years in the Great Piazza.
The house where he lived subsequently became part
of the Tavistock Breakfast Rooms.  In this house,
after the refusal of the government to entertain his
proposal for building a Royal Academy at back of
the King's Mews at Charing Cross (the place which
was later its home for many years), he opened an
academy for the instruction of pupils in drawing. From
the Piazza studios, indeed, the first practical schemes
for a national academy emanated: in the original
instance with Sir Godfrey Kneller, and a few years
later, with Sir James Thornhill.  The best known
works of this painter are the decoration of the Inner
Dome of St. Paul's Cathedral; that of the Great Hall
of the Royal Naval College (formerly the Royal
Hospital) at Greenwich; and of the King's Rooms at
Hampton Court Palace.</p>
<p>That great and original genius, Hogarth (he married
Sir James Thornhill's daughter), was another frequenter
of the Piazza studios. His famous series of pictures,

<pb n="22" id="p.22"/>
" Marriage a la Mode," were first exhibited in the house
where his father-in-law had lived, and which, as we
have mentioned, later became part of the present
Tavistock Hotel. It was in 1750 the "Marriage a
la Mode " series were disposed of by auction. There
were only two competitors for this work, now in the
National Gallery.  A bid of &#x00A3; 110 (which the
purchaser, Mr. Lane, of Hillingdon, near Uxbridge,
generously made guineas), secured possession of the
six, the frames enclosing which, it was stated, with
delicious irony, were valued at four guineas each!
These six chef-d'oeuvres of Hogarth's pencil were,
therefore, valued by the public of little more than a
century ago at exactly one hundred times less than
the sum which was given a few years ago for a single
portrait by one of his most eminent contemporaries.
In 1797, Mr. Angerstein bought the "Marriage a la
Mode" for &#x00A3; 1,000. We wonder what it would fetch
now, if offered to the public at Christie's? In the
rooms where these pictures were exhibited Richard
Wilson afterwards lived; poor Wilson, who painted
his grandest landscapes in vain.  There is a letter
extant written by Wilson to West (subsequently President

             <pb n="23" id="p.23"/>
 of the Royal Academy), requesting him to
purchase some of his painting tools, and a large press or
case for oils and colours (together with a representation
of the Piazza), which had been the property of Sir
James Thornhill. Wilson was unthrifty, and fond of
the bottle. The circumstances of his later life were
painful enough. With extreme difficulty paying the
rent of a single room, and finding it hard case to
provide the cost of his painting materials, he died,
neglected and forgotten, at a little village in
Denbighshire. His fame is now so secure that the sale in
London of a good example from his pencil would
attract purchasers from all parts of the kingdom.
With the death of Wilson, the art associations of the
Piazza came to an end. Henceforth the spot,
memorable as the birthplace and nursery of the English
School of Painting, became dedicated to the fun and
frolic of tavern life.<figure id="fig.10" n="tufts:central:dca:MS004:MS004.002.008.DO01.00007"><head></head></figure></p></div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="Chapter III: THE MART OF NEWS, POLITICS, AND SCANDAL" id="c3"><head>Chapter III: THE MART OF NEWS, POLITICS,
AND SCANDAL.</head><p>
<figure id="fig.12" n="tufts:central:dca:MS004:MS004.002.008.DO01.00008"><head></head></figure></p>

<p>THACKERAY, who knew London better
than most men, somewhere speaks of
Covent Garden as "the joyous
neighbourhood of Covent Garden." No part
of the town has been more famous for its coffee-houses,
taverns, and inns. From the end of the seventeenth
to the middle of the nineteenth century it was the
best known rendezvous of gentlemen visiting London.
Russell Street, now given over chiefly to vegetable
vendors and fruiterers, was once the social Exchange
of the English capital, the Pall Mall of its day, the
mart, that is to say, of news, politics, and scandal.
In this little street stood the most noted of the
coffeehouses of the reigns of William III. and Queen Anne,
familiar to all who are conversant with the best parts
of our literature. " Will's," " Button's," and " Tom's,"

            <pb n="25" id="p.25"/>
the coffee-houses " sacred to polite letters," were the
chief places of general resort in London. The locality
was fashionable. In Bow Street not a few persons of
distinction lived. That worthy representative of the
old English country gentleman of Addison's creation,
Sir Roger de Coverley, was accustomed to make it
his London address toward the latter part of his
career. In earlier time gossips Pepys and Evelyn,
the historians of the Restoration, visited and lodged
there. In the closing years of the seventeenth century
Drury Lane and its neighbourhood was a part of
great respectability. The national theatre (as in our
time) drew all the town to its performances. Wych
Street, Great and Little Queen Street, Lincoln's Inn
Fields, Portugal Street, Long Acre, and the streets
adjacent, exhibited some of the best residences of the
well-to-do classes. York, Bedford, Tavistock, Henrietta,
King, and what are now known as Garrick, Catherine,
and Wellington Streets, were equally well represented
by the houses of the gentry. Foreign princes were
taken to see Bloomsbury Square as one of the wonders
of England; and the district of Soho was the " Mayfair"
of the town. The dedication to Lord North in the

<pb n="26" id="p.26"/>
original edition of "Earl Chesterfield's Letters to his
Son " is dated from Golden Square, showing it to have
been at that period (1774) what some of us would call
a highly-desirable neighbourhood.  The Great and
Little Piazzas were once the daily lounging-place of the
beaux and belles of the fashionable quarter, who thither
came to shop, gossip, and flirt, much as they do in this
our time in the less confined area of the West End.</p>
<p>At the west corner of Bow and north side of
Russell Street stood ' Will's," the oldest and most
honourable of the coffee-houses of the Queen Anne
period. "Coffee-houses" (we take leave to explain
to him to whom the " Spectator " and " Tatler " are as
yet unopened books) from the time of their
commencement in 1652 down to 1740, or thereabout,
when the tavern began to assert its pre-eminence, were
the clubs of London. They differed in this respect
only from the modern club, namely, that whereas the
latter avails itself of the privilege of the black-ball, and
exacts an entrance fee and subscription as a condition
precedent of membership, the former admitted any
decently-attired idler who presented himself, and paid
his penny at the bar, and who could shoulder his way

             <pb n="27" id="p.27"/>
through the crowd of beaux who fluttered around the
attractive bar-maid at the entrance. Though the
times have changed, we still cling to the old fashion of
paying our respects to beauty at the tavern. A
century hence, perhaps, some chronicler of London
life will relate to his contemporaries the traditional
delights of the "Gaiety" and "Criterion," and the
attractions of the "Lous" and "Tinys " who ruled
there as Gay and his friends have bespoken our
sympathy for charming Molly Mogg of " the Rose."
The "Rose" (next which stood the barber's shop
where the gay Templar had his shoes polished
and his periwig powdered) was in Addison's day a
much-frequented tavern at the end of a passage in
Russell Street, adjoining the national theatre, which
fronted upon Drury Lane.</p>
<p>"Will's " was the rendezvous of the wits and poets.
Dryden's patronage and frequent appearance there
made the reputation of the house. After the play, all
who knew London and whom London knew, gathered
at " Will's" for a pipe, a gossip, and a cup of coffee.
To quote an oft-quoted passage of Macaulay: " Under
no roof was a greater variety of figures to be seen;

<pb n="28" id="p.28"/>
earls in stars and garters, clergymen in cassocks and
bands, pert Templars, sheepish lads from the
universities, translators and index-makers in ragged coats of
frieze. The great push was to get near the chair where
John Dryden sat. In winter that chair was always in
the warmest nook by the fire; in summer it stood in
the balcony. To bow to him and hear his opinion of
Racine's last tragedy, or of Bossu's treatise on epic
poetry, was thought a privilege. A pinch from his
snuff-box was an honour sufficient to turn the head
of an enthusiast."</p>
<p>A new generation of wits and authors assembled at
"Button's" in the same street. " Button's" was on
the south side, about two doors from where, at a
later period, stood the old "Hummums," most
comfortable of old London hostelries, sacred to the
memory of the college " Don" and country parson.
It was to " Button's " the gifted and eloquent Addison
frequently withdrew from his vexatious after-dinner
tete-a-tetes with the shrewish countess, his wife. That
lady was never particularly fond of the wit that smells
of wine, and Addison was debarred the company of
many of his convivial friends at her table. "We

               <pb n="29" id="p.29"/>
could talk more freely at the tavern," are words that
Landor (" Imaginary Conversations ") puts in the
mouth of Addison addressing Steele: " there we
have dined together some hundred times." " Aye,"
answers Steele, " most days for many years."
* * * * *"Why cannot I see him   again in his
arm-chair, his right hand upon his breast under
the fawn-coloured waistcoat, his brow erect and clear
as his conscience, his wit even and composed as his
temper, with measurely curls and antithetical top-knots,
like his style; the calmest poet, the most quiet
patriot: dear Addison! drunk, deliberate, moral,
sentimental, foaming over with truth and virtue,
with tenderness and friendship, and only worse in one
ruffle for the wine."</p>
<p>Addison and Steele are the most brilliant of
the company to which "Button's" gave hospitality.
Occasionally, Swift was numbered of it, and Gay
Gay, to whom we owe our first ballad opera (the
"Beggar's Opera"), suggested, it is said, by Swift,
and first " performed at I)rury Lane" in the early
years of the last century--and Prior and Pope.
The lesser of their contemporaries to whom " But-

<pb n="30" id="p.30"/>
ton's " was familiar, would include the names of all the
writers of that day to whom the works of these six
were familiar. To catch a glimpse of the ingenious
Mr. Addison in friendly converse with Sir Richard
Steele was a bait to the literary lounger too alluring to
be withstood.</p>
<p>" Tom's" at the corner of the Piazza, on the north
side over against "Button's," was its most
enterprising rival.  "Tom's" was started in 1764 by a
general subscription among nearly seven hundred of
the nobility, foreign ministers, and gentry of that day.
Its principal room occupied the whole of the upper
floor extending back to the Bedford Tavern. It was
frequented (among others) by Dr. Johnson, Garrick,
Murphy, Dr. Dodd, Goldsmith, Sir J. Reynolds,
Moody, Foote, Sir Philip Francis; and "dukes, lords,
and actors of note " mingled in the daily crowd. We
have seen a little account for refreshments supplied by
Tom (originally a waiter at "Will's) to the vestry of
St. Paul's, Covent Garden, in 1770.  It would
appear that "a dish of chocolate" cost no more
then than it does now-6d. The vestry consumed
34 jellys at the same price, and 2s. 3d. worth of

               <pb n="31" id="p.31"/>
biscuits-not a costly entertainment in comparison of
that which guardians or vestrymen occasionally indulge
in now at the expense of the ratepayers.</p>
<p>Not many yards eastward from Tom's (at No. 8,
Russell Street,) was, in later years, the house of Tom
Davies, the bookseller, in whose little back-parlour
Boswell first met Johnson. The latter, who had just
been refused a favour by Garrick, was in surliest
humour. " He knows the house [i. e., Drury Lane]
will be full, and an order would be worth three
shillings," growled the Doctor to Davies, "and he
refuses me an order for the play for Miss Williams."
" O, Sir !" interpolates the adventurous Bozzy, " I
cannot think Mr. Garrick would refuse such a trifle to
you." " Sir," Johnson sternly replies, " I have known
David Garrick longer than you; and I know no right
you have to talk to me on the subject." Boswell took
the unpleasant snub without flinching, and to that
admirable quality of his of never knowing when he
had been rebuffed, we are, perhaps, indebted for
the best biography ever written.  "Boswell's Life
of Johnson," still maintains its place as the most
instructive and entertaining book of its class in the

<pb n="32" id="p.32"/>
English language. Its first lines may be said to have
been jotted down in the shop of worthy Tom Davies
of Russell Street, actor and bookseller.<figure id="fig.13" n="tufts:central:dca:MS004:MS004.002.008.DO01.00009"><head></head></figure></p>
<p>Covent
Garden,
indeed, was a
favourite
resort of the
great Doctor.
His first
lodging, when he
came to
Lond on from
Lichfield, was
in Exeter
Street, not far
away. At the
"Pine Apple"
in New Street
he took his
frugal cut of meat for 6d., adding a penny for
bread, and a penny for the waiter: "so that I was
quite well served," he wrote, "nay, better than the

             <pb n="33" id="p.33"/>
rest" (who paid a shilling for their dinner), "for they
gave the waiter nothing." That " tipping " the waiter
appears to be a custom of an honourable antiquity,
though, we may parenthetically remark, we find
nowhere any authority for the waiter paying his master
for his place, as some do now in London, to the
obvious disadvantage of poorer customers to whom the
fee, or rather tribute, is an exaction. It was into the
"Market" Dr. Johnson shuffled with those lively
young companions of his middle-age, Beauclerk and
Langton, who on one occasion roused him from his bed
for a frolic at three in the morning. " What, is it you,
you dogs," he roared, wigless and coatless, poker in
hand at his chamber-door in the Temple: " What, is it
you, you dogs ? then I'll have a frisk with you." And
off went the good-natured doctor in rusty-brown coat,
baggy small-clothes, and frouzy wig for a morning's
"frisk" among the Covent Garden porters, whose
courtesy was none of the sweetest. By-and-by the
trio adjourned to a tavern and breakfasted on a bowl
of Bishop-a liquor which in Johnson's day, as he
tells us, was composed of wine, oranges, and sugar.</p>
<p>Savage, Sterne, Hogarth, Smollett, Fielding, and


<pb n="34" id="p.34"/>
Goldsmith are all more or less connected with Covent
Garden history. It was from the "Bedford Arms"
Hogarth and his friends set forth on that holiday jaunt
to Gravesend, Rochester, and Sheerness, which reminds
us of a similar jaunt into Kent made a hundred years
later by one Mr. Pickwick and his friends. At
Billingsgate Hogarth and his party took boat, and "with straw
to lie upon, and a tilt over their heads," made the
journey at night, occasionally sleeping, but more often
eating, drinking, and singing jolly choruses. One
of Hogarth's most familiar works, by the way, the
third print of the " Rake's Progress " (published
in 1735), shows the chief room at the " Rose" in
Russell Street, Covent Garden--the " Rose " which
we have already mentioned. Leathercoat, the fellow
with a bright pewter dish and candle, is a portrait.
He had been for many years porter attached to the
house. Smollett took one of his best known characters,
Hugh Strap ("Life and Adventures of Roderick
Random "), from a hairdresser of the neighbourhood.
Fielding, the author of "Tom Jones," was for a time
magistrate at Bow Street.  " A predecessor of mine,"
he wrote, "used to boast that he made &#x00A3; 1000 a year

              <pb n="35" id="p.35"/>
in his office; but how he did this (if indeed he did
it) is to me a secret. His clerk, now mine, told me I
had more business than he had ever known there; I
am sure I had as much as any man could do.  By
composing instead of inflaming the quarrels of porters
and beggars (which I blush when I say hath not been
universally practised), and by refusing to take a
shilling from a man who most undoubtedly would not have
had another left, I had reduced an income of about
&#x00A3;500 a year of the dirtiest money upon earth to a
little more than &#x00A3;300." The office of magistrate at
Bow Street was paid by fees in Fielding's time.<figure id="fig.14" n="tufts:central:dca:MS004:MS004.002.008.DO01.00010"><head></head></figure></p></div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="Chapter IV: THE COVENT GARDEN TAVERNS" id="c4"><head>Chapter IV: THE COVENT GARDEN TAVERNS</head>

<p><figure id="fig.15" n="tufts:central:dca:MS004:MS004.002.008.DO01.00011"><head></head></figure>SUCCESS to the ten acres" (ought it not
to have been, or was; it not "the seven
acres ? ") was originally the first toast of
the evening at the famous
Saturdaynight dinners of the "Sublime Society of Steaks," a
coterie of gentlemen with whom  George, Prince
Regent, was pleased at times to be familiar.  The
"ten acres" represented the land on which Covent
Garden stood, in the parish of St. Martin-in-the-
Fields.  A survival of the designation may still be
traced in the thoroughfare leading from St. Martin's
to Drury Lane, known as Long Acre. Within those
ten (or seven) acres, at the beginning of the present
century, many of the best known and most frequented
London taverns stood.  The "Slaughters"
coffeehouse in St. Martin's Lane was the chief resort of
military officers till supplanted by the United Service Club.

            <pb n="37" id="p.37"/>
In Maiden Lane was the " Bedford Head," a favourite
retreat of journalists.  In Covent Garden itself were
several taverns of reputation, the sole present
representative of which, on the site of the original building, is
the Tavistock Hotel. We have already briefly sketched
the earlier history of that part of the Piazza where it
stands. When the artists had forsaken it, the house
of Thornhill, Wilson, and the others, became the
auction-rooms of George Robins, one of the best known
characters of his day. He was the founder of what
may be termed the florid school of auction oratory,
and a most successful salesman of noblemen's and
gentlemen's estates. His auction-rooms were as famous
in their day as " Christie's " in our own. In his little
world he reigned supreme, and the most august
personages deigned to honour him with their confidence.</p>
<p>But a few days since, while traversing the intricate
passages of the Tavistock in company of its kindly
manager, Mr. Charles Taylor (who, by the way, is as
much part and parcel of the hotel as any beam, staple,
or wall within it), he took us into a low-ceilinged,
dimly-lighted apartment, with a mantelpiece which
our friend, the artist, said was French, of the period

<pb n="38" id="p.38"/>
of the Directorate.  In that little room  George,
Prince of Wales, was the guest of Mr. George Robins,<figure id="fig.16" n="tufts:central:dca:MS004:MS004.002.008.DO01.00012"><head></head></figure>
the famous London auctioneer.  John, some time
head waiter of the establishment (he reigned there
forty years), had it from William, his predecessor, who
waited at table on that interesting occasion. Unfor-

             <pb n="39" id="p.39"/>
tunately, we have no existing record of the dinner then
served, but probably we should not be far wrong if we
set it down somewhat as follows :--A turbot, a Severn
salmon, a haunch of venison, French beans and
cucumbers, a green goose, an apricot tart, and green
peas. Wines: claret, madeira, and port.  What shall
we say, a couple or three bottles per man? As to
what Mr. Robins and the Prince found else to discuss,
or who was present at that little dinner besides
themselves, we have no means of gratifying the curiosity.</p>
<p>Such little incidents of bygone days can be well
supported by satisfactory evidence in respect of the
Tavistock's affairs. There was John, the waiter
aforesaid, for forty years; Smith, his successor, for
twentythree years; there is Lewis (still living, and hale and
hearty as ever), hall-porter now for a period of
thirtyfive years; there is Samuel, of the hall, his comrade,
whose length of service extends to thirty years; George,
chamberlain since 1855: who does not know George
and those who share with him the duties of waiting?
There is his colleague of the chambers, Henry,
with a service of twenty years; and the overseers
of the cellars have been employed among " mag-

<pb n="40" id="p.40"/>
nums" and bins of "very rare and old" for a like
lengthy period. The man of the smoking-room has
been dealing out cigars and materials for punch for a
full decade to our knowledge. Will Messrs. Cassell,
Petter, and Co., Limited, have the goodness to take
note, for award of their biggest silver medal to each
of these for long and faithful domestic service. Mrs.
Arnold, the ancient housekeeper and historian of the
hotel, who dated back-we'll not disclose the year--
left some thousands of pounds of judicious savings to
the Lifeboat Institution and Charing Cross Hospital.
The head coffee-room waiter, her contemporary, died
leaving to a relative almost as many thousands. We
should like to know of another hotel in London that
could show a like gratifying record of its servants.
All the Tavistock's staff happen to be " English, you
know, quite English, you know " (as Mr. Dixey would
say), and this probably accounts for a good deal of the
comfort and attention one enjoys under its roof.</p>
<p>Mr. George Robins, who came into "the Garden"
in 1780, a few years later leased a portion of his place
to Mr. Harrison. This part became, in 1787, the
Tavistock Breakfast Rooms, where, " besides the

           <pb n="41" id="p.41"/>
essential refreshments of tea and coffee, excellent
soups of various kinds are served up with great
neatness.' So ran Mr. Harrison's original advertisement.
At the end of the last century and, indeed, for some
years later, gentlemen lodged at such places as the
"old Hummums" and "the Grand " (now the New
Club), and took their meals out. They breakfasted at
the coffee-house and dined at the tavern. It was not
till long after the Breakfast-rooms had become merged
in the Tavistock Hotel, and the adjoining famous
Piazza Tavern (of which we shall have something to
say presently) was also taken over by Mr. Harrison,
that he undertook to serve dinners to his customers.
And for many years (think of it, ye gourmets of the
present dining-room, who look for your soup, fish,
entree, and the joint straight from the kitchen), the
dinner provided by " the Tavistock " was cooked at a
neighbouring bakery ! There are those who remember
that state of things-when the joints were carried out
and brought back baked in a big tinned dish, like soldiers'
dinners when we were a boy and lived in barracks at
Plymouth. There was a table d'hote--" ordinary" is
the English word-daily at six sharp, at which Mr.

<pb n="42" id="p.42"/>
Harrison himself presided. And in the breakfast, or
"coffee-room," at guest who asked for a hot dish at
breakfast had to content himself with bacon and eggs.
That was the one staple breakfast dish of the Tavistock
Hotel for at least thirty years. It was cooked in the
still-room by the maids. We have heard of a trustful
youth of that time, now an eminent solicitor of
Edinburgh, who asked a waiter for cream. " Cream !"
cried an irate, satin-stocked, old gentleman at his
elbow; "Cream! I take it you're from the country,
Sir. We know of no such luxury here."</p>
<p>The dining-room of most London taverns originally
differed (except as to size), very little from the common
room of a village inn. Sometimes it was partitioned
off into stiff-backed boxes, topped by red curtains,
sometimes not. The seats were not too comfortable,
though of sufficient space to accommodate four, or
perhaps five, on each side of the table; the floor was
uncarpeted and sprinkled with sand, for the better
removal of dirt. In an outer apartment was the bar,
usually shut in, save as to that central part reserved to
the booking and filing of customers' orders, by a
circular glass window. In the passage, where most

<pb n="43" id="p.43"/>
air was to be found, was the larder, oftener than not
a stout iron hoop suspended from tile ceiling and
hung round with hooks, from    which  depended
joints of meat and poultry. Such to the last was the
larder at " Dolly's," of ancient renown.  The cold
cooked meats of the day were usually conveniently
placed within view of persons passing in and out of
the dining-room, in a glass-windowed cupboard. We
have seen a rough sketch of the tavern coffee room to
which poor old Sedley resorted after his downfall in
the city, when he was beginning to dabble in coal. It
is a low-ceilinged parlour, with four stout-legged tables
placed at intervals, the chairs of the hard-backed
kitchen order, the floor carpeted and dotted with
spittoons. Many of us have become acquainted with
such rooms in our rambles through the shires. A
lanky, seedy-looking waiter is lolling against the door,
and a ringleted damsel, smirking to a gentleman who
reminds one of Tittlebat Titmouse, Esquire, waits
without at the bar to accommodate wayfarers with
"choice wines, spirits, and malt liquors."</p>
<p>The better class of taverns had more spacious
dining-rooms, well-upholstered, and displaying a good

<pb n="44" id="p.44"/>
deal of rich-coloured, well-polished mahogany. The
ordincary dininig-hours were from noon to six o'clock,
and at stated intervals during that time prime joints
were sent round from table to table, as we have seen
them sent round at ancient " Dolly's," aforesaid, in
Queen's Head Passage, Paternoster Row, not wheeled
round on little circular tables, as is still the custom at
"Simpson's," but placed before each customer to
allow of his cutting a plateful for himself. The
coffeeroom at the Tavistock Hotel was, till the year 1854 or
thereabouts, carpetless, and sprinkled with sand. A
strip of matting here and there laid down, lent an
appearance of greater warmth to the place in winter.
Our grandfathers (and fathers too) were content with
such primitive comforts; and we are not disposed to
admit that a heavy carpet, receptacle of untold dirt, is
more healthful or pleasant than the clean flooring of
bare boards. For ourselves we prefer the flooring of
bare boards. But this by the way.</p>
<p>The Piazza Tavern (originally the Piazza
Coffeehouse, where Macklin-" a strange character, an
Irishman of rough humour, a good fives player, and a
very promising actor"-had an academy of Belles

Conent Garden.             <pb n="45" id="p.45"/>
Lettres, and delivered public lectures on oratory),
stood next the Tavistock. Mr. Macklin appears to
have made a most ceremonious affair of his " ordinary,"
bringing in the first dish himself with a napkin over
his arm. The price of the dinner was three shillings
(including wine), and when the repast was concluded
he and the company adjourned to the "School of
Oratory."  Leigh Hunt says he embroiled himself
with a variety of his acquaintance, and once in a
sudden quarrel poked out a man's eye with his stick,
and killed him, for which he narrowly escaped
hanging. The Piazza Tavern was subsequently taken over
by Mr. Harrison and incorporated with the Tavistock.
In the early years of this century " the Piazza
Coffeehouse and Tavern " (such was its later designation),
was one of the most splendid establishments of the
kind in town, providing " dinners for large and small
parties in the most consummate style of elegance."
So runs a contemporary advertisement. It attracted
to its table a good many of the customers of " The
Shakespear under the Piazza," where, by the way, was
set up for a time the famous Lion's Head letter-box,
originally at " Button's." "The Shakespear " was the

<pb n="46" id="p.46"/>
first tavern started in Covent Garden. We believe
we are correct in saying that it stood at the corner
of the Piazza, nearest Russell Street. The sign (painted
by Wale and said to have cost nearly &#x00A3;200) projected
at the corner over the street. Three clubs were held
there in the palmy days of John Company, the Madras,
Bengal, and Bombay; the gentlemen who composed
the last being reputed the highest livers. One Twigg
(who had lived in " the Garden " for forty years, 1775-
1815,) was cook to this tavern, and remembered in his
day that " they had as many as fifty turtle at a time,
and that upon an average from ten to fifteen were
dressed per week; and that it was no unusual thing
to send forty quarts of turtle soup a week into the
country, even as far as Yorkshire."  Doubtless Mr.
Jos. Sedley, of Bogglywollah, heard of the repute
of the house when later he sucked up his soup at the
Piazza.  The largest dinner ever dressed at the
Shakespear Tavern in Twigg's time was of " 108
made dishes besides hams, &amp;c., and vegetables."
This was served on the occasion of Lord Keppell being
made First Lord of the Admiralty.</p>
<p>As the "Shakespear's" fame began to wane, the

<pb n="47" id="p.47"/>
Piazza's " appeared in the ascendant. This became
the most popular tavern in London. Of all the public
men of his time, Richard Brinsley Sheridan probably
knew most of the merits<figure id="fig.17" n="tufts:central:dca:MS004:MS004.002.008.DO01.00013"><head></head></figure>
-of a well-roasted
"haunch" and a good
glass of wine. He was
a very constant
customer of the " Piazza,"
as were many of his
friends, as well those of
wit and dramatic talent,
as those of rank.  It
was by an improvisation
at the " Piazza" that
Theodore Hook, when
little more than a lad,
made that favourable
impression on Sheridan which led to his
introduction to the society of the west end of the town
(it had been better for Hook, perhaps, if he had
not been at the tavern that night), where for
many years he reigned supreme as a humourist and

<pb n="48" id="p.48"/>
amateur singer, but without much credit to himself.
The " Piazza " till long after it passed into possession
of Mr. Harrison (the portrait in oils of that
gentleman still hangs in the coffee-room of the Tavistock)
was a famous London rendevous of " men of light
and leading" in every walk of life. The glories of
" the Phoenix dining-room " are yet a tradition among
the servants of the present hotel. We have before us
"A Catalogue of the whole of the excellent
Furniture and appendages of the Piazza Hotel in Covent
Garden . . including the Furniture of the Noble
Phoenix Room," &amp;c., &amp;c., offered for sale by the
Messrs. Robins on the 12th August, 1857, and five
following days, "by direction of the Proprietors, in
consequence of the unlooked for demand of the
premises for the new Royal Italian Opera."  "The
excellent horse-shoe Spanish mahogany table, 114 feet
in length" had borne many a good old English
dinner in its time. One can picture to oneself the
number of stout-looking " elegant cut globular-shaped
quart decanters" filled with the ruby wine of Oporto
that graced those leaves from the mahogany tree.</p>
<p>A little bill which falls under our eye reminds us of

<pb n="49" id="p.49"/>
the truth of a great philosopher's lament, " my days
are swifter than a weaver's shuttle." This little bill
is addressed from  the Tavistock to a distinguished
and popular personage who ruled the adjoining Royal
Italian Opera house before (and after) that fatal night
when Anderson, the Wizard of the North, was
temporarily in occupation of it.  The items are pleasant to
the fancy :-" 4 cold fowls; 3 pheasants; 2 tongues;
piece of rolled beef; 2 jellies and tarts; bread and
butter, &amp;c.; 4 bottles of Clicquot (at 12S. 6d. the
bottle), 1 of sherry at 6s."  A very appetizing little
supper.  O courteous shade of Mario the superb !
tell us who were of the party that night ? Are they all
with you in the land of shadows, or do any linger
with us still?   When that feast was served     thy
name was in every man's mouth, and thy song stayed
upon the ear.  And now-where's thy renown ?</p>
<quote rend="blockquote">" The noise
Of worldly fame is but a blast of wind,
That blows from diverse points, and shifts its name
Shifting the point it blows from. Shalt thou more
Live in the mouths of mankind, if thy flesh
Part shrivell'd from thee, than if thou hadst died
Before the coral and the pap were left?"</quote>


<pb n="50" id="p.50"/>
<p>Who were "the Astronomicals" that held such
famous feasts in "the noble Phoenix Room," who
there dined together once a month, and took each
his bottle like a man?  Were they legendary
"astronomicals," gentlemen who studied the stars at
midnight in the neighbourhood of the Haymarket,
having well polished their wits with wine, or were
they real " astronomicals," professors of the science
who loved to discuss the flight of comets over
a bottle laid down in a comet year? But sherry
appears to have been the favourite tipple of these
worthies, though port makes a fair show in the bill.
Thirty bottles of wine among twenty gentlemen is not
so bad! Then there were "the Auctioneers "
great diners in their day; "our esteemed and
distinguished" Mr. Edward Robins in the chair. "The
Auctioneers" also took their bottle per man; and
what's more, something in the nature of cooling
beverages afterwards.  Their little  account for
" eleven dinners " includes six bottles of sherry,
two of port, three of very special ditto, two
Clicquot's champagne, a bottle of brandy, and (Lud!
what stomachs these gentlemen must have enjoyed)

<pb n="51" id="p.51"/>
ten pints of ale and sundry "ale cups" to wind up
with!</p>
<p>Between the " Shakespear" and " Piazza " taverns
stood the "Bedford Coffee-house," later tavern and
hotel. We are inclined to think that the
"Shakespear" ultimately became part of it, for the Lion's
Head (its mouth still open for the reception of
such intelligence as shall be thrown into it) passed
into possession of the proprietor of the " Bedford," by
whom it was sold to Richardson, who leased the hotel
which subsequently became Evans's. From
Richardson's it went to Woburn Abbey, being bought by the
Duke of Bedford. Few modern chroniclers of London
make mention of the "Shakespear," but it was a
place of great repute in its day. The waiters there
dressed smartly in ruffles and knee breeches, and it
was thought a bad week if each man had not made his
pound a day. The Beefsteak Club, driven out of
Covent Garden Theatre, took refuge for a time at
the "Shakespear " and later at the " Bedford."  The
history of that club is well known. Among its
members were the Prince of Wales, the Duke of Norfolk,
the Duke of Sussex, Lord Grantley, Sir J. Scott, Mr.

<pb n="52" id="p.52"/>
Ellis, J. Kemble ("expelled for his mode of conduct "),
J. Scott, Captain Morris, Wilkes (the sublime),
Munden, and Fawcett. Nothing but beefsteaks and port
wine, onions and potatoes, were by custom allowed;
but this rule can hardly have been rigidly enforced, for
Twigg (the cook already named) remembered having
served " three or four of the members with fish; and
in April a rump of beef has been roasted and eat cold
with salads." Tradition says that the Duke of Norfolk
was an enormous eater, and would "put away" his
" three or four pounds of beefsteak, and after that take
a Spanish onion and a beet-root, chop them together
with oil and vinegar, and eat that." Such a meal
with (say) three bottles of port wine, and a rummer or
two of punch must have produced, one would have
thought, something of a head in the morning. But
then there were giants in those days, and his Grace of
Norfolk was not the least vigorous among them if we
may credit the stories of his table exploits taken from
contemporary records.</p>
<p>That long, low, dimly lighted, and badly
ventilated coffee-room of the old " Bedford " (now doing
service as a fruiterer's store) has a curious history

<pb n="53" id="p.53"/>
if one did but know it. At the upper end (when
we entered it last) there was a raised floor separated
from the main apartment by an alcove-a kind of
snuggery which had doubtless served as a sanctum
sanctorum to generations of diners, from the days of
Addison to those of Thackeray. After Addison died
and Steele had retired into Wales, the customers of
"Button's " in Russell Street mostly passed over to
the "Shakespear" and "Bedford."  Looking up at
the rows of bells in the passage of that ancient hostelry,
the other day, we noted the " Dryden " and "Russell "
rooms, survivals of that period now considerably more
than a hundred years ago. The "Bedford
Coffeehouse " was a favourite rendezvous of the actors of
the past and beginning of the present century, of whom
Garrick, Quin, Foote, Murphy, Macklin, Munden,
Fawcett, Charles Kemble, John Philip Kemble,
Cooke, Young, Liston, and Farren, are perhaps now
best remembered. It was in a room at the " Bedford "
Richard Brinsley Sheridan proposed to fight out the
interrupted duel with Captain Matthews, his rival for
the hand of beautiful Miss Linley, of Bath, whom
Sheridan married. The master being alarmed they

<pb n="54" id="p.54"/>
went away to the Castle Tavern in Henrietta
Street close by, where they played their little game
out. It was never satisfactorily explained to the public
who was the better swordsman. " Almost immediately
on entering the room we engaged. I struck Mr.
Matthews' point so much out of the line, that I stepped
up and caught hold of his wrist or the hilt of his sword,
while the point of mine was at his breast. You ran
in and caught hold of my arm exclaiming, ' Don't kill
him !' I struggled, and said his sword was in my
power. Mr. Matthews' called out twice or thrice,
'I beg my life !'-we were parted."  Finally, after an
altercation "with much heat," Mr. Sheridan broke
Mr. Matthews' sword and flung the hilt to the other
end of the room. Such was Mr. Sheridan's version
of the Henrietta Street duel. We are not much
concerned now to know who was in the right and who
was in the wrong, or whether Mr. Sheridan's
potations deep had not overbalanced his memory.
"Young Mr. Sheridan " (whose reputation dates from
the beautiful Miss Linley affair) has lain for half a
century past in Westminster Abbey.  <foreign lang="LA">Requiescat in
pace</foreign>.</p>

<pb n="55" id="p.55"/>
<p>There was a famous bully at the " Bedford " in the
time when Sheridan was in truth young Mr. Sheridan,
called Tiger Roach. " He used to sit with a
halfstarved look, a black patch upon his cheek, pale with
the idea of murder, or with rank cowardice, a
quivering look, and a downcast eye. In that manner he
used to sit at table all alone and his soliloquy
interrupted now and then with faint attempts to throw off
a little saliva was to the following effect :-' Hut!
hut ! a mercer's 'prentice with a bag-wig: d-n my
s-l if I would not skiver a dozen of them like larks !
Hut ! hut! I don't understand such airs ! I'd cudgel
him, back, breast, and belly for three skips of a louse!
How do you do, Pat ! Hut ! hut ! God's blood-
Larry, I'm glad to see you !-'Prentices-a fine thing
indeed ! Hut! hut! how d'ye do, Dominick ! D-n
my s-1, what's here to do?' These were the
meditations of this agreeable youth. From one of these
reveries he started up one night when I was there,
called a Mr. Bagnell out of the room, and most
heroically stabbed him in the dark, the other having no
weapon to defend himself with. In this career the
'Tiger' persisted, till at length a Mr. Lennard bran-

<pb n="56" id="p.56"/>
dished a whip over his head, and stood in a menacing
attitude, commanding him to ask pardon directly.
The 'Tiger' shrank from the danger with a 'Hut!
hut! what signifies it between you and me ? Well !
well! I ask your pardon.' "  Thus Arthur Murphy
to David Garrick.  Murphy was, in turns, player,
barrister, and hack-writer for the booksellers, and
ended by becoming a Commissioner of Bankrupts.
He lived, it was said, on "potted stories," but the
foregoing presents too amusing a likeness of a tavern
bully of the period to be criticised too minutely. The
present representative of the " Bedford Coffee-house,
tavern and hotel " is the new red brick building
standing at the corner of James Street, with an entrance
under the north-western Piazza.</p>
<p>The new and old Hummums hotels in the
southwestern Piazza (both have been pulled down within
recent times, and a new building and flower-market
have taken their place) were quiet, old-fashioned
places, whereat some unusual facilities appear to
have been afforded in Dr. Johnson's time for taking
the warm bath. The old Hummums was the first,
and for many years, the only lodging-house within

<pb n="57" id="p.57"/>
Covent Garden. The name is but another rendering
of the Hamman or Turkish bathing-place of our day.
In the fourth decade of the century "Clunn's" and
" Evans's " were added to the list of famous Covent
Garden taverns. These are to be traced from the
original Grand Hotel, the first of its name in London
(Mr. Holland please take note), which was opened in
what had formerly been the mansion of Lord Orford,
and subsequently of Lord Archer. "Clunn's,"
formerly " Richardson's," had a famous port wine,
venison, and turtle reputation; and "Evans's" was best
known for its songs and suppers, and for the genial
spirit who presided in the supper room, Mr. John
Green, better known as " Paddy   Green."  The
"Savage Club" had rooms at Evans's, and later it
became the Falstaff Club, which had its day, and ceased
to be, giving place to the New Club still in existence.</p>
<p>Not a few of us remember Evans's and maybe
look back upon the evenings spent in the supper
rooms, twenty-five years ago, with less of self-reproach
than on some other evenings spent elsewhere. Ah
me ! we are young but once, and when we remember
that time of youth we are still young. We confess

<pb n="58" id="p.58"/>
to a lingering regret when we think upon the songs,
chops, and stout of Evans's.  What a jolly old
place it was ! The very atmosphere of the hotel itself
was old
English.<figure id="fig.18" n="tufts:central:dca:MS004:MS004.002.008.DO01.00014"><head></head></figure> As you
passed up the
flight of
wellworn stone
steps with the
rickety  iron
railings which
had helped up
many an
owner of an
equally
rickety  pair
of gouty old
feet,  a
fullflavoured puff
of warm air
came rushing out upon you from   the cosey old
entrance-hall. Not an offensive puff of warm air,
but one that suggested toothsome morsels of green fat,

<pb n="59" id="p.59"/>
simmering in the copper stewpans below, with just the
suspicion of a smell from the well-roasted " haunch "
or " saddle" standing before the kitchen fire, waiting
to be called as the "six o'clock joint."  Those were
the days when active and healthy men " tackled" the
joint with vigour about the hour of six, afternoon.
There was a port-wine look in the very appearance of
the hall table (old members of the Savage Club will
remember that table); it had a rich deep mahogany
polish upon it, such as is seldom seen now-a-days,
which seemed to bespeak the ease and precision with
which a stout jolly-looking decanter of " very curious
and old " had passed from man to man upon its shining
surface. And Mr. John Green was not lacking the
mellow port-winey look.  The days of three-bottle
men had, doubtless, not been without their influence
on Mr. John Green, who was the personification of a
stout, cheery, open-hearted, kindly English landlord.
We have him in our mind's eye now, standing with
his back to a blazing coal fire, red silk pocket-
handkerchief in one hand, snuff box in the other: a prim,
neat-looking old gentleman of hard upon threescore
years and ten, with an excessively red face, and a

<pb n="60" id="p.60"/>
great deal of very grey hair, dressed in a black dress
coat, black trousers and waistcoat, and wearing a
profusion of shirt-collar of the time-honoured Gladstonian
pattern, encircled by an ample old-fashioned black
satin stock. His familiar salutation, "Ah, dear boy !
How d'ye do, dear boy?" is still remembered among
men in the remorseful forties. It was Mr. Green's
nature, and part of his every night duty, to be cordial
and affable with everyone.</p>
<p>As we remember " Evans's Supper-room," it was a
hall capable of holding comfortably about eight
hundred eaters of suppers. A number of ordinary
restaurant tables, set about in rows, ran the length of the
hall, four chairs to each. The upper portion was
separated from the lower by a row of four Corinthian
columns very elaborately gilded; and in this part the
walls displayed a number of portraits of leading English
actors and actresses, from Nell Gwynne's time
downwards. At the extreme upper end was a small
unadorned stage, destitute of anything in the shape of
scenery, the only articles of furniture upon it being a
piano and harmonium. To the right, a little above
the stage, let into the wall so as to communicate with

<pb n="61" id="p.61"/>
the hotel, was a small screened room,-reputed to
have been the chamber in which Fanny Kemble was
born. This ' box," so-called, was reserved for guests
of the hotel and others, who, by pre-arrangement, and
on the understanding that a supper was ordered, might
be accompanied by ladies. The floor of the hall was
reserved solely to gentlemen-at least in Paddy
Green's time.</p>
<p>The refreshments served consisted of what are
know as " grills "-chops, steaks, broiled kidneys,
poached eggs and bacon, "devilled" bones, Welsh
rarebits, anchovy toasts, and potatoes baked in their
jackets. 'The entertainment provided was singing.
Old English glees and madrigals were sung by a
choir of men and boys, this part of the evening's
entertainment being varied occasionally by a little tumbling
and juggling-brass rings and balancing-rod business
--and by the performances of Herr von Joel on the
penny tin whistle. Herr von Joel handed about his
cigar-box during the early part of the evening, and
drank a good deal of what was offered him by
convivial young gentlemen, and then went upon the stage
and played his penny whistle. " Evans's" was the

<pb n="62" id="p.62"/>
best-conducted of the London supper-rooms (its
reputation fell away in later times) ; and except on festival
occasions, such as the Universities Boat-race day, and
the eve of " the Derby," was as quiet and orderly a
place as a gentleman might wish to eat his supper in.
There was no vulgarity that we remember, and no
Music-hall trash of the " La-di-da " school. Everyone
seemed to be satisfied with his sixpence-worth of
songs ; and if the sums levied by " John " at the door
were not always clear and correct by the unwritten
tariff, that little inconvenience seldom  stayed the
hungry man on his way to the supper-rooms again.</p>
<p>No one knew the old Covent Garden taverns better
than Thackeray, a man who relished their snugness
and hospitality as much as did his learned predecessor
Dr. J ohnson, the vates sacer of taverns. Most respected
and virtuous Reader, who loves the writings of the
Master as we do, William  Makepeace Thackeray
was not always the circumspect, prudent, stately,
greyhaired gentleman of the old Court suburb and the
clubs as we remember him. He had been merry and
young like the most of us. He had lost his way in
Bohemia, as many another traveller has done going

<pb n="63" id="p.63"/>
through the world. We have his own confession that
he once knew Bohemia " very well." <note place="foot" n="1">" The Adventures of Philip."</note> "A pleasant
land," he calls it, "not fenced with drab stucco like
Tyburnia or Belgravia; not guarded by a large army
of footmen; not echoing with noble chariots; not
replete with chintz drawing-rooms and neat tea-tables:
a land over which hangs an endless fog, occasioned
by much tobacco; a land of chambers, billiard-rooms,
supper-rooms, oysters; a land of song; a land where
soda-water flows freely in the morning; a land of tin
dish covers from taverns, and frothing porter; a land
of lotos-eating (with lots of cayenne pepper); . . . a
land where men call each other by their Christian
names, where most are poor, where almost all are
young, and where if a few oldsters do enter, it is
because they have preserved more carefully and
tenderly than other folks their youthful spirits, and
the delightful capacity to be idle."  Yes, William
Makepeace Thackeray knew the land of taverns
and the country of Bohemia.  The characters in
his novels are constantly hovering around and
about them : Major Dobbin, Lieutenant Osborne,


<pb n="64" id="p.64"/>

Jos. Sedley, of the Company's service, Collector at
Bogglywollah ; Clive Newcome, son of the excellent
Colonel; Mr. Arthur Pendennis; the Major, his worthy
uncle; Mr. Warrington (and his remote ancestors,
the Virginians); rackety Captain Shandon of the
Fleet; " honest Jack Finucane; Captain Costigan,
and the rest.  Major Arthur Pendennis-" Major
Arthur Pendennis, in the best blacked boots in all
London, with a checked cravat that was never rumpled
till dinner-time, a buff waistcoat, which bore the crown
of his sovereign on the buttons, and linen so spotless
that Mr. Brummel himself once asked the name of
his laundress "-would, when not dining at his club
or with the most noble the Marquis of Steyne, or
Lord Hobanob, or the Duke of St. David's, betake
himself to the famous Piazza Tavern (Mr. Thomas
Harrison ruled there then) to partake of a good old
English dinner, served in a richly-browned good old
English dining-room. Of what did the " good old
English dinner" of that period of our social history
consist ? It was about the time of Waterloo, when
young Osborne was bent upon thrashing " that
infernal scoundrel Boney ;" but was more pleasantly

                           <pb n="65" id="p.65"/>

occupied for a time in dawdling after Mrs. Rawdon
Crawley at Knightsbridge, and in spending old
Osborne's money about town.</p>
  <p>Thomas Walker ("original" Walker), the Lambeth
police magistrate, who some twenty years after preached
the virtue of a simple style in respect of dining, has left
on record his ideas of English dinners. "If I might
have my choice I should adopt the simple English
style [of cookery] for my regular diet, diversifying it
only occasionally with the French. I like, as a rule,
to abstain from much variety at the same meal."
Here are some of his examples of a wholesome, albeit
epicurean, English dinner: No. I. Turtle, followed
by no other fish but whitebait (with abundance of
brown bread and butter), which is to be followed by
no other meat but grouse, succeeded by simple apple
fritters and jelly, an ice, a cup of coffee and one glass
of liqueur. The wines, punch, champagne and claret.
No. 2 (for Christmas). Crimped cod, woodcocks,
and plum-pudding.   Wines, champagne, and, after
dinner, mulled claret. No. 3. Spring soup, turbot,
"with first-rate lobster sauce," cucumber, and new
potatoes; ribs of beef, French beans, and salad; next

<pb n="66" id="p.66"/>

a very fine dressed crab; and lastly, some jelly. The
wines, champagne, port, and claret.  No. 4 (at the
Athenaeum Club). A dozen and a-half of oysters, a
dish of fine flounders, water-zoutcheed, with plenty of
brown bread and butter; then a brace of grouse with
French beans. Wines, sherry, and claret.</p>
  <p>A more recent authority has given us his views in
respect of an English dinner-a real English dinner, in
the simple English style. Mr. Robert, most amusing
and instructive of City officials (everyone, of course,
has read Mr. Robert's Diary, published by Messrs.
Bradbury, Agnew, and Co.; if not, let everyone take
our advice and at once buy a copy): Mr. Robert has
given us his notions, and very pleasant notions they are,
of an English dinner. It was served to four foreign
gentlemen at their very particular request, Mr. Robert
himself having carte blanche in arranging the bill
of fare. Here it is: Real turtle soup; a lovely turbot;
a real English rumpsteak ("such as no Frenchman
ever seed in his own country," if the London
correspondent of the Paris Figaro will pardon our
presumption in transcribing Mr. Robert's own opinion), with
three dozen native oysters done in butter; and lots of

                             <pb n="67" id="p.67"/>

game to follow. These foreign gentlemen took Punch
with the soup; Johannisberg with the fish; " a bottle of
our oldest champagne " with the steak; Burgundy with
the game (a couple of brace of grouse, we take it; a
bird per man, eh, Mr. Robert?), and some '47 Port
with their cheese.  After such a dinner, we should
be inclined to join hands and dance "Here we go
round the mulberry bush " with even the most
hypercritical of French critics.</p>
  <p>The " simple English style " was, beyond question,
an uncommonly good style, and we may take it that
Major Arthur Pendennis, who was a grand master of
the mode, practised it whenever he condescended to
favour Mr. Harrison, of the Piazza Tavern, with his
commands.</p>
  <p>It was to the Tavistock Hotel Mr. Harry Foker was
accustomed to go whenever he came to London, which
was pretty frequently. Mr. Harry Foker, of St.
Boniface College, Oxbridge, the lively son of Mr. Foker
(Foker's Entire) and Lady Agnes Foker.  Thither
also went, in the days preceding the finding of
Warrington in the Temple, and the founding of that
wellknown journal written for gentlemen by gentlemen,

<pb n="68" id="p.68"/>

"The Pall Mall Gazette," young Mr. Pendennis, and
his friend Mr. Bloundell, who had a tick at "The
Tavistock."  This was, of course, before those little
cards came into vogue at the hotel, on which is stated
the sum total of a customer's daily or weekly liability,
the exactness of which may be ascertained by
consultation of the clerk at the desk. From " The
Tavistock" these young gentlemen sallied forth of nights,
and partook pretty freely of the pleasures of the town,
which have been equally "freely" enjoyed from the
same quarter by subsequent generations of young men
from the Universities who patronize " The Tavistock "
on the festival occasions of their alma mater.
Whenever Mr. Hobnell came to town, " Squire Hobnell, of
the Warren," near to Mr. Pendennis's paternal home
of Fairoaks; whenever he came to London for a lark,
and this was commonly once a year, "when Mrs.
Hobnell could not leave the increasing duties of the
nursery," he also had rooms there. When he was in
London (he was accustomed to say) he liked to do as
London does, "and go it a bit."  He attended all the
theatres, music-halls, casinos, and convivial taverns of
the day; and when he returned to the west, carried
<pb n="69" id="p.69"/>
  <figure id="fig.19" n="tufts:central:dca:MS004:MS004.002.008.DO01.00015"><head>" Mr. Charles Taylor, who after twenty-five years' service
became managing-director."-P. 80.</head></figure>
                                <pb n="71" id="p.71"/>

along with him a beautiful new bonnet and shawl for
Mrs. Hobnell, by way, we surmise, of frustrating that
worthy woman's too-inquisitive inquiry as to the
expenses of his trip. How many of us have brought
similar peace offerings to the domestic altar, after
going it a bit in London ?</p>
  <p>What used to take the gay young students of the
Universities, and the more sedate old bucks of the
clubs, and the Squire Hobnells of " the Warren,"
and the Mr. Sam Huxters, their rollicking friends, and
the notable men of the Press, and the dramatists and
artists, their confreres, and the leading men from
Sheffield, Glasgow, Manchester, and the like : what used to
take all these excellent fellows to the joyous
neighbourhood of Covent Garden, and the welcome shelter of
" the old Tavistock"? We think we may find a
satisfactory answer. " The Tavistock " has been for many
a long year to numberless travellers the most "
clubable" hotel in London. The phrase is Johnsonian
and signifies, as applied to man, sociableness and good
comradeship. It has far more of the essential part of
a good club than the considerable majority of modern
London clubs, and possesses all their comforts without
half their restrictions.</p>
<pb n="72" id="p.72"/>

  <p>A few years ago, a barrister died who had occupied
the same bedroom in the hotel for twenty-eight years.
He had come in casually one night and stayed on till
his death. Another old gentleman who, later, became
his most intimate friend, " happened in " (as the
Americans say) in the same casual way (having journeyed
per "Ramchunder," East Indiaman, Captain Bragg,
from Madras), and he occupied his bedroom, taken for
one night, for fifteen years. The sympathy between
these two old gentlemen grew to be such that the one
was never at his ease without the other. If one did not
appear at the proper hour in the coffee-room at
breakfast, the other fidgetted about till he had ascertained
the cause. If one was ill, the other was at his wit's
end to make him well. By-and-by they quarrelled.
They quarrelled and avoided each other's society
for a fortnight. The two were thoroughly miserable.
At length the offender growing weary of his offence,
went to his room  and wrote a letter of penance,
which was duly delivered to the offendee, silently
sipping his tea at breakfast. He hurried out of the
coffee-room and, on its threshold, ran into the arms of
his friend bent on a similar errand of instant reconciliation.

                                <pb n="73" id="p.73"/>

 The two-well, we do not know that there is
anything we need be ashamed to disclose. The sacred
source of sympathetic tears overflowed, and the two
grasped hands of affectionate reconciliation.  This
friendship became of such sturdy strength long after
the period when lasting friendships are usually made,
and it grew up at the Tavistock.</p>
  <p>One day one of these old gentlemen did not come
down to his customary breakfast in the coffee-room.
" An hour or two passed and we grew concerned about
him," said Mr. Taylor, relating this incident to us.
"We finally opened his door; and when I went into
his room I had a feeling that I was intruding. He
was seated in his armchair. He had wound up his
watch, the end of his cigar lay upon the edge of the
table, and 'The Newcomes' had fallen from his hand
upon the floor. He was as if in sleep, peaceful, and
resting." Death had stolen in quietly to that chamber
and beckoned him away. This old guest of "The
Tavistock" had come from the land where Colonel
Newcome spent the best years of his life; and of him
he was no unworthy counterpart in respect of
cherishing a high sense of honour and a punctilious observance

<pb n="74" id="p.74"/>

 of the conduct of a gentleman. His memory is
still held in affectionate remembrance at the old hotel
in Covent Garden where he lived so many years.</p>
  <p>The domestic history of " The Tavistock " might furnish <figure id="fig.20" n="tufts:central:dca:MS004:MS004.002.008.DO01.00016"><head></head></figure>
 a readable contribution to the popular literature of
the day. Like every other old London hotel it could
a tale (a series of tales) unfold, though no love stories
mingle with its record. But here we speak without
authority, never having been admitted within the
                                  <pb n="75" id="p.75"/>

peaceful precincts of the room dedicated to the ladies
of the bar. It still rigidly adheres to the old-
established rule of the house, to receive none but
gentlemen as guests. Only the other day we saw a
comfortable-looking couple, evidently on a visit to London
from the country, drive up to the hotel with a view,
no doubt, to sojourning there.  But the hall-porter
civilly waved them away, with a recommendation to try
"The Bedford." The only skirts one sees fluttering
about "The Tavistock" corridors are the pink and
white skirts of the housemaids.  And of these the
slyest rogue can catch but a hasty glimpse; though
we have heard it said that the wearers can show some
of the prettiest faces in London. For ourselves, we
have never had the privilege of the sight of one, and
can only repeat what has been told us by those who
have.</p>
  <p>The duties of the chamber are mostly done by
chamberlains-personages of the sterner sex. Was it
not a Judge of the Supreme Court, sitting on the Bench
in open court, who not a great while ago asked leading
counsel learned in the law to describe the functions
of an hotel "chamberlain," thinking it but a pompous

<pb n="76" id="p.76"/>

application of a courtly word. But here stands the
precise meaning in the dictionary: " Chamberlain-An
attendant who has charge of the chambers, as in a
large house or hotel."  The chamberlains of " The
Tavistock," as becomes the retainers of an hotel so
long established and eminently reputable, are staid,
middle-aged, attentive, and trustworthy-retainers, in
fact, of the good old stamp common enough fifty years
ago. Talking of servants of that class, we remember
many years ago that an old gentleman told us how he
had once dined with an eccentric, but rich citizen of
Bath, who was shabby enough to keep his good wine in
the cellars till his guests had well drunk of the bad. The
old butler who waited at table being requested to pass
the wine to the guest aforesaid, leant over and filled his
glass, and at the same time whispered in his ear, " Don't
drink it; I'm going down to bring up some better."
There was a touch of courtesy in that act which must
have been grateful to the guest, and not altogether
displeasing to the host, if ever he came to learn of it,
for it showed that master and man understood and
humoured each other's peculiarities.</p>
  <p>Many an eccentric old gentleman has partaken of
                               <pb n="77" id="p.77"/>

the hospitality of " The Tavistock." We knew of one
who had such a horror of being in debt, that he never
went to his breakfast in the coffee-room but he laid
down half-a-sovereign forthwith on the table to pay
for his bed and breakfast. When he arrived, he
invariably handed, without remark, a sixpence to the
chamberlain at the top of the stairs, which that
functionary, knowing his taste, forthwith exchanged for a
glass of whiskey. He prided himself on never being
without a L's worth of silver for " tips," and when he lay
a-dying requested to be accommodated with change for
a sovereign. It is interesting to know that he died
worth L6o,ooo, and left &#x00A3;20 to be divided among so
many of "The Tavistock's " servants as had attended
upon him for twenty-five years ! There was another old
customer whose name appeared on the hotel's books for
a period of sixty years. Whenever he came he brought
with him a stout oak chest (a sort of muniment chest)
which required the united efforts of three lusty porters
to carry it from the hall to his bedroom. He was a
Renter of Drury Lane Theatre, and religiously
attended the performances at that theatre to "have his
money's worth." He stood, so to say, upon his rights,
<pb n="78" id="p.78"/>

and paid a fairish hotel bill in order that he might
duly assert them. The tradition of the smoking-room
is that he would sit upon the steps of the portico of
the theatre in order to be the first in.</p>
  <p>How long have we now known this old English
home in the joyous neighbourhood of Covent Garden ?
We took our first cut of mutton there with a kindly
Australian who had made his " pile " at Ballarat, in the
month of October, 1854, being at that period of our
history a lad of the Grey Friars' Monastery by Newgate:
so that our experience of its comforts is not solely of
to-day. We have said that in our opinion the popularity
of " The Tavistock " is largely due to the fact that it is
as much club as hotel. The black-ball has no force,
and does not exclude; but if you go there, it is taken
on trust that you are a gentleman. Each guest seems
to be on terms of acquaintance with the other guests;
a man meets his fellow there as if he were an honest
fellow, and not a knave; and there gentlemen talk
to each other without fear of being hurt or
contaminated by the act of letting the mouth speak.
If you should happen to ask of a stranger the way to
the Dining-room, he does not turn his head over a

                  Covent Garden.                <pb n="79" id="p.79"/>

throat-cutting collar, and lisp like an idiot, "I dawnt
knaw." If you should venture a remark with your
neighbour in the writing-room, he does not lift his
eyes with amazement, and examine you from head to
foot with the calm insolence of the British snob. If
you should slip into an unoccupied chair in a crowded
room, your fellow-guest does not resent your coming
as if you had been a poor, uneducated, fustian-
smelling costermonger of "the Garden." In short, if to
"The Tavistock " you go, your presence there shows
you to be a reasonable man. You need not hold your
card-case in your hand, nor are you obliged to begin
a conversation by first nominating (as Americans say)
committee on credentials.
</p>
  <p>When an hotel can boast of a record of unbroken
prosperity for a hundred years, we may be very sure
that the management has been personal, active, and
painstaking. The original Mr. Thomas Harrison in
due time gave place to his son, Mr. Frederick Burgoyne
Harrison, whose tall, handsome presence and
courteous bearing are still remembered at "The Tavistock."
We have heard it said that it was reluctantly he took to
the business of hotel-keeping. In America, to " run a
<pb id="p.80" n="80"/>

hotel " is the height of many a " live " man's ambition.
We were acquainted with a prominent hotel-keeper of
Boston, U.S.A., who was also a litterateur of some
distinction, and editor of a daily paper. Mr. Frederick
Harrison was originally an engineer student in the
workshops of Messrs. Penn.  He was a man of
considerable ability, and when he succeeded his
father, even though the business was distasteful to
him, did what he had to do with his might. "The
Tavistock" became the most popular hotel in London
under his direction. It remained under control of
the Harrison family till I886, the responsible
management for the later part of the time devolving upon Mr.
Charles Taylor, who, after twenty-five years' service,
ultimately became managing director, when the hotel
was purchased by a company. Mr. Taylor wisely
made no changes in the domestic arrangements of the
place. The services of all the old servants were
retained. The time-honoured traditions of " The
Tavistock " were scrupulously preserved. The bowl
without handles, a survival of the dish-of-tea period of
Johnson, still made its appearance in the coffee-room.
Everyone took his turn in stirring the Christmas pud-

                  Covent Garden.                 <pb n="81" id="p.81"/>

ding as of yore. The guests were invited to that
interesting ceremony as usual. The big bowl of punch
was brewed as carefully on New Year's Eve, and
placed as joyously in the holly-decked coffee-room, as
had been the custom every New Year's Eve for many
a year; and the mingled materials, hot and steaming,
were ladled out generously to all comers. Manager,
manager's friends and neighbours, customers, guests,
cook, chamberlains, housemaids, waiters, porters, and
all other the grand array of retainers came to the
Christmas feast at Christmas-tide, and sat together as
our ancestors used to sit, in good old English fashion,
in the grand old hall of the grand old mansion, the
distinction of " the salt " being abolished for the occasion.
The Boxing-night festivities were kept up with all the
old frolic and fun-the dance, the supper (supper
"with champagne " and the rest, after the fashion of
ball suppers of people of degree), with an occasional
dramatic entertainment " by the company " to play the
guests in.</p>
 <p> But if " The Tavistock " management is wise in
respecting the traditions of the hotel (there is one
thing about those traditions which is noteworthy:

<pb n="82" id="p.82"/>

they are more kindly than costly, and are
profitable in showing the servants that their zeal and
trustworthiness are appreciated): if those traditions
are still kept up, it must not be supposed that
the hotel has not advanced with the times.  You
will find the work of Inigo Jones still supporting the
house (go down in the wine cellars and examine it),
but other architects have from time to time extended
and improved the original structure. In I86I a new
wing was added, giving additional accommodation to
the extent of sixty-five rooms, exclusive of the present
dining-room. This improvement cost upwards of
LI3,000. The ground which was cleared for this
new building formed part of the ground belonging
to the original convent. We need hardly inform the
reader that " Covent Garden " is a corruption of
Convent Garden, which was the burying-place belonging
to the Abbots of Westminster in the early part of the
thirteenth century.</p>
  <p>In making the necessary excavations for the new
wing the workmen came upon large quantities of
human bones; and some very interesting ancient
earthen jars and water-vessels. There was a law suit,
                 C               <pb n="83" id="p.83"/>

we believe, between Mr. F. Gye and Mr. Harrison,
touching the rightful ownership of this plot. A man
"in possession" for one of the parties is stated to
have held it for three years-till, in fact, the law suit
was ended-who from his primitive mode of life and
rough habitation became known in the neighbourhood
as Robinson Crusoe.   In 1867, the old red-brick
frontage of the hotel overlooking the market was
stuccoed, and other alterations were carried out on
the upper floor, where the bedrooms (till quite recent
time called dormitories) looked out upon the leads.
The late Sir Michael Bass had always a preference for
one of those old bedrooms, as it was convenient for
getting out of the window on to the leads in summer
time, to smoke. " No. 123" became known as " Mr.
Bass's Room," just as other rooms in "The
Tavistock" are connected with the names of other old
customers. The stairway leading to that room (from
which the Surrey hills might be seen on a clear day)
was an interesting relic of the original dwelling-house
of Charles II.'s reign. With the exception of part
of the existing cellarage, it was probably the last of
the original architect's work.</p>

<pb n="84" id="p.84"/>

<p>These improvements were carried further (the Duke
<figure id="fig.21" n="tufts:central:dca:MS004:MS004.002.008.DO01.00017"><head></head></figure>
of Bedford having granted an extension of lease), by
the addition, in 1875, of the James Street wing, comprising
                                 <pb n="85" id="p.85"/>

 additional accommodation, which included the
present Smoking-room, and two Billiard-rooms below.
In the course of fifteen years, the proprietors had
added 132 rooms, and effected other considerable
improvements in the Tavistock Hotel at a cost of
&#x00A3;35,ooo. An excellent example of the present
architect's work may be seen in the Smoking-room, which is
unquestionably one of the most comfortable and best
ventilated in London. We have seen the right
honourable and distinguished member for Central
Birmingham, with Mr. Jacob Bright, in a snug corner of that
room; in another corner a well-known dramatist and
man of letters; and in yet another, the most popular
English actor of the day discussing affairs with other
popular English actors of the day. We have not
sufficient space (nor yet the inclination) to tell the
names of those above the rank of men of means, and
mere "swells," of which all first-class hotels can show
a plethora, who have sojourned at "The Tavistock."
We asked Mr. Taylor to name a distinguished
person or two of his day, and he led off with Dr.
Livingstone, the African Traveller. Charles Sumner,
the American statesman; Sir Wm. Rae, M. D.,
<pb n="86" id="p.86"/>

of Arctic fame; Captain (now Admiral) Inglefield,
commander in three Arctic expeditions; M. Edmond
About, editor of the Radical "Le XIX&#x00B0; Siecle," and
formerly of the " Gaulois " and "Soir " newspapers;
<figure id="fig.22" n="tufts:central:dca:MS004:MS004.002.008.DO01.00018"><head></head></figure>
Grant and Speke, African explorers; Dr. Kirke, of
Zanzibar; Forrest and Booth, American tragedians;
W. H. Wills, the dramatist, and a host of others
might be named among constant customers of the old
Tavistock. We say nothing of Provosts and Bailies,
<pb n="87" id="p.87"/><figure id="fig.23" n="tufts:central:dca:MS004:MS004.002.008.DO01.00019"><head>The Reading Room</head></figure>
                            <pb n="89" id="p.89"/>

and Mayors, aye, and Lord Mayors, and men with big
schemes " to shove through Parliament," and builders
of bridges and aqueducts, and great ironmasters, your
Crawshays, Armstrongs, Whitworths, and the like; and
merchants and shipowners of Sheffield, Birmingham,
Manchester, and Liverpool, and rich people like
Allsopp and Bass: we say nothing of all these, for if we did
begin to call every man by his name, why we had better
sit down at once and compile a dictionary of mercantile
Men of the Time. The Harvard crew put up at " The
Tavistock" when they came over to whip the Britishers
on their own water (they showed rare pluck, and we
for one cheered them at starting); and the Australian
cricketers know no other home in London. "Harris,
of Dublin, John Knowles, of Manchester, and Chute,
of Bristol" (a query in the " Era" will tell you who
they are), knew " The Tavistock " as well as most men;
and possibly Toole, and Mark Twain, sometime of
New Orleans and the Mississippi River, leadsman,
pilot, and author, might relate a joke or two told in its
Smoking-room. But we must pull together the threads
of our discourse.</p>
   <p>Of all the good old London taverns of bygone days
<pb n="90" id="p.90"/>

the Tavistock is the one which best retains its English
flavour. " The new directorate," says " Atlas " in the
" World," "wisely adhere to the severely Saxon traditions
<figure id="fig.24" n="tufts:central:dca:MS004:MS004.002.008.DO01.00020"><head></head></figure>
of the ancient inn; as of yore, you can peep at your
dinner through a glass window before you eat it, and
the sturdy 'saddle'-loving souls who kick against
'kickshaws' will find much solid satisfaction in the
comforting excellence of the unpretentious cookery.
Moreover, port patrons will find solace in various
vintages dating from the famous 'thirties."' It is
<pb n="91" id="p.91"/><figure id="fig.25" n="tufts:central:dca:MS004:MS004.002.008.DO01.00021"><head>"The dining-room, ample and richly browned."-P. 93.</head></figure>
                              <pb n="93" id="p.93"/>

essentially, what we might term, a winter house-a
house in which the fires are big and come-at-able,
the chairs broad and comfortable, the bedrooms warm
and cosy, the dining-room ample and "richly browned,"
the port wine mild and matured, the dishes
satisfying and English. The taste for venison appears
to be dying out; but this was a famous venison house.
Thirty years ago, when venison was the epicure's dish,
a haunch and neck were, in the season, dressed every
day for dinner at the reasonable charge of 3s. 6d.
Though this fashion has departed, the other happily
remains, of serving " the joint " as the joint ought to
be served, of primest quality, and cooked to perfection
none of your slim after-pieces of " roast," as in dinners
wherein the roast plays second fiddle to the entree; but
inviting substantial cuts sufficient for a reasonable man's
dinner, placed before you on a hot plate with due
accompaniment of well-cooked vegetables. Why does not the
confirmed London diner-out-the man of the old-time
"Albion," and " Simpson's," and " Blanchard's,"-give
a little more attention to the daily fare provided in the
dining-room of " The Tavistock," which now, as in
every other hotel managed by a man of sense, is open

<pb n="94" id="p.94"/>

to the casual customer. Certainly it deserves to be
better known to non-residents.  Nor are the daily
"exhibits" of its coffee-room table to be despised.
The pigeon-pie, the cold pressed beef, the cold saddle,
the ham, the birds, and the soused salmon, always
seem to us more appetizing than those dishes shown
on the side-tables of some other hotels of our
acquaintance.  If a man has no appetite for cold
meats, let him consult with Green, head-waiter of the
establishment (most discriminating and attentive of
head-waiters), who doubtless will recommend, what
we have often eaten in perfection under his advice, a
grilled fillet of beef with mushrooms.</p>
 <p> Though Liberal in all other respects, we confess to
a rigid, unbending conservatism in the matter of
dining-places and dinners, tempered, however, to this
extent, namely, that we prefer a comfortable,
wellventilated, well-furnished dining-room, to a stuffy,
uncomfortable and ill-kept one. To our thinking there
were few pleasanter taverns than the old "Albion " in
Russell Street, Covent Garden, as it was twenty-five
years ago, when Ponsford ruled, and Taylor (with a
staff of most civil and attentive waiters), was his aid. It

                               <pb n="95" id="p.95"/>

was admirably conducted, and the dinners and suppers
were of their kind-plain roast, and boiled, grills, and
stews--excellent. The smoking-room was cosy, and
frequented-by many well-known literary men, actors, and
good fellows generally. " Simpson's " was at its.best (as
we venture to think) about the same period; so was
the "Rainbow" in Fleet Street when Mr. Hale managed
it. The " George," next Twining's bank in the Strand,
then gave a first-rate fish dinner daily at five, such as
we never see nowadays in London. If this should
meet the eye of the genial lessee of the little theatre
in King William Street, we are sure he will bear us
out that old Mr. Griffiths (the last of the old school
of gentlemen landlords, with the manners and courtesy
of a prince) supplied one of the best dinners at is. 6d.
to be had in London. When the said genial lessee
was acting "Brutus Toupet, the Terror of Kings,"
" Augustus de Rosherville," and "Bob Cratchit," at
the Adelphi, under Webster's regime, we often had
the pleasure of sitting next him at the " George."
Griffiths gave three or four kinds of fish, and a couple
of joints, and the company all sat down to dine at the
same table. After dinner there were pipes and punch,
<pb n="96" id="p.96"/>

and each man chatted with his neighbour.   The
" Scotch Stores " and "American Stores," in Oxford
Street, were good taverns of their class. By no means
a bad dinner was then to be had at the " Shades " (now
covered by the Empire Theatre) in Leicester Square.
"The Green Dragon " in Bishopsgate Street, too, was
an excellent tavern of ancient respectability. "
Blanchard's," in Beak Street, was more comfortable, we
think, when it was less crowded. All these good
English taverns served " the joint" in perfection.</p>
 <p> A correspondent has lately written to a London
newspaper <note place="foot" n="2"> <title>The Daily News</title>, <date value="1886-09-07">Sept. 7, 1886</date>.</note>-a little intolerantly, perhaps, but evidently
after cogitating his own experiences-suggesting to
hotel and restaurant proprietors to advertise if they
employ English or foreign waiters, and as to whether
their cuisine be English or foreign. " I am convinced,"
he writes, "the result would be in favour of those
who adhere to the old English ways. A large company
assembled here [at a Zurich hotel], unanimously
expressed their dislike to foreign waiters and foreign
food as compared with the food and waiters we used
to have in England. I am convinced all-including
                         <pb n="97" id="p.97"/>

foreigners-even at higher charges, would prefer purely
English waiters and English food. The imitation French
food now in vogue in London is neither wholesome
nor palatable, and if the writer who alludes to Italian
restaurants knew of what the food sold in them really
consists, he would not risk his health by patronising
them." The "imitation French food" may be good
or it may be bad in those restaurants; that point we
do not care to discuss. We, however, are at one with
the writer, whoever he may be, who pleads for a return
to English waiters and English cookery in London.
An " Ex-M.P.," in the columns of another London
daily,<note place="foot" n="3"><title>The Daily Telegraph</title>, <date value="1886-09-13">Sept. 13, 1886</date>.</note> gives some pleasant reminiscences of
"Bellamy's,' the House of Commons kitchen of days gone
by. Bellamy and Kew were housekeepers of that
august assembly at the beginning of the century. They
supplied members with luncheons, dinners, and wine.
Their's was "a plain room, of which a large portion
surrounding the immense fire-place was lined with
red bricks painted a bright vermilion. A lot of tables,
separated by screens (like the dining-room of the
'Cock,' in Fleet Street), were crowded by members


<pb n="98" id="p.98"/>

whose loud talk and jovial hilarity come back at this
moment to my ears .... 'Bellamy's' was famous for
its Yorkshire ham-the first Bellamy that ever flourished
upon that or some adjacent spot, came to London,
I have been told, from Hull ... The room was
what we should now call a grill-room, and was
modelled upon the pattern of the Beefsteak Club,
of which the gridiron, with ' Beef and Liberty'for a
motto, was the ensign. Sydney Smith [a frequenter
of 'Bellamy's'], then frequently addressed by his
friends as 'Peter Plymley,' was the most fastidious
and critical gourmet in England, and had the credit
of suggesting the addition of a thimbleful of Veuve
Clicquot--dry champagne had not as yet come into
fashion-to a slice of broiled ham, which I remember
that he considered it sacrilege to eat with mustard.</p>
 <p> "The great majority of the guests, however, came
to ' Bellamy's' to partake of hissing hot steaks and
chops fresh from the gridiron. The most remarkable
features of the place were, first, that the attendants
and waiters were demure, soberly-clad, middle-aged
women who never smiled; and, secondly, that the
wines drunk were almost invariably port and Madeira.
                              <pb n="99" id="p.99"/>

In a book which is now very rare, called 'A Carouse
in the Commons,' it is stated that-' Baronets who date
from the Conquest, and squires of ancient degree,
care nothing for the unassuming look of that kitchen,
which they regard as part and parcel of the British
Constitution, if the steak be hot and good, if it can be
conveniently and quietly despatched, and the tinkle
of the division bell can be heard while the dinner
proceeds.' It was an age of taverns of which I am
now writing, and Lord Eldon adjourned from  the
bench at Westminster Hall every day at half-past
one p.m. to partake of a steak and a bottle of port at
'The Cat and Bagpipes,' which stood at the corner
of Downing Street. 'Call England a proud nation,
forsooth !' exclaims the author of 'A Carouse in the
Commons,'-'Say that the House of Commons is
aristocratic! Both the nation and its representatives
must be patterns of Republican humility if all the
pomp and circumstance of dining in their luxurious
houses, surrounded by splendour, powdered livery
servants and exquisite viands, can be forgotten in
Bellamy's kitchen.' " </p>
  <p>What struck the writer's boyish fancy most was

<pb n="100" id="p.100"/>

"the amazing amount of pale old Madeira, at a
fabulous price, which the convives around consumed.
There were at that time old country gentlemen in
abundance who, instead of brewing a vat of mighty
ale when their eldest son and heir was born, laid in a
pipe of Madeira, to be consumed when the little
stranger had attained his majority. The grape disease
had not as yet invaded the districts where the famous
wine, so dear to the more refined of our predecessors
and so detrimental to those of them with gouty
proclivities, was produced. There was a huge tub under
the window at ' Bellamy's' into which water slowly
trickled from a spout at the top, and at the bottom of
which there was a small perforation to allow the liquid
to escape. Into this tub a solemn-looking old waiter
-the only male attendant in the room except the
host himself--plunged the funnel-shaped glasses which
required washing. Reverting to those primitive times,
it would amaze modern legislators to think how simple
and unpretending in their tastes were the stout squires
and far-descended noblemen, all of them 'acred up
to the chin,' who, instead of luxurious clubs and French
cookery, were satisfied with ' Bellamy's.' "
                 Covent Garden.               <pb n="101" id="p.101"/>

  There will be a reaction some day from the Anglo-
French dinner and entree business (a French
gentleman told us the other day that he never could get a
cut of beef out of England, nor an entree but in
France);<figure id="fig.26" n="tufts:central:dca:MS004:MS004.002.008.DO01.00022"><head></head></figure>
and   then,
perhaps, we
shall get
back once
again to the
more
wholesome
English style.
What
Engi s h man
who   loves
his  dinner
wants   his
slice out of the saddle of mutton cut the thickness of
a shilling, or his bit of turbot dipped out of the
fishkettle, wherein it has been soddening along with other
meagre portions for an hour and more ? Why should
we be compelled to go to German and Italian cafes

<pb n="102" id="p.102"/>

for our cut of mutton? What do Germans,
Frenchmen, or Italians know of the saddle, the haunch, or
"the silver side of the round"? Is there any food
more digestible and wholesomer in its way than plain
roast and boiled ? Ask Mr. Robert, the greatest living
authority on dinners and diners (we have taken the
liberty of quoting him more fully elsewhere), whose
contributions to Punch add to our merriment and
stock of information on this most interesting subject.
We have had too much, of recent years, of kickshaws
and maccaroni. Let's hark back a bit to the
wellroasted saddle and sirloin, and let us see our turbot,
brill, or slice of salmon cut from the fish itself, and not
served boiled to bits and flavourless, and disguised
with sauce of capers, or tinned lobster from
Massachusetts Bay.
  We should like to see the management of "The
Tavistock " take this matter in hand, and let the world
know that the old Tavern-style is still kept up in
Covent Garden. With its history and traditions, " The
Tavistock " is the very place to attract the diner who is
tired of the Continental fashion, which may be best
studied at our fashionable hotels, or, better still, at

                 Covent Garden.              <pb n="103" id="p.103"/>

Paris, Brussels, or Berlin.  The present Managing
Director, Mr. Charles Taylor, was pupil in a good
school. He graduated under the late Mr. Harrison.
He knows all about "richly-browned dining-rooms,"
<figure id="fig.27" n="tufts:central:dca:MS004:MS004.002.008.DO01.00023"><head></head></figure>
and the roast saddle, the haunch, and "the sirloin,"
rumpsteaks, and cod's head and oysters, and grouse,
woodcock, partridges, and venison. The cellars he
controls contain some fine samples of old Ports and
Burgundies, Clarets, and Champagnes. His staff of
waiters is second to none. Let him move his co-di-
<pb n="104" id="p.104"/>

rectors to give us a reproduction in large of the old
" Piazza Tavern," where we may taste of the foods and
dainties of our forefathers; where, if a man's appetite
inclines that way, he may taste a glass of Bishop or of
Sack o' winter nights, and a good supper of grilled
bones or oysters. This should not disturb the privacy
of the "Old Tavistock;" and when the "Piazza
Tavern" exists again in name and reputation, we
shall have revived some of the pleasanter memories
of "the joyous neighbourhood of Covent Garden."</p>
 <p> The following verses may not inappropriately serve
as appendix of our little book. If we have told in it
little that is new, we have made amends in interesting
the Reader (as we hope) in what is old. London of
to-day is not so delightful a pleasure-ground to all of
us, that we can afford to pass by any chance retreat
that promises repose and somewhat of the pleasant
hospitality of old times. Some of us are past the
age when kicking the heels about in marble halls,
and parading ourselves in drawing-rooms of almost
regal magnificence, lends any charm to life. Like
Christophero Sly, we like not all this splendour, and
beg for a draught of small ale. If you would give us

                  Covent Garden.                <pb n="105" id="p.105"/>

conserves, give us conserves of beef.  We prefer the
simple village inn of Mistress Marian Hacket of
Wincot to the stately building with the    marble
columns. We plead for occasional retirement and
somewhat of the soberer fashion of our forefathers.
We ask for an old armchair in an old-fashioned tavern
out of the hurly-burly, where one sees and hears less
of the bustle of the Boulevards. Alas ! that our ending
should be in the nature of a lament. In transcribing
these verses, we ask pardon of the anonymous writer
whose permission we have not first obtained. He
doubtless has knowledge of " the old Tavistock."  If
ever he comes that way we hope he will grant us
absolution, if not over a steaming bowl of Bishop,
glass to glass, brimmed with ruby wine of '47, than
which, we'll wager, he will not find a better bottle
within sound of the boom of " Big Ben."</p>
            <lg type="ballad"><l>A BALLAD OF OLD INNS.</l>

<l>" Where shall I find them-the Inns that I dream about,</l>
  <l>' Bushes,' ' Bell Savages,' ' Horses,' and ' Heads '?</l>
<l>Where seek the signboard that bragged from its beam about</l>
  <l>Commonplace comforts, good cheer, and good beds ?
</l>
<pb n="106" id="p.106"/>

<l>"Vainly-beguiled by traditions of Thackeray,</l>
  <l>Etchings of Crowquill, and sketches by Boz-</l>
<l>Rove I 'mid London's new-fangled gimcrackery,</l>
<l>  Searching 'Time is' for the haunts of 'Time was.'</l>
<l>"Vainly, through byway, through alley and rookery,</l>
<l>  Vainly I hunger the hostel to find</l>
<l>Warranting hope of plain fare and plain cookery,</l>
<l>  Rest for the body and peace for the mind.</l>
<l>  *        *          *          *          *</l>

<l>" Gone are the surly ' twin heads of the Saracens,'</l>
<l>  Blest for a Browdie, though sacred to Squeers;</l>
<l>Gone the ' White Hart,' where that prince of comparisons,</l>
<l>  Weller, blacked boots in the prime of his years.</l>
<l>"Gone too the ' Slaughters,' that notable snuggery,</l>
<l>  Where gentle Dobbin, the brave and the true,</l>
<l>Weary of uniform, pipe-clay, and puggaree,</l>
<l>  Slighted his supper when hasting to woo.</l>

<l>"Where is ' mine hostess,' the buxom and motherly,</l>
<l>  Warm in her welcome and apt in her jest ?</l>
<l>Where the head-waiter, half-lordly, half-brotherly,</l>
<l>  Patron and slave to the oft-coming guest ?</l>

<l>" Where jolly Boniface, 'neath whose protectorate</l>
<l>  Port was a proverb and Punch was a law ?</l>
<l>Gone-to make way for a phantom Directorate,</l>
<l>  Shadows intangible, sovereigns of straw.</l>
                                     <pb n="107" id="p.107"/>

<l>" Where are the signs, each a pun or a riddle, gone--</l>
<l>  ' Nobody,' ' Nowhere,' the ' Mouth,' and the ' Mail'?</l>
<l>Where, Piccadilly, have Puss and her Fiddle gone,</l>
<l>  Mystical tribute to poor chat fidele?</l>

<l>" Where are they all ?  'Mid our 'Grands ' and our ' Avenues,'</l>
<l>  Where the blest freedom from tumult and din ?</l>
<l>Where shall I find, in our six-storey parvenus,</l>
<l>  Licence for taking 'mine ease in mine Inn' ?</l>

<l>" Lost in the limbo of popular fallacies,</l>
<l>  Calm and tranquillity fade like a dream;</l>
<l>Ease yields to ornament, taverns turn palaces,</l>
<l>Stages en route to a social paralysis-</l>
  <l>Plutus the postboy, his Pegasus steam."</l></lg>

<p>  <figure id="fig.28" n="tufts:central:dca:MS004:MS004.002.008.DO01.00024"><head></head></figure></p>
  <pb n="108" id="p.108"/>
  <p><figure id="fig.29" n="tufts:central:dca:MS004:MS004.002.008.DO01.00025"><head>THE GREAT PIAZZA (UNDER THE TAVISTOCK BREAKFAST-ROOMS) IN 1787.
</head>
</figure>
</p>
</div1>
</body>

<back>
<div1 type="appendix" n="Advertisements" id="back001">

<pb n="109" id="p.109"/>

<p>
<list type="simple">      <head> WHAT THE CELLARS CONTAIN AT
"THE TAVISTOCK. "Old Wines Bottled in the Hotel"</head>



<item>PORTS of 1820, 1834, 1840, 1851, and other famous Vintages.</item>

<item>CLARETS of 1858, 1862, 1864, 1865, 1870, 1874, of the best
   Shippers.</item>

<item>CHAMPAGNES. All the leading Brands. Old landed.
</item>
<item>HOCKS. Old Cabinet.</item>

<item>SHERRIES, -
            Very Old, in Bottle.</item>
<item>MADEIRAS,</item></list></p>
<p>Visitors are, at any time, welcome to view the Cellars.

These are very Extensive, and contain a Large and

Valuable Stock.</p>

<pb n="110" id="p.110"/>

 <p> THE SUMMER EXHIBITION

           OF HIGH-CLASS

ENGLISH &#x0026; CONTINENTAL

          PICTURES
               AT

 ARTHUR TOOTH AND SONS'

         New Galleries,

    5 &#x0026;6, H A Y M A R K E T
      (Opposite Her Majesty's Theatre),

        IS NOW OPEN.
     ADMISSION-ONE SHILLING,
         INCLUDING CATALOGUE.
         <pb n="111" id="p.111"/>
    <figure id="fig.30" n="tufts:central:dca:MS004:MS004.002.008.DO01.00026"><head></head></figure>
							A
                        SUGGESTION
                              FOR A

                           SATUR-
                           DAY-TO-
                           MONDAY
                           TRIP.
THE FOREST HOTEL AT EPPING FOREST.

 [See next page.</p>
<pb n="112" id="p.112"/>              
 <p>    THE ROYAL FOREST HOTEL AT
                  CHINGFORD.</p>
<p>A   SUGGESTION for a Saturday-to-Monday trip will
    be acceptable to many a reader of this little book.
The ways of spending that brief period of rest away from
London, and yet near London, are neither so many or
various that one should spare himself the trouble of
tendering a hint to a busy man. We lately made an
excursion to Epping Forest. The forest is little known to
west-end Londoners and visitors to London, and we
commend it to their notice. It is easily accessible by rail
from Liverpool Street to Chingford direct, or by road by
way of the northern outskirts-Regent's Park, Camden
Road, Seven Sisters Road, Tottenham High Road
(crossing the Lea at the ferry), and so past Chingford Old
Church to Chingford Green. In the spring, summer, and
autumn months, the Londoner weary awhile of the
hubbub and confusion of the town, will find in Epping Forest
as peaceful seclusion, as picturesque scenery and pleasant
woodland walks, and as bracing air as he will find
anywhere round London.</p>
  <p>Let him make note of the Forest Hotel, and he need
be under no apprehension of not finding comfortable
quarters. We have stayed there, and can testify of its
comfort, quiet, and rural attractiveness.  It is remote
from well-worn paths and the " madding crowd's ignoble

                  Advertisments        <pb n="113" id="p.113"/>

strife;" and, save on great festival occasions, such as
Bank Holiday, is as peaceful a retreat as a tired
wayfarer need wish for.  It stands on high ground
overlooking a wide extent of country; and with its broad
balconies, bay windows, high gables, red steep roof, and
pretty and charmingly decorated rooms, is most
picturesque. There is a garden reserved to the more
contemplative visitor, where, under summer skies, all the
joys of sense (which, by the way, according to Pope, lie
in three words-health, peace, and competence) may be
passively revelled in; and the most active man also will
find ample opportunity of gratifying his hobby, whether
it be riding, driving, or walking.</p>
  <p>We doubt not that a comfortable room, fresh country
food, that is to say, good butter, eggs, milk, and bread
(which we take leave to consider the essentials at a
country hotel), good meat well cooked, a good bottle of
wine, and a moderate bill, will have a marked influence
in attracting west-end Londoners and their friends to the
Forest Hotel at Chingford for a little rest and country
air from Saturday to Monday.</p>
 <p> The reader will do well to consult a little book, which
costs but sixpence, and which affords a vast amount of
interesting and useful information respecting Epping
Forest and the adjacent country-"Walks in Epping
Forest," by Percy Lindley-and then to make his way to
the Forest Hotel at Chingford, and set about turning that
information to practical account.</p>
                           

<pb n="114" id="p.114"/>               
     <p>   BENTLEY PRIORY.</p>

<p>THIS charming Country Mansion, formerly the seat of
     the Marquis of Abercorn, and the residence of the
late Queen Adelaide, continues to maintain its high
reputation as a first-class residential Hotel, affording all the
comforts of an English nobleman's house at very
moderate expense.</p>
  <p>It is situated in the midst of a most beautiful demesne
of 250 acres, facing south, and is sheltered from the north
and east winds.</p>
  <p>Tennis Lawns, Cricket and Football Grounds, and four
and a half acres of Ornamental Water for Boating and
Fishing, magnificent Conservatory or Winter Garden,
Cedar Gardens, and Deer Park.</p>
  <p>The Hotel Stables contain some of the finest boxes in
England, with every accommodation. There is a frequent
and rapid service of trains by the London and North
Western Railway from Broad Street or Euston to Harrow.
The Hotel Omnibus meets certain trains, and Carriages
can be had on notice being given.</p>
 <p> All necessary information can be obtained from the
Secretary, Bentley Priory, Stanmore, Middlesex.</p>
 <p> A well-appointed four-horse Coach leaves the Hotel
Metropole daily at 11:30 a.m., calling at the "White
Horse Cellars," due at Bentley Priory at 1:15 p.m.,
returning at 4:30 p.m.</p>
<pb n="115" id="p.115"/>
   <p>THE BEST HANDBOOK TO
 MODERN LONDON.</p>

 <p>PROFUSELY ILLUSTRATED WITH ORIGINAL SKETCHES
            BY WELL-KNOWN ARTISTS.</p>

           <p> "LONDON OF TO-DAY."</p>

      <p> " Our Little Village would you view,
           And all its sights and lions do,
           Without the least delay;
         Or if you're anxious to divine
         The restauants where you should dine-
         Where best the food is and the wine--
           The inns where you should stay;
         If all about the Town you'd know,
         I'd counsel you at once to go
         Straight off to Messrs. SAMPSON Low,
         And buy a book, by EYRE PASCOE,
           Called London of To-day."</p>
                       <p>Punch, or the London Charivari,
                               April 3, 1886.</p>
  <p>Copies of this entertaining and gossipy little volume
for 1887 may be had, price 3s. 6d., on application to
the Clerk at the Desk, Coffee Room, Tavistock
Hotel.</p>
<pb n="116" id="p.116"/>                

 <p> "Sir Peter Lely first brought it in repute.     In the
angle of the Piazza, which now forms a part of the
Tavistock Hotel, lived this successor of Vandyck
in England, 'the most capital painter' of the reign of
Charles II."  See page 16.</p>

  <p>Under the North Piazza, on the very spot as described above,
is carried on the old-established business of!</p>
             <p> G. R. MILES,

   TEA AND COFFEE MERCHANT,

                   ESTABLISHED 1815.</p>

  <p>This firm retains its well-known reputation, and sells the
choicest qualities and various growths of China, Assam, and
Ceylon Teas.</p>
<p>  Moning, Souchong, Pekoe, Darjeeling, Kaisow, Oolong,
Assam, Green.</p>
 <p> Long experience in tea-tasting, and unwearied attention to
that delicate work, enables this firm to offer great advantages to
small as well as large consumers.</p>
  <p>Coffee of various countries-Ceylon, Mysore, East India
Mocha, Costa Rica, &amp;c.</p>
  <p>A well-selected stock, both of Teas and Coffees, duty paid, or
in bond, can always be sampled.</p>
  <p>This house has been long noted for the Navy Cocoa, which is
held in much esteem by invalids and delicate persons.</p>

     <pb n="117" id="p.117"/>
     <p> R. DIEPPE,

               BUTCHER,</p>

  <p>  54 &#x0026;   54 1/2, LONG    ACRE, LONDON.
Established upwards of Seventy Years, during which
   period the firm has supplied the following among
         the old Taverns of Covent Garden:</p>

<p>THE TAVISTOCK, RICHARDSON'S, CLUNN'S, EVANS'S,
      THE BEDFORD, AND THE Hummums.</p>

 <p>Visitors and Country Customers can be Supplied with
           the Primest Meat in Season.</p>
<p>HAUNCHES OF MUTTON, BARONS, AND THE ROUND OF
     BEEF, SADDLES OF MUTTON, VENISON, AND
                  HOUSE LAMB.
     ALL KINDS OF POULTRY AND GAME.</p>

 <p> " No saddle can I get worth having outside ' The Tavistock.'"
--Extract from a Letter to the Manager of the Tavistock Hotel.</p>

<p>Telegraphic Address -
       DIEPPE, LONG ACRE.</p>
<pb n="118" id="p.118"/>          
<figure id="fig.32" n="tufts:central:dca:MS004:MS004.002.008.DO01.00027"><head></head></figure>
<p>Telephone No. 3753.</p>

   <p>SHERSTON &#x0026; CO.,

JOB AND POST MASTER TO H.R.H. THE
           PRINCE OF WALES.

  FIRST CLASS DRAGS, BRAKES, AND
              OMNIBUSES.
SUPERIOR JOB AND POST HORSES, LANDAUS, BROUGHAMS,
      VICTORIAS, ETC., SET FOR ANY PERIOD,
        Chief Office:-40, HAYMARKET.
   68, HAYMARKET, 38, WHITCOMB STREET.
      HORSES TAKEN IN TO STAND AT LIVERY.</p>

  <pb n="119" id="p.119"/>
<p>JAMES SHOOLBRED   &#x0026; CO.,

     TOTTENHAM COURT ROAD,

            LONDON,
For CARPETS,
      UPHOLSTERY,

 CABINET FURNITURE.</p>
<pb n="120" id="p.120"/>         
  <p> H. J. TOWELL,

 FISHMONGER, POULTERER, AND

         DEALER IN GAME,

             33, STRAND,</p>

  <p>Next door to Charing Cross Station.
One of the Largest        Businesses  in

              London.</p>
<p>Country Orders carefully packed and despatched
  to any Railway Station on the shortest
                notice.</p>

         
<p>HUDSON BROTHERS,

       PROVISION MERCHANTS,
 Have served the Tavistock Hotel for many years.
                  Chief Depot:-
            52, LUDGATE HILL.
               I Wholesale Warehouse :-
      7 AND 9, ST. BRIDE STREET, E.C.
              LONDON BRANCHES:-
      160, New Bond Street.
      444, Strand.
      Cannon Street, Railway Approach.
      Islington, 9, High Street.
      Liverpool Street, 45, 46, and 47.
      Fenchurch Street, 3, Railway Place.
      Great Eastern Railway, on the Platform.
      Gresham Buildings, Blackfriars.
      Victoria Station, 6, Wilton Road.
      Dowgate Hill, opposite Walbrook.
              COUNTRY BRANCHES:-
       Brighton, 67, East Street.
       Eastbourne, 62, Terminus Road.
       Surbiton Hill, The Pavement.</p>
<pb n="122" id="p.122"/>             

   <p>DENT'S WATCHES, CLOCKS, AND CHRONOMETERS,

                E. DENT &#x0026; CO.,

                        61, STRAND,</p>

   <p>(OPPOSITE BEDFORD STREET, AND CLOSE TO THE
                TAVISTOCK HOTEL.)
City House: 4, ROYAL EXCHANGE, CORNHILL.
       Factory: 4, HANWAY PLACE, W.</p>

<p>MAKERS to H. M. the Queen, H.R.H. the Prince of
   Wales, and the principal Foreign and Colonial
   Governments.</p>
<p>MAKERS of the Great Clock (Big Ben) of the Houses of
    Parliament.</p>
<p>MAKERS of the Standard Clock of the Royal Observatory,
   Greenwich.</p>
<p>ALL articles of E. DENT &#x0026; Co.'s manufacture bear their
   Trade Mark, as shown above. Without this none
   are genuine.</p>

<p>New Illustrated Catalogue of Watches and Clocks at
        reduced prices sent free on application.</p>

<p>E. DENT &#x0026; Co., 61, Strand, &#x0026; 4, Royal Exchange, London.</p>

     <pb n="123" id="p.123"/>
<p>The Estate Offices,
       No. 28, CADOGAN PLACE,
                     BELGRAVE SQUARE.</p>

           <p> Visitors     to   the    metropoolis
              desirous of securing Furnished or Unfurnished
              Residences in the best positions in</p>
                <p>BELGRAVIA,
                       KENSINGTON,
                               MAYFAIR,
                                  ST. JAMES'S, &amp;c.,
will find their labours very materially lightened by calling at the
old-established offices of MESSRS. GODWIN AND BASLEY,
the well-known Estate Agents, who have on their books
particulars of all the finest Houses in the market.</p>
  <p> Their carefully revised and explicit Index to Register of
Town Properties is published every Month, and forwarded to
applicants free of cost.</p>
                  
<p>Sales by Auction are held at the Mart,
                    Tokenhouse Yard, E. C., twice a month.</p>
                 

       <p>GODWIN &#x0026; BASLEY,
Auctioneers, Valuers, Estate Agents, Surveyors, Architects,
              Assessors, aud Arbitrators,
   SURVEYORS tO THE HOLLAND ESTATE IN CHELSEA,
     No. 28, CADOGAN PLACE, S.W.</p>

  <p>BANKERS: -THE LONDON AND COUNTY BANKING
        COMPANY AND THE ALLIANCE BANK.</p>
<pb n="124" id="p.124"/>             
<p>FELIXSTOWE TIDAL DOCK,
     WITHIN THE PORT OF HARWICH.

   VESSELS ARE NOT CHARGED DOCK DUES.</p>

<p>THIS OPEN I)OCK is of the most perfect character,
    having 23 feet of water at low water ordinary spring
tides. A branch railway enables waggons to go alongside
the vessels, and communication is established direct from
the water side by railway with all parts of Great Britain.</p>
  <p>The Company undertakes to Discharge or Load Vessels
entering the Dock; also the Warehousing, Storage and
Delivery from Warehouse or Quay into Railway Waggons,
or Delivery to Quay for Export.</p>
  <p>Information as to Dues and Charges may be obtained
from
                J. BUCKNALL COOPER,
                        Secretary and Manager.</p>
   <p> Felixstowe,
         Suffolk.</p>

<p>PIER HOTEL AND RAILWAY STATION ADJOIN
                  THE DOCK.</p>

      <pb n="125" id="p.125"/>
 <p>HOTEL DU NORD,

            COLOGNE.</p>
             <p> Directors -
J. FRIEDRICH, ESQ.  LEWIS JEFFERIS, ESQ.
THOMAS SHARPE, ESQ.  CHARLES T. TAYLOR, ESQ.</p>
<p>This Hotel is one of the most important

Hotels in Europe, and has been visited by
all the Crowned Heads of Europe. The
arrangements of the Hotel are perfect. The

Rooms are Magnificently Furnished, and
the Public Rooms are all that can be de-

sired.

The Hotel is close to the Railway Station.</p>
<pb n="126" id="p.126"/>         
<p>ROUGEMONT HOTEL,

              EXETER.

    DEVON AND EXETER HOTEL CO:, LIMITED.

THE LARGEST AND ONLY MODERN HOTEL
              IN EXETER.

Replete with every Comfort for Families and Gentlemen.
   MAGNIFICENT BILLIARD SALOON.

          TABLE D'HOTE, 7 O'CLOCK.

      NIGHT PORTER ON PATROL.

                 T. W. HUSSEY,
                              Manager.</p>

                 <pb n="127" id="p.127"/>
                    <figure id="fig.31" n="tufts:central:dca:MS004:MS004.002.008.DO01.00028"><head></head></figure>

 <p>QUEEN'S HOTEL, CHELTENHAM,

 It has within the last two years been entirely refurnished and
 decorated, and is one of the best hotels in the
                WEST OF ENGLAND.
  Sheltered by the Cotswold Hills, Cheltenham is at all times a
favourite place as a health resort.
  It is a capital hunting centre, having the Cotswold, Duke of
Beaufort's, Lord Fitzhardinge's, and other packs in the vicinity.
  The country around is charming for riding and driving, with
numerous places of interest.
  The educational colleges are of the highest standard, and there
is abundance of good society.

                TERMS MODERATE.</p>
<pb n="128" id="p.128"/>          
               <p>   THE

CLIFTONVILLE HOTEL,

             MARGATE.

 Situate on the High Cliffs facing and close to the
 Sea, accommodates more than 200 Visitors.

 LIBERAL TABLE.    HIGH-CLASS CUISINE.

       Wines of the Finest Quality.

ONE OF THE BEST AND MOST POPULAR
         HOTELS IN ENGLAND,

           GOOD STABLING.

 Tariff on Application to
             LEWIS JEFFERIS,
                 Resident Managing Director.
                    Advertisements.                 <pb n="129" id="p.129"/>
           HARROGATE

             AS A HEALTH RESORT.

  THE QUEEN HOTEL, HARROGATE.</p>

<p>THE QUEEN, Harrogate, is one of the largest first-class
     Family Hotels in the North of England, and is as widely
famed for its Cuisine as its Convenience.  It was established in
1671, and has been recently considerably enlarged.</p>
 <p> The accommodation comprises Elegant Public Drawing and
Dining Rooms, Reading, Smoking and Billiard Rooms; twenty
Private Sitting and Two Hundred Bedrooms, fitted up with good
taste.</p>
  <p>The Hotel has a South aspect, and stands in its own extensive
and beautiful Pleasure Grounds; in which are six Lawn Tennis
Courts for the use of the Visitors at the Hotel. The " Queen"
being situate in the highest part of Harrogate, facing the Stray,
commands a fine view of the surrounding country, and is only a
few minutes' walk from the Sulphur, Chalybeate, and Kissengen
Springs, Baths, and Public Gardens and Concert Rooms.</p>
 <p> The "Old Sulphur" Water is supplied in a room in the
Grounds every morning; but Visitors preferring it, are conveyed
free of charge to and from the Old Sulphur Well, each morning,
in private Carriages.</p>

<p>THE QUEEN HOTEL, HARROGATE.

                       TARIFF.
         Board and table d'hote gs. 6d. per day.</p>

<pb n="130" id="p.130"/>                
<figure id="fig.34" n="tufts:central:dca:MS004:MS004.002.008.DO01.00029"><head></head></figure>
<p>Royal    Mounnt      Ephraim       Hotel,

         TUNBRIDGE WELLS, KENT.

IF there be a place in England which may fairly lay claim to be
described as picturesque, surely it is Tunbridge Wells. In itself
justifiably renowned for its splendid common, with its noble
masses of rock, its numberless walks, and its distant views, the
district of which it is the centre is equally famous for natural
beauties unusually attractive.  There is charming Rusthall
Common and its "happy valley," and, close at hand,
picturesque Speldhurst; and there is Southborough Common,
another lovely spot, the High Rocks, the Promenade called
the Pantiles, a quaint and striking relic of a past age, all within
a couple of miles. Other attractions, too, abound within easy
reach; the historic Pevensey, the very interesting old and
perfect specimen of a moated house, near Groombridge; Eridge
Castle and Rocks, &amp;c.
  Tunbridge Wells can be reached from Charing Cross in little
more than an hour.
  At the above Hotel, under the able management of Miss
Prouse, will be found excellent accommodation, with extreme
cleanliness, and every home comfort.</p>

            <pb n="131" id="p.131"/>
 <p>BATT'S FAMILY HOTEL,

 41 AND 42, DOVER     STREET, PICCADILLY,
                  LONDON, W.

  This long-established, First-Class Family Hotel is near
the Palaces, Parks, Clubs, and West End Shops.

                Telegraphic Address:-
          "BATT'S HOTEL," London.

                   FREDERIC SMITH,
       DOUGLAS-ISLE OF MAN.

CASTLE MONA HOTEL,
Situate within its own beautifully wooded and extensive
grounds, and overlooking and within 1oo yards of the superb
Bay of Douglas.
The Hotel was built by the former Duke of Athole as his
private Marine residence.
There is magnificent Sea Bathing, Boating, and Fishing in
the Bay.
  Omnibus and Servants attend the arrival of the various
Steamers from Liverpool, Barrow, Fleetwood, &amp;c.
  For Tariff, address-
                     The Manager.</p>

<pb n="132" id="p.132"/>             

<p>The  Egyptian Cigarette and French  Government
         Tobaccos Company, Limited.
     86-88, LEADENHALL STREET,
               YENIDJEH AND CAIRO.
<figure id="fig.35" n="tufts:central:dca:MS004:MS004.002.008.DO01.00030"><head></head></figure>
     FINEST BRANDS OF EGYPTIAN CIGARETTES:
 "EGYPTIAN     BEAUTIES," "THE MOSLEM,"
              AND "AU SOLEIL."
 Beware of worthless imitations of the above unrivalled Brands.
 All Cigarettes bear the Company's Trade Marks and are to be
                had of all Tobacconists.</p>
                <pb n="133" id="p.133"/>
                <figure id="fig.36" n="tufts:central:dca:MS004:MS004.002.008.DO01.00031"><head></head></figure>
<pb n="134" id="p.134"/>           

<p>"Taunus Water is all that can reasonably, or even by the
most exacting, be expected from a Sparkling Table Water."-</p>
<p>A. HILL HASSELL, M.D.
  A GUARANTEED NATURAL
  SPARKLING MINERAL WATER
TAUN US"</p>

   <p> As supplied to Her Majesty the QUEEN,
      and H.R.H. the PRINCE OF WALES.
The TAUNUS SPRING is at Grosskarben,
Frankfort-on-the-Maine.
  PROPRIETORS:-The Taunus Spring Natural Mineral
           Water Company (Limited).
HEAD OFFICES: 23, LIME STREET, LONDON, E.C.</p>

               <pb n="135" id="p.135"/>
<p>
 BURROUGHES &#x0026; WATTS.-Patent Billiard Tables.
 BURROUGHES &#x0026; WATTS.- Have Patented Inventions
BURROUGHES &#x0026; WATTS.-Not contained in any others.
BURROUGHES &#x0026; WATTS.-The Patent Metal Frame Cushion
BURROUGHES &#x0026; WATTS.- -Far surpasses anything of the kind,
BURROUGHES &#x0026; WATTS.- Being noiseless and cold-resisting.
BURROUGHES &#x0026; WATTS.-The Patent Pockets are quite
BURROUGHES &#x0026; WATTS.-A boon, no metal projections.
BURROUGHES &#x0026; WATTS.-Patent Billiard Tables
BURROUGHES &#x0026; WATTS.-Have been awarded
BURROUGHES &#x0026; WATTS. -Highest Gold Medals
BURROUGHES &#x0026; WATTS.-Throughout the World.
BURROUGHES &#x0026; WATTS.-Are made of best materials,
BURROUGHES &#x0026; WATTS.-In perfect taste
BURROUGHES &#x0026; WATTS.- -And finish.
BURROUGHES &#x0026; WATTS.-May be hired
BURROUGHES &#x0026; WATTS.-For Three Years,
BURROUGHES &#x0026; WATTS.-After which time
BURROUGHES &#x0026; WATTS.-They become the property
BURROUGHES &#x0026; WATTS.--Of the hirer.
BURROUGHES &#x0026; WATTS.-Patent Convertible Tables.
BURROUGHES &#x0026; WATTS. -Patent Billiard Markers.
BURROUGHES &#x0026; WATTS.-Patent Universal Rest.
BURROUGHES &#x0026; WATTS.-Patent Metal Bridge.
BURROUGHES &#x0026; WATTS.-Patent Cigar Tray.
BURROUGHES &#x0026; WATTS.- Patent Jointed Cue.
BURROUGHES &#x0026; WATTS.-Patent Interchangeable Tips.
BURROUGHES &#x0026; WATTS.--Patent Cue Hanger.
BURROUGHES &#x0026; WATTS.-Patent Cue Tipper.
BURROUGHES &#x0026; WATTS.-Patent Ball Adjuster.
BURROUGHES &#x0026; WATTS.-Registered Sighting Angle.
BURROUGHES &#x0026; WATTS.-" Billiards," 10th Thousand.
BURROUGHES &#x0026; WATTS.-" Billiards, Simplified," 15th Thousand.
BURROUGHES &#x0026; WATTS.- Established over 50 years at
BURROUGHES &#x0026; WATTS.-Soho Square, London, W.</p>

<pb n="136" id="p.136"/>             
       <p> THREE GOLD MEDALS.

HIGHEST AWARDS EVER OBTAINED BY ANY ARTIFICIAL
                STONE COMPANY,

METROPOLITAN FIRE BRIGADE. HER MAJESTYS WAR
    OFFICE. METROPOLITAN BOARD OF WORKS.

WILKES' METALLIC FLOORING AND EUREKA CONCRETE

               COMPANY, LIMITED.

 STABLE PAVIORS TO H.R.H. THE PRINCE OF WALES.

 GOLD MEDAL, INTERNATIONAL HEALTH
              EXHIBITION, 1884.

    AWARDED ONLY GOLD MEDAL, 1884,
  Being the highest award given for Superiority in Paving.

  By Appointment to the International Inventions Exhibition,
              South Kensington, 1885.

 By Appointment to the Colonial and Indian Exhibition, South
                 Kensington, 1886.
                 CHIEF OFFICES:-
17, DEVONSHIRE SQUARE, BISHOPSGATE, E.C.
  Works: MIDLAND RAILWAY, WEST KENSINGTON, W.
       Depots: ST. PANCRAS AND BISHOPSGATE.</p>

             <pb n="137" id="p.137"/>
           <p> THE NATIONAL

FIRE INSURANCE CORPORATION,
                      LIMITED.
  HEAD OFFICE-72, KING     WILLIAM      STREET,
                    London, E.C.
          WEST END-I2, PALL MALL, S.W.
                    TRUSTEES.
SIR HENRY ARTHUR HUNT, C.B., 45, Parliament Street, and 54,
   Eccleston Square.
CHARLES HOARE, Esq. (Messrs. Hoare).
                    DIRECTORS.
SIR GABRIEL GOLDNEY, Bart., Beechfield, Chippenham, Wilts
   (Chairman).
FOSTER MORTIMORE, Esq. (Boutcher, Mortimore and Co.), (Deputy-
   Chairman).
H. W. HOARE, Esq., Oakfield, Crawley.
HENRY LOFTS, Esq. (Messrs. Lofts and Warner), 130, Mount Street,
   Grosvenor Square.
ROBERT OWEN WHITE, Esq. (late of J. Bazley White and Bros.).
THE HON. R. W. GROSVENOR, 37, Park Lane, W., and The Lodge,
   Brackley.
THOMAS A. H. HAMOND, Esq., 56, Lincoln's Inn Fields, W.C., and
   Swaffham, Norfolk.
HENRY A. HUNT, Esq., 45, Parliament Street, S.W.
                     BANKERS.
               MESSRS. HOARE, Fleet Street.
                     MANAGER.
                  WILLIAM COLLIS.
                  SOLICITORS.
 Messrs. COPE AND CO., Great George Street, Westminster, S.W.
   HONORARY CONSULTING ARCHITECT.
              CHARLES BARRY, Esq., F.S.A.
                     AUDITORS.
Messrs. ROBERT A. McLEAN AND CO., I, Queen Victoria Street, E.C.
  FORMS OF PROPOSAL and all information can be obtained at
the Head Office, at the Branch Offices, or from any of the
Agents to the Corporation.</p>

<pb n="138" id="p.138"/>            

<p>ESTABLISHED IN THE REIGN OF KING GEORGE III.
       C. HODGSON,

   24, BEDFORD STREET,
           COVENT GARDEN, W.C.,
               MANUFACTURER OF

HIGH-CLASS AERATED MINERAL WATERS,
     SODA  WATER, POTASS, LITHIA,
SELTZER, LEMONADE, GINGER           ALE, &amp;c.
  As supplied to the following celebrated Hotels, &amp;c.,
in Covent Garden :-
      THE TAVISTOCK (upwards of 70 years),
    The Piazza,          The Hummums,
    Kilpack's,           Evans's,
    Offley's,            Clunn's,
    Ashley's,            Beef Steak Club,
    The Royal Italian Opera, for many years,

  Besides many other important Hotels, Clubs, and
Private Families in other parts of London and the
Country.</p>

            <pb n="139" id="p.139"/>
<figure id="fig.37" n="tufts:central:dca:MS004:MS004.002.008.DO01.00032"><head></head></figure>
              <p>   SCOTCH     WHISKY.
     "BONNIE DUNDEE."

 A Special Blend of the finest old Scotch Whiskies, extensively
 used in England, France, Germany, India, and the Colonies,
and in much favour in the West End London Clubs, Hotels,
and Private Families, as supplied by

GEORGE LLOYD ALISON,

    59, HAYMARKET, LONDON, AND
       14, PANMURE STREET, DUNDEE.

 N.B. "The Tavistock Hotel has used this Special Blend of
 Whisky for now nearly a quarter of a century."
 Extract of a letter to Mr. C. T. Taylor, Managing-Director of
 "The Tavistock," dated 21st February, 1887:--"Will you
 please inform me where you get your Scotch Whisky; it is the
 best I get anywhere."</p>
<pb n="140" id="p.140"/>         
<p>MESSRS. BELTON &#x0026; SONS,

   HOTEL AND BREWERY VALUERS AND
             AUCTIONEERS

      81, HATTON GARDEN, LONDON.

 ESTABLISHED BEST PART OF A CENTURY.
 <figure id="fig.38" n="tufts:central:dca:MS004:MS004.002.008.DO01.00033"><head></head></figure>
 THE PERFECT EMPTY BAG.  For Continental Traelling.
THE PERFECT FITTED BAG. WONDERFUL For its Strength.
           CATALOGUES POST FREE.
   S.  FISHER, 188, STRAND.</p>

         <pb n="141" id="p.141"/>

              <p> OPTICIAN TO
<figure id="fig.39" n="tufts:central:dca:MS004:MS004.002.008.DO01.00034"><head></head></figure>
    Her									The
 Majesty's                       National Rifle
 Government,                      Association of
    The                           Great Britain
 War Office,                          and
Admiralty, &amp;c.                      America.
                By Appointment.
    J. H. STEWARD,

        406, 66, 456, STRAND, AND

           54, CORNHILL, LONDON.
<figure id="fig.40" n="tufts:central:dca:MS004:MS004.002.008.DO01.00035"><head></head></figure>
                    BINOCULAR, OPERA, FIELD,
                      and MARINE GLASSES of
                      the Finest Quality.
                    SPECTACLES and EYE-
                      GLASSES scientifically
                      adapted.
THE &#x00A3;2 2S. BINOCULAR.

                Highest Awards:
   GOLD AND SILVER MEDALS, 1884, 1885.</p>
<pb n="142" id="p.142"/>           
    <p> THOMAS COLE,

 HAT AND CAP MANUFACTURER,

          156, STRAND, W.C.
       (Four doors City side of Somerset House).
HATS FOR HUNTIING, SHOOTING, FISHING, BOATING, RIDING,
              AND DRIVING, &amp;C.
              <pb n="143" id="p.143"/>
              <figure id="fig.41" n="tufts:central:dca:MS004:MS004.002.008.DO01.00036"><head>THE BILLIARD ROOM OF THE TAVISTOCK HOTEL.</head></figure>
<pb n="144" id="p.144"/>
<figure id="fig.42" n="tufts:central:dca:MS004:MS004.002.008.DO01.00037"><head></head></figure></p>
</div1>
</back>
</text>
</TEI.2>