<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/P4X/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
 <!ENTITY % TEI.prose 'INCLUDE'>
 <!ENTITY % TEI.names.dates 'INCLUDE'>
 <!ENTITY % TEI.figures 'INCLUDE'>
 <!ENTITY % TEI.XML 'INCLUDE'>
]>
<TEI.2>

<teiHeader>
	<fileDesc>
		<titleStmt>
			<title>Essays and Orations, Read and Delivered at the Royal College of Physicians to which is Added an Account of the Opening of the Tomb of King Charles.</title>
			<author>Henry Halford</author>
		</titleStmt>

		<editionStmt>
			<edition><date>2002-01-01</date></edition>
		</editionStmt>

		<extent>43880 bytes</extent>

		<publicationStmt> 
			<distributor>Tufts University Digital Collections and Archives</distributor>
			<address>
				<addrLine>Tufts University</addrLine>
				<addrLine>35 Professors Row</addrLine>
				<addrLine>Tisch Library Medford, MA 02155</addrLine>
			</address>
			<idno>tufts:central:dca:UA069:UA069.005.DO.00053</idno>
			<availability status="free"><p>This publication is freely available for scholarly or educational use.</p></availability>
		</publicationStmt>

  		<notesStmt>
			<note>This is a digital version of Henry Halford's Essays and Orations, Read and Delivered at the Royal College of Physicians originally published in 1833.
			</note>
		</notesStmt>

    	<sourceDesc>
		<biblStruct>
			<monogr>
				<title>Essays and Orations, Read and Delivered at the Royal College of Physicians to which is Added an Account of the Opening of the Tomb of King Charles.</title>
				<author>Henry Halford</author>
				<imprint>
					<pubPlace>London: Albemarle Street.</pubPlace>
					<publisher>John Murray</publisher>
					<date>1833</date>
				</imprint>
			</monogr>
		</biblStruct>
		</sourceDesc>
	</fileDesc>

	<encodingDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
			<stdVals><p>Standard date values are given in ISO form: yyyy-mm-dd.</p></stdVals>
			<interpretation><p>Prominent personal names are marked.</p>
					<p>Place names are marked.</p>
					<p>Dates are marked.</p>
			</interpretation>
		</editorialDecl>

		<refsDecl n="TOC">
			<state unit="preface"/>
		</refsDecl>
		<refsDecl n="TOC">
			<state unit="abstract"/>
		</refsDecl>
		<refsDecl n="TOC">
			<state unit="chapter"/>
		</refsDecl>
		<refsDecl n="TOC">
			<state unit="authentication"/>
		</refsDecl>
		<refsDecl n="TOC">
			<state unit="appendix"/>
		</refsDecl>
		<refsDecl n="TOC">
			<state unit="Bolles Notation"/>
		</refsDecl>
		<classDecl>
		<taxonomy id="LCSH"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy>
		<taxonomy id="LC"><bibl><title>Library of Congress</title></bibl></taxonomy>
		</classDecl>
	</encodingDesc>

	<profileDesc>
		<creation><date>2000-01-01</date></creation>
		<langUsage><language id="EN" usage="100">English.</language></langUsage>

		<textClass>
			<keywords scheme="LCSH">
			<list>
			<item>Medicine.</item>
			</list>
			</keywords>
			<classCode scheme='LC'>DA 396.A22</classCode>
		</textClass>
	</profileDesc>

	<revisionDesc>
		<change><date>2004-08-24</date><respStmt><name>Cynthia Mackey</name><resp>admin.</resp></respStmt><item>Updated text to TEI P4 XML. Added Tufts Digital Library object identifiers for figures.</item></change>
	</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>


<text>
<front>
	<titlePage>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart type="main">Essays and Orations,
			<lb/>Read and Delivered
			<lb/>at
			<lb/>The Royal College of Physicians;</titlePart>
			<titlePart type="desc">to which is added
			<lb/>An Account of the Opening of the
			<lb/>Tomb of King Charles I.</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
			<byline>BY
			<lb/><docAuthor>Sir Henry Halford, Bart., M.D., G.C.H.,</docAuthor>
			<lb/>President of the College</byline>
		<docEdition>Second Edition</docEdition>
		<docImprint>
			<pubPlace>London:</pubPlace>
			<publisher>John Murray</publisher><address><addrLine>Albermarle Street</addrLine></address>
			<docDate>1833</docDate>
		</docImprint>
		</titlePage>
				
<pb id="iii" n="iii"/>

<div1 type="preface" n="PREFACE" id="front001">

<head>PREFACE.</head>



<p>OF the following small collection of Papers,
the two first were written for a work called
<quote>'The Transactions of the <orgName key="ROYAL COLLEGE OF PHYSICIANS">Royal College of
Physicians</orgName>,'</quote> and were published in the fourth
and fifth volumes of the series. The third
was meant for the same work, but it was
read at an evening meeting of the <orgName key="ROYAL COLLEGE OF PHYSICIANS">College</orgName>,
which was attended by many eminent characters in the church and in the law, as well
as a numerous body of the profession.</p>
  <p>The subsequent ones were written expressly for a mixed audience, to whom it was
probable that a strictly professional paper
would be less acceptable than one on a


<pb id="iv" n="iv"/>



medical subject capable of being illustrated
by literature, (a common bond of connexion
of all the liberal professions,) or which admitted of a discussion of the duties and
offices of a physician in that last scene of
human life in which every man, sooner or
later, must appear and bear his part. The
conduct of a physician on whom is fixed the
only hope of saving life, and on whom the
dying look often rests before the eye is
closed for ever, may fairly be thought
interesting to every hearer.</p>
  <p>Papers so addressed to an audience have
something of a rhetorical character about
them, and approach the nature of the Latin
Orations which follow. The first of these
was given many years ago in commemoration
of the Benefactors and eminent Physicians

<pb id="v" n="v"/>

of the College; the second on occasion
of opening the new building, in <date value="1825">1825</date>.
The account of what appeared on opening
the Coffin of <persName key="Charles I">King Charles I</persName>. is a reprint
of a former paper, and the drawing which
accompanies it is a faithful representation
of the countenance of the King at that time,
(<date value="1813">1813</date>.)</p>



</div1>
</front>
<body>
<pb id="p.i"  n="i"/>


<div1 type="abstract" n="To the Reader" id="front002">

       <head type="sub">AN ACCOUNT

           OF WHAT APPEARED ON

         OPENING THE COFFIN

                 OF


<persName key="Charles I.">KING CHARLES THE FIRST</persName>,

     IN THE VAULT OF <persName key="Henry VIII.">King Henry VIII.</persName>

                IN

  <placeName key="ST. GEORGE'S CHAPEL">ST. GEORGE'S CHAPEL</placeName>, <placeName key="WINDSOR">WINDSOR</placeName>,

      ON THE <date value="1813-04-01">FIRST OF APRIL, MDCCCXIII</date>.</head>




<pb id="p.ii"  n="ii"/>


               <p><hi rend="cl">TO THE READER</hi>.</p>

<p>THE following narrative of the investigation, which
took place at <placeName key="Windsor">Windsor</placeName>, on Thursday the <date value="1813-04-01">1st of April,
1813</date>, in the vault of <persName key="Henry VIII.">King Henry VIII.</persName>, will probably
be rendered more satisfactory by a comparison with
the statements of <persName key="Hyde,Edward">Lord Clarendon</persName> and <persName key="Herbert">Mr. Herbert</persName>,
with respect to the interment of <persName key="Charles I.">King Charles I.</persName>
  For the convenience of the reader, therefore, those
narratives are here reprinted, as an appendix.</p>

</div1>
<pb id="p.iii"  n="iii"/>

<div1 type="chapter" n="Opening the Coffin of King Charles I" id="c1">



<head type="sub">OPENING THE COFFIN OF KING CHARLES I.</head>

<p><figure id="fig.01" n="tufts:central:dca:MS004:MS004.002.028.DO01.00001"><head>Sir Henry Halford, Bart. G.C.H.</head></figure><hi rend="cl">IT</hi> is stated by <persName key="Hyde,Edward">Lord Clarendon</persName>, in his History of the Rebellion, that the body of <persName key="Charles I.">King
Charles I.</persName>, though known to be interred in
<placeName key="St. George's Chapel">St. George's Chapel</placeName>, at <placeName key="Windsor">Windsor</placeName>, could not
be found, when searched for there some
years afterwards. It seems, by the historian's account, to have been the wish and
the intention of <persName key="Charles II.">King Charles II.</persName>., after his
restoration, to take up his father's corpse,
and to re-inter it in <placeName key="Westminster Abbey">Westminster Abbey</placeName>,
with those royal honours which had been
denied it under the government of the regicides. The most careful search was made
for the body by several people, amongst
whom were some of those noble persons
whose faithful attachment had led them to


<pb id="p.iv"  n="iv"/>


pay their last tribute of respect to their unfortunate master by attending him to the
grave. Yet such had been the injury done
to the chapel, such were the mutilations it
had undergone, during the period of the
usurpation, that no marks were left, by which
the <hi rend="italic">exact</hi> place of burial of the king could
be ascertained.<note place="foot" n="1"><persName key="Pope,Alexander">Pope</persName>, alluding to the doubt which was entertained in
his day, as to the place of the King's interment, invokes the
Muse to
     <quote rend="blockquote">'Make sacred <persName key="Charles I.">Charles</persName>'s tomb for ever known,
     '(Obscure the place and uninscribed the stone.')</quote>
                       <hi rend="italics">Windsor Forest</hi>, v. 319.</note></p>
  <p>There is some difficulty in reconciling this
account with the information which has
reached us since the death of Lord Clarendon, particularly with that of Mr. Ashmole,
and more especially with that most interesting narrative of Mr. Herbert, given in the
<quote>'Athenae Oxonienses.'</quote>  Mr. Herbert had
been a groom of the bed-chamber, and a


<pb id="p.v"  n="v"/>

faithful companion of the king in all circumstances, from the time he left the <placeName key="Isle of Wight">Isle of Wight</placeName>,
until his death-was employed to
convey his body to <placeName key="Windsor">Windsor</placeName>, and to fix upon
a proper place for his interment there; and
was an eye-witness to that interment, in the
vault of <persName key="Henry VIII.">King Henry VIII.</persName></p>
  <p>Were it allowable to hazard a conjecture,
after <persName key="Hyde,Edward">Lord Clarendon</persName>'s deprecation of all conjectures on the subject, one might suppose
that it was deemed imprudent, by the ministers of <persName key="Charles II.">King Charles II.</persName>. that his Majesty
should indulge his pious inclination to re-inter
his father, at a period when those ill-judged
effusions of loyalty which had been manifested by taking out of their graves and
hanging up the bodies of some of the most
active members of the court which had condemned and executed the king might, in
the event of another triumph of the republicans, have subjected the body of the



<pb id="p.vi"  n="vi"/>



monarch to similar indignity.   But the fact
is, <persName key="Charles I.">King Charles I.</persName> was buried in the vault of
<persName key="Henry VIII.">King Henry VIII.</persName> situated precisely where
Mr. Herbert has described it;<note place="foot" n="2">Mr. Herbert, whose account furnished the clue to our
inquiry, retired immediately after his Majesty's death into
<placeName key="Yorkshire">Yorkshire</placeName>, and lived to the beginning of the next century.
His papers were not published till sometime after his death.
</note> and an
accident has served to elucidate a point in
history, which the great authority of
<persName key="Hyde,Edward">Lord Clarendon</persName> had involved in some obscurity.</p>
   <p>On completing the mausoleum which his
present Majesty has built in the tomb-house,
as it is called, it was necessary to form a
passage to it from under the choir of
<placeName key="St. George's Chapel">St. George's Chapel</placeName>. In constructing this passage, an aperture was made accidentally in
one of the walls of the vault of <persName key="Henry VIII.">King Henry
VIII.</persName>, through which the workmen were enabled to see, not only the two coffins which
were supposed to contain the bodies of <persName key="Henry VIII.">King
Henry VIII.</persName> and <persName key="Seymour,Jane">Queen Jane Seymour</persName>, but




<pb id="p.vii"  n="vii"/>



a third also, covered with a black velvet
pall, which, from Mr. Herbert's narrative,
might fairly be presumed to hold the remains of <persName key="Charles I.">King Charles I.</persName></p>
  <p>On representing the circumstance to <persName key="George IV.">the
Prince Regent, his Royal Highness</persName> perceived at once, that a doubtful point in history might be cleared up by opening this
vault; and accordingly <persName key="George IV.">his Royal Highness</persName>
ordered an examination to be made on the
first convenient opportunity. This was done
on the first of April last, the day after the
funeral of the Duchess of Brunswick, in the
presence of <persName key="George IV.">his Royal Highness</persName> himself, who
guaranteed thereby the most respectful care
and attention to the remains of the dead
during the inquiry. <persName key="George IV.">His Royal Highness</persName>
was accompanied by his Royal Highness
the Duke of Cumberland, Count Munster,
the Dean of <placeName key="Windsor">Windsor</placeName>, Benjamin Charles
Stevenson, Esq., and <persName key="Halford,Henry">Sir Henry Halford</persName>.</p>



<pb id="p.viii"  n="viii"/>



  <p>The vault is covered by an arch, half a
brick in thickness, is seven feet two inches
in width, nine feet six inches in length, and
four feet ten inches in height, and is situated in the centre of the choir, opposite
the eleventh knight's stall, on the sovereign's side.</p>
  <p>On removing the pall, a plain leaden coffin,
with no appearance of ever having been inclosed in wood, and bearing an inscription
<quote>'<persName key="Charles I.">KING CHARLES</persName>, <date value="1648">1648</date>,'</quote> in large, legible
characters, on a scroll of lead encircling it,
immediately presented itself to the view. A
square opening was then made in the upper
part of the lid, of such dimensions as to admit a clear insight into its contents. These
were, an internal wooden coffin, very much
decayed, and the body carefully wrapped
up in cere-cloth, into the folds of which
a quantity of unctuous or greasy matter
mixed with resin, as it seemed, had been

<figure id="fig.02"  n="tufts:central:dca:MS004:MS004.002.028.DO01.00002"><head>His Royal Highness, George, Prince of Wales, Regent of the United Kingdom</head></figure>

<pb id="p.ix"  n="ix"/>



melted, so as to exclude, as effectually as
possible, the external air. The coffin was
completely full; and from the tenacity of
the cere-cloth, great difficulty was experienced in detaching it successfully from
the parts which it enveloped. Wherever
the unctuous matter had insinuated itself,
the separation of the cere-cloth was easy;
and when it came off, a correct impression of
the features to which it had been applied
was observed in the unctuous substance. At
length, the whole face was disengaged from
its covering. The complexion of the skin
of it was dark and discoloured. The forehead and temples had lost little or nothing
of their muscular substance; the cartilage
of the nose was gone; but the left eye, in
the first moment of exposure, was open and
full, though it vanished almost immediately :
and the pointed beard, so characteristic of
the period of the reign of <persName key="Charles I.">King Charles</persName>, was


<pb id="p.x"  n="x"/>


perfect. The shape of the face was a long
oval; many of the teeth remained; and the
left ear, in consequence of the interposition
of the unctuous matter between it and the
cere-cloth, was found entire.</p>
  <p>It was difficult, at this moment, to withhold a declaration, that, notwithstanding
its disfigurement, the countenance did bear
a strong resemblance to the coins, the busts,
and especially to the pictures of <persName key="Charles I.">King
Charles I.</persName> by <persName key="Vandyke,Peter">Vandyke</persName>, by which it had
been made familiar to us. It is true, that
the minds of the spectators of this interesting sight were well prepared to receive this
impression; but it is also certain, that such
a facility of belief had been occasioned by
the simplicity and truth of Mr. Herbert's
Narrative, every part of which had been
confirmed by the investigation, so far as it
had advanced: and it will not be denied
that the shape of the face, the forehead, and
<figure id="fig.03"  n="tufts:central:dca:MS004:MS004.002.028.DO01.00003"><head>Charles the I King of Gr. Britain, France, &#x0026; Ireland, &#x0026;c.</head></figure>

<pb id="p.xi"  n="xi"/>



eye, and the beard, are the most important
features by which resemblance is determined.</p>
   <p>When the head had been entirely disengaged from the attachments which confined
it, it was found to be loose, and, without
any difficulty, was taken up and held to
view.  It was quite wet,<note place="foot" n="3">I
have not asserted this liquid to be blood, because I
had not an opportunity of being sure that it was so, and I
wished to record facts only, and not opinions: I believe it,
however, to have been blood, in which the head rested. It
gave to writing paper, and to a white handkerchief, such a
colour as blood which has been kept for a length of time
generally leaves behind it. Nobody present had a doubt of
its being blood; and it appears from Mr. Herbert's narrative, that the King was embalmed immediately after decapitation. It is probable, therefore, that the large blood
vessels continued to empty themselves for some time afterwards. I am aware, that some of the softer parts of the
human body, and particularly the brain, undergo, in the
course of time, a decomposition, and will melt. A liquid,
therefore, might be found after long interment, where solids
only had been buried: but the weight of the head, in this
instance, gave no suspicion that the brain had lost its substance; and no moisture appeared in any other part of the
coffin, as far as we could see, excepting at the back part of
the head and neck.</note> and gave a



<pb id="p.xii"  n="xii"/>

greenish red tinge to paper and to linen
which touched it. The back part of the
scalp was entirely perfect, and had a remarkably fresh appearance; the pores of the
skin being more distinct, as they usually are
when soaked in moisture; and the tendons
and ligaments of the neck were of considerable substance and firmness. The hair was
thick at the back part of the head, and, in
appearance, nearly black. A portion of it,
which has since been cleaned and dried,
is of a beautiful dark brown colour. That
of the beard was a redder brown. On the
back part of the head it was more than an
inch in length, and had probably been cut
so short for the convenience of the executioner, or perhaps by the piety of friends
soon after death, in order to furnish memorials of the unhappy king.</p>
  <p>On holding up the head, to examine the
place of separation from the body, the

<pb id="p.xiii"  n="xiii"/>



muscles of the neck had evidently retracted
themselves considerably; and the fourth cervical vertebra was found to be cut through
its substance transversely, leaving the surfaces of the divided portions perfectly smooth
and even, an appearance which could have
been produced only by a heavy blow, inflicted
with a very sharp instrument, and
which furnished the last proof wanting to
identify <persName key="Charles I">King Charles the First</persName>.</p>

<p><figure id="fig.04" n="tufts:central:dca:MS004:MS004.002.028.DO01.00004"><head>Charles the First</head></figure></p>

  <p>After this examination of the head, which
served every purpose in view, and without
examining the body below the neck, it was
immediately restored to its situation, the
coffin was soldered up again, and the vault
closed.</p>
  <p>Neither of the other coffins had any inscription upon them. The larger one, supposed on good grounds to contain the remains of <persName key="Henry VIII.">King Henry VIII.</persName> measured six
feet ten inches in length, and had been


<pb id="p.xiv "  n=" xiv"/>



inclosed in an elm one of two inches in thickness: but this was decayed, and lay in small
fragments near it. The leaden coffin appeared to have been beaten in by violence
about the middle; and a considerable opening in that part of it exposed a mere skeleton of the king.  Some beard remained
upon the chin, but there was nothing to
discriminate the personage contained in it.</p>
  <p>The smaller coffin, understood to be that
of <persName key="Seymour,Jane">Queen Jane Seymour</persName>, was not touched;
mere curiosity not being considered, by the
<persName key="George IV.">Prince Regent</persName>, as a sufficient motive for
disturbing these remains.</p>
  <p>On examining the vault with some attention, it was found that the wall, at the west
end, had, at some period or other, been partly
pulled down and repaired again, not by regular masonry, but by fragments of stones
and bricks, put rudely and hastily together
without cement.</p>


          <pb id="p.xv"  n="xv"/>

  <p>From <persName key="Hyde,Edward">Lord Clarendon</persName>'s account, as well
as from Mr. Herbert's narrative of the interment of <persName key="Charles I">King Charles</persName>, it is to be inferred,
that the ceremony was a very hasty one,
performed in the presence of the Governor,
who had refused to allow the service according to the Book of Common Prayer to be
used on the occasion; and had, probably,
scarcely admitted the time necessary for a
decent deposit of the body. It is not unlikely, therefore, that the coffin of
<persName key="Henry VIII.">King Henry VIII.</persName> had been injured by a precipitate introduction of the coffin of King
Charles; and that the Governor was not
under the influence of feelings, in those
times, which gave him any concern about
Royal remains, or the vault which contained
them.</p>
  <p>It may be right to add, that a very small
mahogany coffin, covered with crimson velvet, containing the body of an infant, had

<pb id="p.xvi"  n="xvi "/>



been laid upon the pall which covered King
Charles.  This is known to have been a
still-born child of Princess George of
Denmark, afterwards Queen Anne.



LONDON, APRIL 11, <date value="1813">1813</date>.</p>

</div1>
<pb id="p.xvii"  n="xviii"/>
<div1 type="chapter" n="authentication" id="c2">
          <head>AUTHENTICATION.</head>

<p>WHEN the manuscript containing the above account was read to his late Majesty, then Prince
Regent, by whose command it had been drawn up,
the King was pleased to desire that He might
authenticate it, which He did, immediately previous to its being deposited in the British Museum,
by the accompanying autograph.</p>
<p><figure id="fig.05"  n="tufts:central:dca:MS004:MS004.002.028.DO01.00005"><head>Authentication</head></figure></p>


</div1>
</body>
<back>
<pb id="p.xix" n="xix"/>
<div1 type="appendix" n="APPENDIX I" id="back001">


<head>APPENDIX I.</head>

<p><figure id="fig.06" n="tufts:central:dca:MS004:MS004.002.028.DO01.00006"><head>Edward Earle of Clarendon, Lord High Chancellor of England and Chancellor of the University of Oxford</head></figure></p>

<p>[Extract from <persName key="Hyde,Edward">Clarendon</persName>'s 'History of the Rebellion and
  Civil Wars in England,' Vol. iii. Part I. p. 393, Oxford,
  <date value="1807">1807</date>.]</p>


<p> His body was immediately carried into a room at
 Whitehall; where he was exposed for many days
 to the public view, that all men might know that
 he was not alive. And he was then embalmed,
 and put into a coffin, and so carried to <placeName key="St. James's">St. James's</placeName>;
 where he likewise remained several days. They
 who were qualified to order his funeral declared,
 <q type="spoken">that he should be buried at <placeName key="Windsor">Windsor</placeName> in a decent
 manner, provided that the whole expense should
 not exceed five hundred pounds.</q> The Duke of
 Richmond, the Marquis of Hertford, the Earls of
 Southampton and Lindsey, who had been of his
 bed-chamber, and always very faithful to him,
 desired those who governed, <q type="spoken">that they might
 have leave to perform the last duty to their dead
 master, and to wait upon him to his grave;</q> which,
 after some pauses, they were permitted to do;


<pb id="p.xx "  n="xx "/>




 with this, "that they should not attend the corpse
 out of town; since they resolved it should be
 privately carried to <placeName key="Windsor">Windsor</placeName> without pomp or
 noise, and then they should have timely notice,
 that, if they pleased, they might be at his interment."  And accordingly it was committed to four
 of those servants who had been by them appointed
 to wait upon him during his imprisonment, that
 they should convey the body to <placeName key="Windsor">Windsor</placeName>; which
 they did.  And it was, that night, placed in that
 chamber which had usually been his bed-chamber: the next morning, it was carried into the
 great hall, where it remained till the lords came;
 who arrived there in the afternoon, and immediately went to Colonel Whitchcot, the governor of
 the castle, and showed the order they had from
 the Parliament to be present at the burial, which
 he admitted: but when they desired that his
 Majesty might be buried according to the form of
 the Common Prayer Book, the Bishop of London
 being present with them to officiate, he positively
 and roughly refused to consent to it; and said,
 "it was not lawful, that the Common Prayer
 Book was put down, and he would not suffer it to
 be used in that garrison where he commanded;"
 nor could all the reasons, persuasions, and entreaties, prevail with him to suffer it. Then they
 went into the church, to make choice of a place
 for burial. But when they entered into it, which



<pb id="p.xxi"  n="xxi"/>



 they had been so well acquainted with, they found
 it so altered and transformed, all inscriptions, and
 those landmarks pulled down, by which all men
 knew every particular place in that church, and
 such a dismal mutation over the whole, that they
 knew not where they were: nor was there one old
 officer that had belonged to it, or knew where our
 princes had used to be interred. At last, there
 was a fellow of the town who undertook to tell
 them the place where, he said, <q type="spoken">"there was a
 vault, in which <persName key="Henry VIII.">King Harry VIII.</persName> and
 <persName key="Seymour,Jane">Queen Jane Seymour</persName> were interred."</q>   As near that
 place as could conveniently be, they caused the
 grave to be made. There the King's body was
 laid, without any words, or other ceremonies than
 the tears and sighs of the few beholders. Upon
 the coffin was a plate of silver fixed, with these
 words only, <persName key="Charles I">King Charles</persName>, <date value="1648">1648</date>.  When the
 coffin was put in, the black velvet pall that had
 covered it was thrown over it, and then the earth
 thrown in; which the Governor stayed to see
 perfectly done, and then took the keys of the
 church.</p>
  <p>I have been the longer and the more particular
 in this relation, that I may from thence take
 occasion to mention what fell out long after, and which
 administered a subject of much discourse; in
 which, according to the several humours and
 fancies of men, they who were in nearest credit


<pb id="p.xxii"  n="xxii"/>




 and trust about the King underwent many very
 severe censures and reproaches, not without
 reflection upon the King himself.  Upon the return
 of <persName key="Charles II.">King Charles II.</persName>.
 with so much congratulation,
 and universal joy of the people, above ten years
 after the murder of his father, it was generally
 expected that the body should be removed from
 that obscure burial, and with such ceremony as
 should be thought fit, should be solemnly deposited with his Royal ancestors in King Harry
 the Seventh's chapel, in the collegiate church
 at Westminster.   And the King himself intended nothing more, and spoke often of it, as
 if it were only deferred till some circumstances
 and ceremonies in the doing it might be adjusted.  But, by degrees, the discourse of it
 was diminished, as if it were totally laid aside
 upon some reason of state, the ground whereof
 several men guessed at according to their fancies,
 and thereupon cast those reproaches upon the
 statesmen as they thought reasonable, when the
 reasons which were suggested by their own imaginations did not satisfy their understanding.
 For the satisfaction and information of all men, I
 choose in this place to explain that matter; which,
 it may be, is not known to many; and at that
 time was not, for many reasons, thought fit to be
 published. The Duke of Richmond was dead
 before the King returned; the Marquis of Hertford


<pb id="p.xxiii "  n=" xxiii"/>



 died in a short time after, and was seldom out
 of his lodging after his Majesty came to <placeName key="Whitehall">Whitehall</placeName>:
 the Earl of Southampton and the Earl of
 Lindsey went to <placeName key="Windsor">Windsor</placeName>, and took with them such
 of their own servants as had attended them in that
 service, and as many others as they remembered
 had been then present, and were still alive; who all
 amounted to a small number; there being, at the
 time of the interment, great strictness used in
 admitting any to be present whose names were
 not included in the order which the lords had
 brought. In a word, the confusion they had at
 that time observed to be in that church, and the
 small alterations which were begun to be made
 towards decency, so totally perplexed their memories,
 that they could not satisfy themselves in
 what place or part of the church the Royal body
 was interred: yet where any concurred upon this
 or that place, they caused the ground to be
 opened at a good distance, and, upon such
 enquiries, found no cause to believe that they were
 near the place: and, upon their giving this account
 to the King, the thought of that remove was laid
 aside; and the reason communicated to very few,
 for the better discountenancing further enquiry.'</p>

<pb id="p.xxiv "  n=" xxiv"/>
<p>
<figure id="fig.07"  n="tufts:central:dca:MS004:MS004.002.028.DO01.00007"><head>K. Charles, 1st, Martyred</head></figure></p>
</div1>
<pb id="p.xxv"  n="xxv"/>
<div1 type="appendix" n="APPENDIX II" id="back002">

             <head>APPENDIX II.</head>

<p>[Extract from <persName key="Wood,Anthony">Wood</persName>'s 'Athenae Oxonienses,' folio edition.
  Vol. ii. p. 703. Printed for Knaplock, Midwinter, and
  Tonson, <date value="1721">1721</date>.</p>

 <p>THERE was a passage broke through the wall
 of the Banqueting-house, by which the King
 passed unto the scaffold: where, after his Majesty
 had spoken, and declared publicly that he died a
 Christian according to the profession of the Church
 of England (the contents of which have been
 several times printed), the fatal stroke was given
 by a disguised person.  Mr. Herbert during this
 time was at the door leading to the scaffold, much
 lamenting; and the Bishop coming from the
 scaffold with the Royal corpse, which was
 immediately coffined and covered with a velvet pall, he
 and Mr. Herbert went with it to the back stairs
 to have it embalmed. The Royal corpse being
 embalmed and well coffined, and all afterwards
 wrapped up in lead, and covered with a new
 velvet pall, it was removed to <placeName key="St. James's">St. James's</placeName>. Where
 to bury the King was the last duty remaining.
 By some historians it is said the King spoke


<pb id="p.xxvi"  n="xxvi"/>


something to the bishop concerning his burial.
Mr. Herbert, both before and after the King's
death, was frequently in company with the bishop,
and affirmed, that he never mentioned anything to
him of the King's naming any place where he
would be buried; nor did Mr. Herbert (who
constantly attended his Majesty, and after his coming
to Hurst Castle was the only person in his bedchamber)
hear him at any time declare his mind
concerning it. Nor was it in his lifetime a
proper question for either of them  to ask,
notwithstanding they had oftentimes the opportunity,
especially when his Majesty was bequeathing to
his royal children and friends what is formerly
related. Nor did the bishop declare any thing
concerning the place to Mr. Herbert, which
doubtless he would upon Mr. Herbert's pious care about
it; which being duly considered, they thought no
place more fit to inter the corpse than in the
chapel of <persName key="Henry VII.">King Henry VII.</persName>, at the end of the
church of <placeName key="Westminster Abbey">Westminster Abbey</placeName>, out of whose loins
<persName key="Charles I.">King Charles I.</persName> was lineally extracted, &#x0026;c.
Whereupon Mr. Herbert made his application to
such as were then in power for leave to bury the
King's body in the said chapel, among his ancestors; but his request was denied, for this reason, that his burying there would attract infinite
numbers of all sorts thither, to see where the
King was buried; which, as the times then were,



<pb id="p.xxvii "  n=" xxvii"/>



was judged unsafe and inconvenient.  Mr. Herbert
acquainting the bishop with this, they then
resolved to bury the King's body in the
Royal Chapel of <placeName key="St. George">St. George</placeName>,
within the Castle of <placeName key="Windsor">Windsor</placeName>,
both in regard that his Majesty was Sovereign of
the Most Noble Order of the Garter, and that
several Kings had been there interred; namely,
<persName key="Henry VI.">King Henry VI.</persName>, <persName key="Edward IV.">King Edward IV.</persName>, and
<persName key="Henry VIII.">King Henry VIII.</persName>, &#x0026;c.  Upon which consideration
Mr. Herbert made his second address to the
committee of Parliament, who, after some deliberation, gave him an order, bearing date the 6th
of February, <date value="1648">1648</date>, authorising him and Mr.
<persName key="Mildmay,Anthony">Anthony Mildmay</persName> to bury the King's body there,
which the governor was to observe.</p>
  <p>Accordingly the corpse was carried thither front
<placeName key="St. James's">St. James's</placeName>, February 7, in a hearse covered with
black velvet, drawn by six horses covered with
black cloth, in which were about a dozen gentlemen,
most of them being such that had waited upon
his Majesty at <placeName key="Carisbrook Castle">Carisbrook Castle</placeName>, and other places,
since his Majesty's going from <placeName key="Newcastle">Newcastle</placeName>. Mr.
Herbert shewed the governor, Colonel Whitchcot,
the committee's order for permitting Mr. Herbert
and <persName key="Mildmay,Anthony">Mr. Mildmay</persName> to bury him, the late King, in
any place within <placeName key="Windsor Castle">Windsor Castle</placeName>, that they should
think fit and meet. In the first place, in order
thereunto, they carried the King's body into the
Dean's house, which was hung with black, and



<pb id="p.xxviii"  n="xxviii"/>


after to his usual bedchamber within the palace.
After which they went to <placeName key="St. George's Chapel">St. George's Chapel</placeName> to
take a view thereof, and of the most fit and
honourable place for the Royal corpse to rest in.
Having taken a view, they at first thought that
the tomb-house, built by <persName key="Wolsey,Thomas">Cardinal Wolsey</persName>, would
be a fit place for his interment; but that place,
though adjoining, yet being not within the Royal
Chapel, they waived it; for, if <persName key="Henry VIII.">King Henry VIII.</persName>
was buried there, (albeit to that day the particular place of his burial was unknown to any,) yet,
in regard to his Majesty, <persName key="Charles I.">King Charles I.</persName> (who
was a real defender of the Faith, and as far from
censuring any that might be) would upon occasional discourse express some dislike in
<persName key="Henry VIII.">King Henry</persName>'s proceedings, in misemploying those vast
revenues, the suppressed abbies, monasteries, and
other religious houses were endowed with, and by
demolishing those many beautiful and stately
structures which both expressed the greatness of
their founders, and preserved the splendour of the
kingdom, which might at the Reformation have in
some measure been kept up and converted to sundry pious uses.</p>
  <p>Upon consideration thereof, those gentlemen
declined it, and pitched upon the vault where <persName key="Edward IV.">King
Edward IV.</persName> had been interred, being on the north
side of the choir, near the altar, that King being
one his late Majesty would often times make honourable




<pb id="p.xxix"  n="xxix"/>



mention of, and from whom his Majesty
was lineally propagated. That, therefore, induced
Mr. Herbert to give order to N. Harrison and
Henry Jackson to have that vault opened, partly
covered with a fair large stone of touch, raised
within the arch adjoining, having a range of iron
bars gilt, curiously cut according to church work,
&#x0026;c. But as they were about this work, some noblemen came thither; namely, the Duke of Richmond,
the Marquis of Hertford, the Earl of Lindsey,
and with them Dr. Juxon, Bishop of London,
who had licence from the Parliament to attend the
King's body to his grave. Those gentlemen,
therefore, Herbert and <persName key="Mildmay,Anthony">Mildmay</persName>, thinking fit to
submit, and leave the choice of the place of burial
to those great persons, they in like manner viewed
the tomb-house and the choir; and one of the
Lords beating gently upon the pavement with his
staff, perceived a hollow sound; and thereupon
ordering the stones and earth to be removed, they
discovered a descent into a vault, where two coffins
were laid near one another, the one very large, of
an antique form, and the other little. These they
supposed to be the bodies of <persName key="Henry VIII.">King Henry VIII.</persName>
and <persName key="Seymour,Jane">Queen Jane Seymour</persName> his third wife, as indeed
they were. The velvet palls that covered their
coffins seemed fresh, though they had lain there
above one hundred years.</p>
  <p>The Lords agreeing that the King's body


<pb id="p.xxx"  n="xxx"/>


should be in the same vault interred, being about
the middle of the choir, over against the eleventh
stall upon the sovereign's side, they gave order to
have the King's name and year he died cut in
lead; which whilst the workmen were about, the
Lords went out and gave Puddifant, the sexton,
order to lock the chapel door, and not suffer any
to stay therein till further notice. The sexton did
his best to clear the chapel; nevertheless, Isaac,
the sexton's man, said that a foot-soldier had hid
himself, so as he was not discerned; and being
greedy of prey, crept into the vault, and cut so
much of the velvet pall that covered the great body
as he judged would hardly be missed, and wimbled
also a hole through the said coffin that was largest,
probably fancying that there was semething well
worth his adventure. The sexton at his opening
the door espied the sacrilegious person; who
being searched, a bone was found about him, with
which he said he would haft a knife. The Governor
being therefore informed of, he gave him
his reward; and the Lords and others present
were convinced that a real body was in the said
great coffin, which some before had scrupled.
The girdle or circumscription, of capital letters of
lead put about the King's coffin, had only these
words: <persName key="Charles I."><hi rend="italic">King Charles</hi></persName>, <date value="1648">1648</date>.</p>
   <p>The <persName key="Charles I.">King</persName>'s body was then brought from his
bedchamber down into <placeName key="St. George's Hall">St. George's Hall</placeName>, whence,


<pb id="p.xxxi"  n="xxxi"/>



after a little stay, it was with a slow and solemn
pace (much sorrow in most faces being then
discernible) carried by gentlemen of quality in mourning.
The noblemen in mourning also held up the
pall; and the governor, with several gentlemen,
officers and attendants, came after. It was then
observed, that at such time as the King's body
was brought out from <placeName key="St. George's Hall">St. George's Hall</placeName>, the sky
was serene and clear; but presently it began to
snow, and the snow fell so fast, that by that time
the corpse came to the west end of the Royal
chapel, the black velvet pall was all white (the
colour of innocency), being thick covered over with
snow. The body being by the bearers set down
near the place of burial, the Bishop of London
stood ready, with the service-book in his hands, to
have performed his last duty to the King his
master, according to the order and form of burial
of the dead set forth in the Book of Common
Prayer; which the Lords likewise desired; but it
would not be suffered by Colonel Whitchcot, the
governor of the castle, by reason of the <hi rend="italic">Directory to
which</hi> (said he) <hi rend="italic">he and
others were to be conformable</hi>. Thus went the
<hi rend="italic">white <persName key="Charles I.">King</persName></hi> to his grave, in
the forty-eighth year of his age, and twenty-second
year and tenth month of his reign.'</p>

</div1>
<pb n="xxxii"/>
<div1 type="appendix" n="Bolles Notation" id="back003">
<head>Bolles Notation</head>
<p><figure id="fig.08" n="tufts:central:dca:MS004:MS004.002.028.DO01.00008"><head>Bolles Notation</head></figure></p>
  <p>In the royal vault, in the choir, which is near the eleventh stall, on
the Sovereign's side, are the remains of <persName key="Henry VIII.">Henry VIII.</persName>., and his queen
 <persName key="Seymour,Jane">Lady Jane Seymour</persName>, <persName key="Charles I.">Charles I.</persName> and an infant daughter of Queen
Anne. Upon opening the vault for the interment of the latter, the
coffins containing the remains of these royal personages were discovered,
but no further research was made till <date value="1813">1813</date>,
when <persName key="George IV">George IV</persName>.,
then Prince Regent, determined that an investigation should be
made--the place of interment of <persName key="Charles I.">Charles I.</persName>, being involved in considerable
doubt. The vault was consequently opened in the presence of his
Royal Highness and several other individuals, when the correctness of
the surmise was clearly proved, the head and body being found in a
plain leaden shell. The coffin of <persName key="Henry VIII.">Henry VIII.</persName>., contained only the
skeleton of that monarch; and as no additional historical facts were
attainable by inspecting that of his consort, the vault was then closed.</p>

<p> From "<placeName key="Windsor">Windsor</placeName> Guide."</p>




</div1>
</back>
</text>
</TEI.2>
